<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;9 Devotion as Possession on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/3_Classical_Literature/9_Devotion_as_Possession/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;9 Devotion as Possession on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/3_Classical_Literature/9_Devotion_as_Possession/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 Devotional Possession in the Gītā and Ānandavardhana</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/3_Classical_Literature/9_Devotion_as_Possession/01_Devotional_Possession_in_the_GItA_and_Anandavardhana/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/3_Classical_Literature/9_Devotion_as_Possession/01_Devotional_Possession_in_the_GItA_and_Anandavardhana/</guid>
      <description>Indian devotional (bhakti) literature is one of the most prominent genres for discussion of āveśa and allied notions of divine or oracular possession. Vallabhācārya (1479–1531) provides an epitome of this in his commentary on the Bhāgavata-Purāṇa (BhP 10.27.24),1 entitled “Subodhinī.” Vallabhācārya writes: bhagavadāveśo hi sarvajñatā bhavati (one who is in a state of divine possession becomes omniscient). Bhakti literature is also the most prominent locus for discussion of the aesthetics of possession, a topic that Vallabhācārya and his followers, as well as the Vaiṣṇava disciples of Śrī Caitanya, take up in full.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>02 Vallabhācārya’s Concept of Āveśa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/3_Classical_Literature/9_Devotion_as_Possession/02_VallabhAcAryas_Concept_of_Avesha/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/3_Classical_Literature/9_Devotion_as_Possession/02_VallabhAcAryas_Concept_of_Avesha/</guid>
      <description>Vallabhācārya mentions āveśa in several brief works. His Nirodhalakṣaṇa,9 a text of twenty verses describing the symptoms (lakṣaṇa) of the highest devotional state (nirodha), contains the following verses: “Indeed, for the benefit of those whose senses have become defiled as a result of immersion in the world [saṃsārāveśa], [I declare that as a general principle] one should connect all the [sense] objects with Kṛṣṇa, the underlying omnipotent Lord. Worldly pain or separation cannot exist for those whose minds are always immersed in [āviṣṭa] the attributes of the destroyer of the demon Mura [viz.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>03 Śrī Caitanya and the Gauḍīya Concepts of Āveśa, Avatāra, and Multiple Bodies</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/3_Classical_Literature/9_Devotion_as_Possession/03_shrI_Caitanya_and_the_GauDIya_Concepts_of_Avesha_AvatAra_and_Multiple_Bodies/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/3_Classical_Literature/9_Devotion_as_Possession/03_shrI_Caitanya_and_the_GauDIya_Concepts_of_Avesha_AvatAra_and_Multiple_Bodies/</guid>
      <description>The material on āveśa in the Gauḍīya (Bengali) tradition of Kṛṣṇa bhakti is equally rich and is consistent with these findings. I shall briefly examine a few passages from the works of Jīva and Rūpa Gosvāmī, the two greatest disciples and successors of Śrī Caitanya (1486–1533). One of the important and unique uses of āveśa in this tradition, explicated by Rūpa, occurs in the term āveśāvatāra. Avatāras may be either full or partial “descents” or appearances of the Lord in the world, manifested for the purpose of performing a specific action or series of actions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>04 Āveśa and Bhāva</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/3_Classical_Literature/9_Devotion_as_Possession/04_Avesha_and_BhAva/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/3_Classical_Literature/9_Devotion_as_Possession/04_Avesha_and_BhAva/</guid>
      <description>In view of these accounts of possession in the performances of the Kṛṣṇa and Rām līlās, can we ask whether the equivalent of “dramatic possession” is found in Sanskrit theater? The answer appears to be a qualified “yes.” We should be careful, however, not to confuse possession with other altered states. For example, in Kalidasa’s rendition of the tale of Purūravas and Urvaśī, Purūravas wanders about in a state of madness born of extreme longing for his beloved Urvaśī, who had disappeared in a sage’s garden (Vikramorvaśīya, Act 4).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>05 Āveśa, Bhāva, and Alternative Vedāntas</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/3_Classical_Literature/9_Devotion_as_Possession/05_Avesha_BhAva_and_Alternative_VedAntas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/3_Classical_Literature/9_Devotion_as_Possession/05_Avesha_BhAva_and_Alternative_VedAntas/</guid>
      <description>In this connection, it is relevant to reprise an observation by A. K. Ramanujan on Nammāḻvār, the great Tamil saint whose poetry predates by several centuries the works of Vallabhācārya and Rūpa Gosvāmī. Nammāḻvār “speaks frequently of being entered, filled, taken over, enslaved as well as enabled by a divine being,”48 characteristics of possession found in contemporary ethnographies. Although Nammāḻvār wrote in Tamil, this description could be extended to many Sanskrit authors.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>06 NOTES</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/3_Classical_Literature/9_Devotion_as_Possession/06_NOTES/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/3_Classical_Literature/9_Devotion_as_Possession/06_NOTES/</guid>
      <description>Vallabhācārya’s enumeration of the chapters differs from that of most standard editions. This corresponds to BhP 10.30.24 in the text used in other sectarian traditions. Cf. BhG 8.5, 12.7; also F. Smith 1998b. Cf. BhG 1.28 kṛpayā parayāviṣṭho (filled with supreme tenderness); also 2.1; but 8.10c: bhruvor madhye prāṇam āveśya samyak (having properly focused the prāṇa between the eyebrows). Trans. Ingalls et al. 1990:653. tvam eva paramātmasvarūpo viśvasāras tasya bhaktiḥ śraddhādipūrvaka upāsanākramajas tadāveśas tena tulyam api na labdham āstāṃ tāvat tajjātīyam; see also Ingalls et al.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
