<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;Labeling on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/labeling/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;Labeling on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/labeling/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>(A)theism/ (a)dEvism?</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/labeling/atheism/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/labeling/atheism/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The English word God may to a hindu mean either a deity (&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Deva_%28Hinduism%29&#34;&gt;dEvatA&lt;/a&gt;) or that which pervades everything (&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brahman&#34;&gt;brahman&lt;/a&gt;) (both of which are distinct from the Abrahamist notion of a true God). This leads to confusion while talking to Hindus. Hindu-s have a stronger need (because of unique conditioning) for distinguishing deva from brahman compared to say Egyptians or Japanese. So, their tendency to take God to mean brahman is quite understandable.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Henotheism</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/labeling/henotheism/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/labeling/henotheism/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;intro&#34;&gt;Intro&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;In henotheism, one reveres a single god as the only one in a given hymn and the others are at that time ignored.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;For relationship with monotheism and polytheism, see &lt;a href=&#34;../polytheism/&#34;&gt;polytheism&lt;/a&gt; page.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;in-hinduism&#34;&gt;In Hinduism&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;In the Veda, however, the gods worshipped as supreme by each sect stand still side by side. No one is first always, no one is last always. Even gods of a decidedly inferior and limited character assume occasionally in the eyes of a devoted poet a supreme place above all other gods. It was necessary, therefore, for the purpose of accurate reasoning to have a name, different from polytheism, to signify this worship of single gods, each occupying for a time a supreme position, and I proposed for it the name of Kaihenotheism, that is a worship of one god after another, or of Henotheism, the worship of single gods.&amp;rdquo; [&lt;a href=&#34;https://books.google.com/books?id=DLQIAAAAQAAJ&amp;amp;dq=kulluka%20bhatta%20garga&amp;amp;pg=PA76#v=onepage&amp;amp;q=henotheism&amp;amp;f=false&#34;&gt;MM&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Polytheism</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/labeling/polytheism/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/labeling/polytheism/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;polytheism-vs-monotheism-definitions&#34;&gt;Polytheism vs Monotheism: Definitions&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;broader-definition-reducibility-to-unity&#34;&gt;Broader definition: Reducibility to unity&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Polytheism is: &amp;ldquo;Any theological account in which the divine is not reducible to unity, but rather intrinsically plural.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;examination&#34;&gt;Examination&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Would the concept of the Trinity be an example of Divinity being intrinsically and irreducibly plural? Christians claim it is not (three persons, one substance).&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;position-of-henotheism&#34;&gt;Position of henotheism&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;See &lt;a href=&#34;../henotheism/&#34;&gt;henotheism&lt;/a&gt; page for intro.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Based on whether these Gods are considered fundamentally distinct, monotheism (by the &amp;ldquo;broader&amp;rdquo; reducibility test) or polytheism can encompass henotheism.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Connection with brahman - see &lt;a href=&#34;../../hierarchy/polycentrism/&#34;&gt;polycentrism&lt;/a&gt; .&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Polytheism can be understood in terms of all Gods being inherent in &lt;em&gt;each&lt;/em&gt; God, rather than all Gods being inherent in &lt;em&gt;one&lt;/em&gt; God. Some authors use the term &amp;ldquo;polycentric polytheism&amp;rdquo; to refer to this understanding.&amp;rdquo; - Edward Butler&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;stronger-definition-aloneness-in-the-god-class&#34;&gt;Stronger definition: aloneness in the God class&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Here exactly one God can claim &amp;ldquo;God&amp;rdquo; status. There may be other divinities -but they may not be called &amp;ldquo;God&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Nowadays, very many Hindus will tell you that in essence, Hinduism is a monotheism. These Hindus are not even aware of the proper meaning of this word. Monotheism does not mean that you worship one God (already requiring a serious reinterpretation of the many Gods effectively worshipped by most Hindus, from the Vedic rishis on down), the way some Hindus choose one God to worship from among many, a phenomenon that scholars of religion call henotheism. Nor is it the inclusive oneness of a divine essence underlying all the gods, or monism, as enunciated in the profoundest Vedic verses. It means an exclusive worship of a jealous God banishing all others. Mono- does not mean “one”, as Hindus seem to think; it means “alone”, hence “not tolerating another”. It does not say: “Allah and Shiva are one”, it says: “Only Allah is true, burn Shiva.” So far, there is no such jealous God in Dharma.&amp;rdquo; [Koenraad Elst &lt;a href=&#34;http://koenraadelst.blogspot.in/2015/02/down-with-decolonization.html&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;].&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
