<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;Labeling on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/labeling/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;Labeling on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/labeling/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>(A)theism/ (a)dEvism?</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/labeling/atheism/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/labeling/atheism/</guid>
      <description>The English word God may to a hindu mean either a deity (dEvatA) or that which pervades everything (brahman) (both of which are distinct from the Abrahamist notion of a true God). This leads to confusion while talking to Hindus. Hindu-s have a stronger need (because of unique conditioning) for distinguishing deva from brahman compared to say Egyptians or Japanese. So, their tendency to take God to mean brahman is quite understandable.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Henotheism</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/labeling/henotheism/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/labeling/henotheism/</guid>
      <description>Intro In henotheism, one reveres a single god as the only one in a given hymn and the others are at that time ignored. For relationship with monotheism and polytheism, see polytheism page. In Hinduism &amp;ldquo;In the Veda, however, the gods worshipped as supreme by each sect stand still side by side. No one is first always, no one is last always. Even gods of a decidedly inferior and limited character assume occasionally in the eyes of a devoted poet a supreme place above all other gods.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Polytheism</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/labeling/polytheism/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/labeling/polytheism/</guid>
      <description>Polytheism vs Monotheism: Definitions Broader definition: Reducibility to unity Polytheism is: &amp;ldquo;Any theological account in which the divine is not reducible to unity, but rather intrinsically plural.&amp;rdquo; Examination &amp;ldquo;Would the concept of the Trinity be an example of Divinity being intrinsically and irreducibly plural? Christians claim it is not (three persons, one substance).&amp;rdquo; Position of henotheism See henotheism page for intro. Based on whether these Gods are considered fundamentally distinct, monotheism (by the &amp;ldquo;broader&amp;rdquo; reducibility test) or polytheism can encompass henotheism.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
