<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/skandaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 04 Oct 2008 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/skandaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>The wives of Mars and the Carmen Arvale</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/skandaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2008-10-04_the-wives-of-mars/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Oct 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/skandaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2008-10-04_the-wives-of-mars/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2008/10/04/the-wives-of-mars/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In our earlier discussion we had argued based on structural homologies&#xA;the marut-s of the vedic system are “para-skanda”. We speculated that&#xA;kumAra himself descends from a para-vedic Indo-Iranian system, which&#xA;contained an ancestral version of the deity, who in that system was the&#xA;homolog of the marut-s of the vedic system. This para-vedic skanda was&#xA;laterally transferred to the vedic system in the late vedic period of&#xA;India. This transfer most probably occurred by an independent&#xA;Indo-Iranian invasion from the Northwest frontiers of India, prior to&#xA;the historical Iranian invasions of the Achaemenids, Sakas and&#xA;Kushana-s. By developing this line of argument further we accepted the&#xA;possible proto-Indo-European (probably excluding Hittite) origin of the&#xA;deity. In this light we are reasonably comfortable with the homology of&#xA;Mars and the Maruts: Given that the older Italic form Mars is Mavors,&#xA;their proto-IE ancestor can be accepted as *Mawort. The only&#xA;philological problem that does bother us a little is the vR^iddhi of the&#xA;initial vowel in the Italic branch.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On to shrI-parvata</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/skandaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-11-29_on-to-shri-parvata/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Nov 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/skandaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-11-29_on-to-shri-parvata/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2006/11/29/on-to-shri-parvata/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://photos1.blogger.com/x/blogger2/6438/855/1600/251284/kumAragRiha.png&#34;&gt;&lt;figure class=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &lt;a href=&#34;https://i2.wp.com/photos1.blogger.com/x/blogger2/6438/855/320/318420/kumAragRiha.png&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;img src=&#34;https://i2.wp.com/photos1.blogger.com/x/blogger2/6438/855/320/318420/kumAragRiha.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &#xA;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The core altars of a kumAra-gR^iha. The green elements mark the fire&#xA;altars&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;He sat in the place where the first of the pieces had fallen. In his&#xA;mind’s eye h remembered the tale of the great grahanatha: “tArakAsura&#xA;the accursed enemy of the gods wore a li~Nga around his neck that&#xA;protected him from death as long as it was there. As he fought viShNu&#xA;and vIrabhadra their weapons failed on him after prolonged and fierce&#xA;duels. Finally the one born of the arrow-forest charged forth to meet&#xA;the daitya. After a prolonged duel he finally struck the daitya with his&#xA;charmed shakti, from which none escape. The shakti shattered the li~Nga&#xA;into 5 fragments and the pierced the daitya-s broad chest slaying him.&#xA;The pieces of the li~Nga fell on pR^ithivi and each became a&#xA;maha-li~Nga in which The god is worshiped.” It was near the first of&#xA;these pieces he had constructed a kumAra gR^iha. After having performed&#xA;the kha-chakra-dharaNi he offered the oblations to the bull-headed&#xA;nandikeshvara at the appropriate altar. Then he moved over to the altar&#xA;of pilipichChikA and offered seven oblations: pilipichChikA, revatI,&#xA;shakunI, ShaShThi, jAtahAriNi, mukhamaNDikA and devasenA on the&#xA;pa~nchami day. Even as the last oblation hit the fire a terrifying&#xA;graha named pariprakAsha arose, filling the air with awe that only the&#xA;masters of the mahAmantra know. He muttered the graha-stotraM was&#xA;transported to the great mound of shrI-parvata by that awful graha. Atop&#xA;shrIparvata he remained lying at night performing the complete cycle of&#xA;the kha-chakra-dhyAna. He joined the siddhaugha.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The AkhyAna of skanda-patnI</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/skandaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-10-19_the-akhyana-of-skanda-patni/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Oct 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/skandaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-10-19_the-akhyana-of-skanda-patni/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2006/10/19/the-akhyana-of-skanda-patni/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;OM hrIM ShaShaThI devyai svAhA ||&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The wandering sUta said: “Listen to the wonderous AkhyAna of&#xA;skanda-patnI that relieves unborn and young kids from troubles. In days&#xA;long past I was wandering in the fringes of the magadha, when I stumbled&#xA;into the mighty brahmin, kashyapa, the son of marIchI. I asked him to&#xA;narrate to me the tale of the wonderous exploits of skanda and his&#xA;agents.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;kashyapa said: “Listen sUta this ancient story of the great god kumAra,&#xA;the commander of the deva forces and his agents. In the ancient kalpa,&#xA;after the devas had drunk the amR^ita, the asura-s smarting due to their&#xA;outwitting sought to avenge themselves. The gods have won account of vAk&#xA;they said. We too shall strive with our vAk, declared dundubhi the lord&#xA;of the asuras. All the asuras put forth their mighty vAk simulataneously&#xA;and from the asura-vAk was born the deadly asura-kanyA, dIrgha-jihvI.&#xA;The asuras then attacked the gods and a fierce battle broke out. The&#xA;devas fought with their ranks comprised of the vasus, the rudras and&#xA;Adityas, and their commander-in-chief being the six-headed skanda. He&#xA;had with him his brothers and gaNa-s lead by shAkha, vishAkha, nejamesha&#xA;and the bull-headed nandI. At first the deva assault drove back the&#xA;asuras to pAtAla, but then they let out their secret agent-&#xA;dIrgha-jihvI. Of black color and with many strong arms and a long&#xA;lolling tongue the asura-kanyA rushed on the deva army. She started&#xA;eating up the weapons shot by the devas and licking them up with her&#xA;long tongue. Seeing their army in disarray the deva-s huddled around&#xA;their commander kumAra and asked him to aid them in battle.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>vedic mantra-s adapted for kaumAra ritual</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/skandaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-10-18_vedic-mantras-adapted-for-kaumara-ritual/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Oct 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/skandaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-10-18_vedic-mantras-adapted-for-kaumara-ritual/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2006/10/18/vedic-mantras-adapted-for-kaumara-ritual/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://photos1.blogger.com/blogger2/6438/855/1600/kumAra_mantra_vedic.0.gif&#34;&gt;&lt;figure class=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &lt;a href=&#34;https://i0.wp.com/photos1.blogger.com/blogger2/6438/855/320/kumAra_mantra_vedic.0.png&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;img src=&#34;https://i0.wp.com/photos1.blogger.com/blogger2/6438/855/320/kumAra_mantra_vedic.0.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &#xA;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;kumAram mAtA yuvatiH samubdhaM guhA bibharti na dadAti pitre |&lt;br&gt;&#xA;anIkam asya na minaj janAsaH puraH pashyanti nihitam aratau ||&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The young mother keeps the boy hidden in secret, nor gives him to the&#xA;father;&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Men see his undiminishing radiance only when he is set up on the fuel&#xA;sticks [reeds].&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the vedic context it refers to agni hidden within his “mother”: the&#xA;kindling wood block, who is hidden away from the father: the fire-drill.&#xA;He become visible only when placed on the fire-sticks in the altar. The&#xA;term aratau has been somewhat obscure to some commentators. It is a&#xA;synonym of aratni, which means a unit length (probably ell), which is a&#xA;metaphor for the samidh which might be an aratni long.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>kumAra vidyA-s</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/skandaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-10-10_kumara-vidya-s/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Oct 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/skandaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-10-10_kumara-vidya-s/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2006/10/10/kumara-vidya-s/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://photos1.blogger.com/blogger2/6438/855/1600/kumara_tryakSharI.1.png&#34;&gt;&lt;figure class=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &lt;a href=&#34;https://i2.wp.com/photos1.blogger.com/blogger2/6438/855/320/kumara_tryakSharI.1.png&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;img src=&#34;https://i2.wp.com/photos1.blogger.com/blogger2/6438/855/320/kumara_tryakSharI.1.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &#xA;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Of the mUrti-s of kumAra [Note 1] that are worshiped by the educated&#xA;kaumAra sAdhaka there are few having a special significance. The first&#xA;of these is of great import for a dvija in devoted the yAj~nIkI&#xA;perfection. It is the form known as ajArUDha. Here the great lord of the&#xA;beautiful ShaShThi is meditated upon in the bindu of the maNDala thus:&lt;br&gt;&#xA;dvimukhaM chAShTa-bahuM cha shvetaM vA shyAMa-skandharaM |&lt;br&gt;&#xA;sruvAkShamAlAM khaDgaM cha svastikaM dakShiNe kare ||&lt;br&gt;&#xA;kukkuTaM kheTakaM vajraM Ajya-pAtraM tu vAmake |&lt;br&gt;&#xA;agnihotra-vidhi devaM agni-jAta svarUpakaM ||&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The second circle</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/skandaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-05-08_the-second-circle/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 May 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/skandaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-05-08_the-second-circle/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2006/05/08/the-second-circle/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We had sought she who dwells in the midst of the kiri chakra. Our&#xA;AchArya’s AchArya the one learned in the great atharvan lore with all&#xA;its parishiShTha-s, kalpa-s brAhmaNa and upaniShads retired to live in&#xA;the most picturesque land south of lATa pradesha, with forests largely&#xA;inhabited by niShAda tribes. There on the banks of the Damanganga river&#xA;he settled down with the forest providing him the quietude and oShadhI-s&#xA;for his rites. We decided after the great battle of tIkShNa jvara to&#xA;proceed to the sylvan slopes of Damanganga to spend time in tapasya and&#xA;acquisition of the vidyAs of the goat-headed one and she who dwells in&#xA;the midst of the kiri chakra. We got into the train that bore us on the&#xA;long journey and then we used a ratha to reach the silent Ashrama on the&#xA;banks of the Damanganga to go with our acts. The setting was most&#xA;splendid. We found that path through which ShaShThinAtha and his wife&#xA;AryamekhalA had traversed the regions infested with fierce kirATas and&#xA;bhilla-s to reach the shores skirting the sahayAdrI’s. There we went to&#xA;the ancient kumAra gR^iha, we as the sun was reaching the western peg.&#xA;The pleasant breezes were blowing from the west and we sat by the&#xA;chaitya. The amaraugha of his includes rudra, himavat’s pretty daughter,&#xA;agni and ga~Nga. The mAnavaugha began with vishvAmitra and haimavatI,&#xA;passing through, brahmAskanda, through ShaShThinAtha and AryamekhalA.&#xA;From him to saMbhadra and divyamekhalA. Then the mAnavaugha split into&#xA;the ogha of the adhoretas who moved along the paschima mayUkha and&#xA;pUrNagiri pITha and ogha of the Urdhvaretas that dwelt in prAchya&#xA;mayUkha and then moved to kumAra tapovana. We joined the adhoretasas,&#xA;being of this world.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The kaumAra vidyA</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/skandaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-01-16_the-kaumara-vidya/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Jan 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/skandaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-01-16_the-kaumara-vidya/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2006/01/16/the-kaumara-vidya/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Having paid respect with to rAja bhojadeva, who stands in the line of&#xA;the teachers from ShaShThinAtha we salute the god who is in the embrace&#xA;of sUryasunuduhitR^i.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The cryptic mantra goes thus:&lt;br&gt;&#xA;vAk (holy speech) is the varman (armour)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;the karNabindvADhya (ear ornaments) go with the charama (last one)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The Fish banner flutters (mInaketana)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;salutations to kumAra.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We also worship that awful being, riding a horse or a violent elephant,&#xA;embracing pUrNA and puShkalA along with his hosts like goptR^i&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The mahA-kumAra-rahasya</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/skandaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-11-18_the-maha-kumara-rahasya/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Nov 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/skandaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-11-18_the-maha-kumara-rahasya/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2005/11/18/the-maha-kumara-rahasya/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The great rahasya of the 6-headed one goes thus:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;First there is the praNava, which encompasses the akSharas from&#xA;shrIkaNTha the father of the young god to the last of the pentads of&#xA;brahman.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;kAmarUpaM vahnyArUDhaM bindumAlinIbhuShitaM kAlabindumilitaM (the&#xA;first core bIja)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;tryashraM yoniH (the 2nd core bIja)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;tritIya [tithi] iti ichChA ( the 3rd core bIja)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;unmeSha (the 4th core bIja)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;AkAsha tattvaM cha anuttaraM (5th core bIja)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;tasyAnte viShNupriyA ( for the second time 6th core bIja)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;vahnI vAmalochanA cha binduruttara rUpaM (7th core bIja)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;tasyAnte dvitIya ShaDAkSharI iti //&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;After having strung the bIjas and combined them with the second&#xA;ShaDakShari of kumAra you get the mahAmantra. Of all the vidyAs of&#xA;kumAra it is the most difficult to grasp.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>skanda gaNas</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/skandaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-07-23_skanda-ganas/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Jul 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/skandaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-07-23_skanda-ganas/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2005/07/23/skanda-ganas/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Weighed down by the arrows showered by our foes, we call upon son of the&#xA;ranger of kailAsha. He who bears the bow in battle and showers arrows on&#xA;the dAnava horde. He who is called ugratamaa and bhImatama, who rushes&#xA;to battle with the the axe and spear, we worship him in the midst of the&#xA;six-fold maNDala. One who is dallying with sumukhi and biDAlAkShI, we&#xA;bow to him.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>kaumArI</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/skandaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-04-30_kaumari/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Apr 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/skandaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-04-30_kaumari/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2005/04/30/kaumari/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;kaumArI &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.hello.com/&#34;&gt;&lt;figure class=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &lt;a href=&#34;https://i0.wp.com/photos1.blogger.com/pbh.gif&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;img src=&#34;https://i0.wp.com/photos1.blogger.com/pbh.gif&#34; alt=&#34;Posted by Hello&#34; title=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &#xA;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://photos1.blogger.com/img/133/1300/640/kaumari2.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;figure class=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &lt;a href=&#34;https://i2.wp.com/photos1.blogger.com/img/133/1300/400/kaumari2.jpg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;img src=&#34;https://i2.wp.com/photos1.blogger.com/img/133/1300/400/kaumari2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &#xA;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ShaM namaH ShaShaTyai ca maM maM maM keki keki mahAmayUryaI svAhA&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The secret of sumukhI</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/skandaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-04-07_the-secret-of-sumukhi/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Apr 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/skandaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-04-07_the-secret-of-sumukhi/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2005/04/07/the-secret-of-sumukhi/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The great deva sanatkumAra, the son of the fiery agni, is always in the&#xA;company of his two wives: the glorious biDAlAkShi and the wonderous&#xA;sumukhI. The one who knows this rahasya and performs the invocation of&#xA;sumukhI along with the great dhUrtasvamI will be favored by them. That&#xA;glorious goddess sumukhI also called the great mahAmayUrI, engaged in&#xA;amorous dalliance with the dhUrta, is described as sulabhAgati. In the&#xA;midst of her yantra, the mate of kArttikeya is meditated as residing and&#xA;invoked with the mighty mantra (in mantra shAstra code):&lt;br&gt;&#xA;karNa ; sanayana dyuti; jarAsana svetesha ; lakShmI ; dirgha nandi ;&#xA;sadR^ik kriya ; samAdhava meSha ; karNo bhR^igu ; sendhikA tandrI ;&#xA;khidevi ma &amp;lt;svayamarupa&amp;gt; ; dIrgha viyat ; pishAchinI &amp;lt;svayamarupa&amp;gt; ;&#xA;himAdrijA ; sarginandajatritayaM.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>skanda vara</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/skandaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-03-18_skanda-vara/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Mar 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/skandaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-03-18_skanda-vara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2005/03/18/skanda-vara/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The boons offered by the deity kumAra are of great certainty, but they&#xA;be extremely perplexing and their good result may only be seen after&#xA;some ironic hardship undergone by the recepient. Hence is he known as&#xA;the roguish dhUrta, who composed the taskara vidyA by manifesting as&#xA;kanakahastin and bhAskaranandin. But even the paths to the attainment of&#xA;chaurya perfection were not straight. amba wanted to slay bhIShma for&#xA;which she received a garland from kumAra but none ever wore it. So she&#xA;had to wait till as shikhaNDin she could wear it herself and slay the&#xA;kuru warrior. Likewise, kAtyAyana could not receive the kaumAra grammar&#xA;till he found the boy who learned things on hearing only once.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The deadly foe-destroying yoga of brahmaNya deva</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/skandaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2004-09-12_the-deadly-foe-destroying-yoga-of-brahmanya-deva/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Sep 2004 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/skandaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2004-09-12_the-deadly-foe-destroying-yoga-of-brahmanya-deva/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2004/09/12/the-deadly-foe-destroying-yoga-of-brahmanya-deva/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“We pacify the six-headed being, of fiery birth, who is lost in the&#xA;embrace of the beautiful daughter of the god of the gods indra. May his&#xA;lethal darts not harm us and instead strike our foes.”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;At the heart of the kaumara tantric rite lies the great secret yoga&#xA;which destroys ones foes. The skandArchana kalpadruma and other obscure&#xA;kaumAra texts refer to this secret yoga, the configuration of the&#xA;incantation for which is normally revealed only by oral tradition.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The roguish Karttikeya and the wives of the gods</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/skandaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2004-08-02_the-roguish-karttikeya-and-the-wives-of-the-gods/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Aug 2004 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/skandaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2004-08-02_the-roguish-karttikeya-and-the-wives-of-the-gods/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2004/08/02/the-roguish-karttikeya-and-the-wives-of-the-gods/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We worship the roguish deity kumAra with offerings as ordained by the&#xA;school of the great sage gopatha.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Due to the efficiency of the law enforcement and strictures of the&#xA;dharma shAstra the rogues and thieves of the land were no longer able&#xA;achieving their aims. So the rogues and thieves decided to worship the&#xA;great spear-wielding deity who is known to some as son of agni, to&#xA;others as the first born son of the fierce rudra and to yet other as the&#xA;son of the kR^ittikA-s. The chief of the taskara-s accordingly set up a&#xA;well decorated maNDapa and invoked kumAra with the great formulae ending&#xA;in the refrain “&lt;strong&gt;dhurtaM AvAhayAmyahaM&lt;/strong&gt;“. Pleased by the worship the&#xA;six-headed god promised the rogues that their trouble will come to an&#xA;end.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ShaShTi</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/skandaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2004-06-06_shashti/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Jun 2004 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/skandaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2004-06-06_shashti/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2004/06/06/shashti/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ShaShTi&lt;/strong&gt; is the wife of the terrible 6-headed lord of the bhUtas. She&#xA;is the daughter of yama or indra. When grandson of manu was still-born&#xA;he was revived by the great ShaShTi. She is also known as devasenA or&#xA;senA and is worshipped on the shri pa~nchamI, the 5th day after&#xA;dIpAvali. A tarpaNaM performed to her and kumAra with the mantras from&#xA;the bodhAyana dharmasUtra. Usually the tarpaNaM is performed under a&#xA;large ashvatta tree or some other tree. A cat’s face may be draw on a&#xA;cloth or a leaf and left there as to invoke her. Then a cat is offered&#xA;milk as it is the vAhana of ShaShTi and she is supposed to accept&#xA;offerings that form. This day marks her marriage with the great kumAra.&#xA;She is also invoked on the 6th day after the birth of a child to keep&#xA;away the awful agents of her husband from obliterating the child. She is&#xA;accordingly invoked in the Ayushya homa performed for safe-guarding the&#xA;lives of kids. She is worshipped by thieves and knaves on the 6th day of&#xA;the waning moon for success in thievery. Another important rite of&#xA;ShaShTi is the AraNya ShaShTi that is performed around May-June during&#xA;the first 6th digit of the waxing moon. The rite is usually done under a&#xA;kadamba tree in a forest, where an idol of ShaShTi may be installed.&#xA;Then oblations are offered in the fire with the AraNya sUktaM of the&#xA;R^ig veda and then a tarpaNaM for kumAra and devasenA is done. An&#xA;oblation is also offered to the mAtrika lohitAyani, a female gaNa of&#xA;kuMAra. Then food is left for a fishing cat or a lynx and women are&#xA;given a thread to wear around their wrist.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Forms</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/skandaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/forms/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/skandaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/forms/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The 16 forms of kumAra (each has his own visualization) recovered from a corrupt manuscript of the ShoDasha-subrahmaNya-dhyAna from the dramiLa country:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;ज्ञान-शक्ति-धरः (१) स्कन्दो (२) देव-सेनापतिस् (३) तथा ।&#xA;सुब्रह्मण्यो (४) गजारूढः (५) शर-कानन-सम्भवः (६) ॥&#xA;कार्तिकेयः (७) कुमारश् (८) च षण्मुखस् (९) तारकान्तकः (१०) ।&#xA;सेनानीर् (११) ब्रह्मशास्ता (१२) च वल्ली-कल्याण-सुन्दरः (१३) ॥&#xA;बालश् (१४) च क्रौञ्च-भेत्ता (१५) च शिखि-वाहन (१६) एव च।&#xA;एतानि स्वामि-नामानि पठेत् षोडश नित्यशः ॥&#xA;यः पठेत् सर्वपापेभ्यः स मुच्येत मुनीश्वर ।&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>UDupi kRShNa image origins</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/skandaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/uDupi-kRShNa-image-origins/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/skandaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/uDupi-kRShNa-image-origins/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;iconographic-similarities&#34;&gt;Iconographic similarities&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Similar images&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;An image of skanda from the hamlet of Dhank in Gujarat from the 300s of CE: &lt;a href=&#34;https://x.com/blog_supplement/status/1156051150531178496&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;A skanda from the temple built in what&amp;rsquo;s now the NWFP of TSP by the Kabul shAhIya-s in 700s. &lt;a href=&#34;https://x.com/blog_supplement/status/461397202888556544&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The image at Udupi while today worshiped as a kR^iShNa is rather transparently an old repurposed kaumAra idol.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;karnataka-decline&#34;&gt;karNATaka decline&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://x.com/blog_supplement/status/922680397061910528&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The association of nAga-s with kumAra is common in the karNATa country &amp;amp; adjoining regions of the andhra country.  Of course in the old kaumAra ritual 1 of the mothers receiving bali is kadru: kadrave nAgamAtre svAhA |&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>YoginI-pratyaxam</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/skandaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/yoginI-pratyaxam/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/skandaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/yoginI-pratyaxam/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://x.com/blog_supplement/status/1925398502818898083&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When he successfully performs the mantra-s taught by skanda himself, meditating on the lotus of his forehead, he sees the ferocious therocephalous yoginI-s like siMhamukhI, mArjArI, R^ikShAkShI, vArAhI, vR^iShAnanA, ajAnanA, R^ikShakarNI and the like, as ordained in the yAmala tantra. He then pleases them with the rahastarpaNa and the rahoyAga. If his rite is successful, he has taken a step on the highest mantramarga*. He who attempts the secret mantra-s without the sign and permission of skanda attains dismal failure.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>नीलशिखण्डवाहनः</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/skandaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/nIlashikhaNDavAhanaH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/skandaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/nIlashikhaNDavAhanaH/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://threadreaderapp.com/thread/1585831325948252162.html&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;नील॑शिखण्ड॒ वा ह॑नः ।&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The AV mantra nIlashikaNDavAhanaH is used in kaumAra parlance as the renowned aShTAkShari-vidyA. The word nIlashikhaNDa is a unique usage of the AV tradition that is not &lt;em&gt;endogenous&lt;/em&gt; to the RV, YV or SV. It likely emerged as a term in the Indo-Iranian border zone where the core of AV tradition developed.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It is specifically applied to rudra or his ectypes bhava &amp;amp; sharva which some traditions see as his twin sons ~ ashvin-s of the RV. The AV usage likely parallels the nilagrIva of the YV tradition that became dominant in the later H tradition. AV-vulgate 6.93.1 refers to sharva rather than skanda (yes the 2 are related). The interpretation of AV-vul 20.132 in the vaidika sense goes thus:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>शिवस्य गुरुः</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/skandaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/shivasya_guruH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/skandaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/shivasya_guruH/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;mythemes-antiquity&#34;&gt;Mytheme&amp;rsquo;s antiquity&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This mytheme of the father playing along to lose to his son to enhance his glory is an old IE one. In the foundation of the Olympic games Zeus appears as a wrestler &amp;amp; purposely loses to Herakles to enhance his glory. Similarly, indra loses to arjuna at khANDava in order to enhance his son&amp;rsquo;s glory. Similarly, I suspect that these mytheme has been incorporated in the case of rudra enhancing kumAra.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
