<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/skandaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 04 Oct 2008 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/skandaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>The wives of Mars and the Carmen Arvale</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/skandaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2008-10-04_the-wives-of-mars/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Oct 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/skandaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2008-10-04_the-wives-of-mars/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
In our earlier discussion we had argued based on structural homologies the marut-s of the vedic system are “para-skanda”. We speculated that kumAra himself descends from a para-vedic Indo-Iranian system, which contained an ancestral version of the deity, who in that system was the homolog of the marut-s of the vedic system. This para-vedic skanda was laterally transferred to the vedic system in the late vedic period of India.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On to shrI-parvata</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/skandaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-11-29_on-to-shri-parvata/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Nov 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/skandaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-11-29_on-to-shri-parvata/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
The core altars of a kumAra-gR^iha. The green elements mark the fire altars
He sat in the place where the first of the pieces had fallen. In his mind’s eye h remembered the tale of the great grahanatha: “tArakAsura the accursed enemy of the gods wore a li~Nga around his neck that protected him from death as long as it was there. As he fought viShNu and vIrabhadra their weapons failed on him after prolonged and fierce duels.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The AkhyAna of skanda-patnI</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/skandaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-10-19_the-akhyana-of-skanda-patni/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Oct 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/skandaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-10-19_the-akhyana-of-skanda-patni/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
OM hrIM ShaShaThI devyai svAhA ||
The wandering sUta said: “Listen to the wonderous AkhyAna of skanda-patnI that relieves unborn and young kids from troubles. In days long past I was wandering in the fringes of the magadha, when I stumbled into the mighty brahmin, kashyapa, the son of marIchI. I asked him to narrate to me the tale of the wonderous exploits of skanda and his agents.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>vedic mantra-s adapted for kaumAra ritual</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/skandaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-10-18_vedic-mantras-adapted-for-kaumara-ritual/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Oct 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/skandaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-10-18_vedic-mantras-adapted-for-kaumara-ritual/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
kumAram mAtA yuvatiH samubdhaM guhA bibharti na dadAti pitre |
anIkam asya na minaj janAsaH puraH pashyanti nihitam aratau ||
The young mother keeps the boy hidden in secret, nor gives him to the father;
Men see his undiminishing radiance only when he is set up on the fuel sticks [reeds].
In the vedic context it refers to agni hidden within his “mother”: the kindling wood block, who is hidden away from the father: the fire-drill.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>kumAra vidyA-s</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/skandaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-10-10_kumara-vidya-s/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Oct 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/skandaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-10-10_kumara-vidya-s/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
Of the mUrti-s of kumAra [Note 1] that are worshiped by the educated kaumAra sAdhaka there are few having a special significance. The first of these is of great import for a dvija in devoted the yAj~nIkI perfection. It is the form known as ajArUDha. Here the great lord of the beautiful ShaShThi is meditated upon in the bindu of the maNDala thus:
dvimukhaM chAShTa-bahuM cha shvetaM vA shyAMa-skandharaM |</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The second circle</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/skandaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-05-08_the-second-circle/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 May 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/skandaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-05-08_the-second-circle/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
We had sought she who dwells in the midst of the kiri chakra. Our AchArya’s AchArya the one learned in the great atharvan lore with all its parishiShTha-s, kalpa-s brAhmaNa and upaniShads retired to live in the most picturesque land south of lATa pradesha, with forests largely inhabited by niShAda tribes. There on the banks of the Damanganga river he settled down with the forest providing him the quietude and oShadhI-s for his rites.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The kaumAra vidyA</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/skandaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-01-16_the-kaumara-vidya/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Jan 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/skandaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-01-16_the-kaumara-vidya/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
Having paid respect with to rAja bhojadeva, who stands in the line of the teachers from ShaShThinAtha we salute the god who is in the embrace of sUryasunuduhitR^i.
The cryptic mantra goes thus:
vAk (holy speech) is the varman (armour)
the karNabindvADhya (ear ornaments) go with the charama (last one)
The Fish banner flutters (mInaketana)
salutations to kumAra.
We also worship that awful being, riding a horse or a violent elephant, embracing pUrNA and puShkalA along with his hosts like goptR^i</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The mahA-kumAra-rahasya</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/skandaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-11-18_the-maha-kumara-rahasya/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Nov 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/skandaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-11-18_the-maha-kumara-rahasya/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
The great rahasya of the 6-headed one goes thus:
First there is the praNava, which encompasses the akSharas from shrIkaNTha the father of the young god to the last of the pentads of brahman. kAmarUpaM vahnyArUDhaM bindumAlinIbhuShitaM kAlabindumilitaM (the first core bIja) tryashraM yoniH (the 2nd core bIja) tritIya [tithi] iti ichChA ( the 3rd core bIja) unmeSha (the 4th core bIja) AkAsha tattvaM cha anuttaraM (5th core bIja) tasyAnte viShNupriyA ( for the second time 6th core bIja) vahnI vAmalochanA cha binduruttara rUpaM (7th core bIja) tasyAnte dvitIya ShaDAkSharI iti // After having strung the bIjas and combined them with the second ShaDakShari of kumAra you get the mahAmantra.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>skanda gaNas</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/skandaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-07-23_skanda-ganas/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Jul 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/skandaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-07-23_skanda-ganas/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
Weighed down by the arrows showered by our foes, we call upon son of the ranger of kailAsha. He who bears the bow in battle and showers arrows on the dAnava horde. He who is called ugratamaa and bhImatama, who rushes to battle with the the axe and spear, we worship him in the midst of the six-fold maNDala. One who is dallying with sumukhi and biDAlAkShI, we bow to him.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>kaumArI</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/skandaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-04-30_kaumari/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Apr 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/skandaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-04-30_kaumari/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
kaumArI ShaM namaH ShaShaTyai ca maM maM maM keki keki mahAmayUryaI svAhA</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The secret of sumukhI</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/skandaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-04-07_the-secret-of-sumukhi/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Apr 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/skandaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-04-07_the-secret-of-sumukhi/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
The great deva sanatkumAra, the son of the fiery agni, is always in the company of his two wives: the glorious biDAlAkShi and the wonderous sumukhI. The one who knows this rahasya and performs the invocation of sumukhI along with the great dhUrtasvamI will be favored by them. That glorious goddess sumukhI also called the great mahAmayUrI, engaged in amorous dalliance with the dhUrta, is described as sulabhAgati. In the midst of her yantra, the mate of kArttikeya is meditated as residing and invoked with the mighty mantra (in mantra shAstra code):</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>skanda vara</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/skandaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-03-18_skanda-vara/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Mar 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/skandaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-03-18_skanda-vara/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
The boons offered by the deity kumAra are of great certainty, but they be extremely perplexing and their good result may only be seen after some ironic hardship undergone by the recepient. Hence is he known as the roguish dhUrta, who composed the taskara vidyA by manifesting as kanakahastin and bhAskaranandin. But even the paths to the attainment of chaurya perfection were not straight. amba wanted to slay bhIShma for which she received a garland from kumAra but none ever wore it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The deadly foe-destroying yoga of brahmaNya deva</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/skandaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2004-09-12_the-deadly-foe-destroying-yoga-of-brahmanya-deva/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Sep 2004 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/skandaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2004-09-12_the-deadly-foe-destroying-yoga-of-brahmanya-deva/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
“We pacify the six-headed being, of fiery birth, who is lost in the embrace of the beautiful daughter of the god of the gods indra. May his lethal darts not harm us and instead strike our foes.”
At the heart of the kaumara tantric rite lies the great secret yoga which destroys ones foes. The skandArchana kalpadruma and other obscure kaumAra texts refer to this secret yoga, the configuration of the incantation for which is normally revealed only by oral tradition.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The roguish Karttikeya and the wives of the gods</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/skandaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2004-08-02_the-roguish-karttikeya-and-the-wives-of-the-gods/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Aug 2004 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/skandaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2004-08-02_the-roguish-karttikeya-and-the-wives-of-the-gods/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
We worship the roguish deity kumAra with offerings as ordained by the school of the great sage gopatha.
Due to the efficiency of the law enforcement and strictures of the dharma shAstra the rogues and thieves of the land were no longer able achieving their aims. So the rogues and thieves decided to worship the great spear-wielding deity who is known to some as son of agni, to others as the first born son of the fierce rudra and to yet other as the son of the kR^ittikA-s.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ShaShTi</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/skandaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2004-06-06_shashti/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Jun 2004 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/skandaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2004-06-06_shashti/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
ShaShTi is the wife of the terrible 6-headed lord of the bhUtas. She is the daughter of yama or indra. When grandson of manu was still-born he was revived by the great ShaShTi. She is also known as devasenA or senA and is worshipped on the shri pa~nchamI, the 5th day after dIpAvali. A tarpaNaM performed to her and kumAra with the mantras from the bodhAyana dharmasUtra. Usually the tarpaNaM is performed under a large ashvatta tree or some other tree.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>नीलशिखण्डवाहनः</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/skandaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/nIlashikhaNDavAhanaH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/skandaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/nIlashikhaNDavAhanaH/</guid>
      <description>Source: TW
नील॑शिखण्ड॒ वा ह॑नः ।
The AV mantra nIlashikaNDavAhanaH is used in kaumAra parlance as the renowned aShTAkShari-vidyA. The word nIlashikhaNDa is a unique usage of the AV tradition that is not endogenous to the RV, YV or SV. It likely emerged as a term in the Indo-Iranian border zone where the core of AV tradition developed.
It is specifically applied to rudra or his ectypes bhava &amp;amp; sharva which some traditions see as his twin sons ~ ashvin-s of the RV.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>शिवस्य गुरुः</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/skandaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/shivasya_guruH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/skandaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/shivasya_guruH/</guid>
      <description>Mytheme&amp;rsquo;s antiquity This mytheme of the father playing along to lose to his son to enhance his glory is an old IE one. In the foundation of the Olympic games Zeus appears as a wrestler &amp;amp; purposely loses to Herakles to enhance his glory. Similarly, indra loses to arjuna at khANDava in order to enhance his son&amp;rsquo;s glory. Similarly, I suspect that these mytheme has been incorporated in the case of rudra enhancing kumAra.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
