<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;12 The Medicalization of Possession in Āyurveda and Tantra on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/12_Medicalization/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;12 The Medicalization of Possession in Āyurveda and Tantra on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/12_Medicalization/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 Disease-Producing Spirit Possession</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/12_Medicalization/01_Disease-Producing_Spirit_Possession/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/12_Medicalization/01_Disease-Producing_Spirit_Possession/</guid>
      <description>The Caraka-Saṃhitā, the oldest of the major āyurvedic texts,1 mentions three kinds of therapy (cikitsā): daivavyapāśraya (spiritual), yuktivyapāśraya (rational), and sattvāvajaya (psychological).2 Regardless of readily available (and well-known) definitions of these terms in canonical āyurvedic texts, practicing physicians most often quote the following Sanskrit verse as a prelude to any discussion of the treatment of mental illness, including those diagnosed as caused or exacerbated by spirit possession:
janmāntarakṛtam pāpaṃ vyādhirūpeṇa jāyate |</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>02 Bhūtavidyā: Vedic and Āyurvedic Demonologies</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/12_Medicalization/02_BhUtavidyA_Vedic_and_Ayurvedic_Demonologies/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/12_Medicalization/02_BhUtavidyA_Vedic_and_Ayurvedic_Demonologies/</guid>
      <description>The history of bhūtavidyā can be extended back to the early vedic period, in which, in the Ṛgveda (ṚV), the gods (deva, sura) were distinguished from their archenemies (asura, dānava), and in which the battle between the gods and demons was eternally fought, often to a standstill, though with a slight, if temporary, advantage to the gods. The ṚV identifies other categories of ethereal beings as well, who opposed humanity rather than the gods.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>03 The Āyurvedic Demonologies</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/12_Medicalization/03_The_Ayurvedic_Demonologies/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/12_Medicalization/03_The_Ayurvedic_Demonologies/</guid>
      <description>Possession in the āyurvedic texts has been addressed before, notably by Mitchell Weiss,36 who analyzes Indian categories of unmāda and exogenous disease-causing spirits with reference to Freudian and other psychoanalytic categories.37 In addition, Jan Meulenbeld has succinctly described views and categories of bhūtavidyā set forth in different āyurvedic texts. These textual differences have been considerable and should be kept in mind in the ensuing discussions. Among the areas of disagreement were the nature of bhūtas, their ontological reality, their number and identity, their cultural origins, and what constitutes the discipline of bhūtavidyā, including knowing not just the names and descriptions of bhūtas but the diagnostics, pharmacology, and ritual treatment for possession by bhūtas.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>04 Other Indic Demonologies</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/12_Medicalization/04_Other_Indic_Demonologies/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/12_Medicalization/04_Other_Indic_Demonologies/</guid>
      <description>I have limited the above critique to medical texts because Weiss and Clifford have offered the most important theoretical contributions to the consideration of negative possession in South Asia available to date, and they both do so in the context of classical medical texts. However, bhūtavidyā has a broad panorama in South Asian culture, and much of it lies in areas peripheral to these texts. Therefore, in the interest of providing a more complete portrait of negative possession in South Asia, let us consider a few other demonologies, from both texts and ethnographies.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>05 Piśācas and the Piśācmocan Temple</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/12_Medicalization/05_PishAcas_and_the_PishAcamocan_Temple/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/12_Medicalization/05_PishAcas_and_the_PishAcamocan_Temple/</guid>
      <description>Because of the ubiquity of the piśāca, a few words must be said about it. An illuminating passage appears in the Nīlamata Purāṇa (NP), a text from Kashmir that depicts a social and spiritual universe densely populated with ethereal beings of nearly unimaginable variety, which readily interact with one another as well as with humans. These beings comprise devas, gandharvas, apsarases, yakṣas, guhyakas, kinnaras, nāgas, rākṣasas, piśācas, and millions of others.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>06 Childsnatchers and Therapy to Counter Demonic Possession</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/12_Medicalization/06_Childsnatchers_and_Therapy_to_Counter_Demonic_Possession/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/12_Medicalization/06_Childsnatchers_and_Therapy_to_Counter_Demonic_Possession/</guid>
      <description>(Piśacagṛhītabhaiṣajyam)191
A section from the MBh (3.216–219) on the birth of Skanda and the origin of bālagrahas or childsnatchers was explored in Chapter 6. That passage contains much of the essential information found in the āyurvedic texts, including specialized works on pediatrics, descriptive lists of bālagrahas, diseases attributed to them, and remedies. Perhaps the most comprehensive of these passages appears in the Kāsyapa Saṃhitā (KS) of the seventh century, a text that now survives in only two fragmentary manuscripts, testifying to the fact that it was soon eclipsed by other texts, particularly the AH, despite sections like this one that are more comprehensive than the corresponding sections of the later texts.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>07 Healing and the Circulation of Knowledge</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/12_Medicalization/07_Healing_and_the_Circulation_of_Knowledge/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/12_Medicalization/07_Healing_and_the_Circulation_of_Knowledge/</guid>
      <description>As important as it is to examine the categories and taxonomies of bhūtavidyā, it is equally important to examine the healing process. This involves investigating the broader dynamics of exorcism: ritual, pharmacopia, healers, and the interaction between healer and client. Some of this has been addressed above, in anthropological and other ethnographic discussions of the healing process.212 We shall here look more closely at selected passages from the vast āyurvedic and tantric material, mostly the former.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>08 Possession and Exorcism in Contemporary Āyurveda</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/12_Medicalization/08_Possession_and_Exorcism_in_Contemporary_Ayurveda/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/12_Medicalization/08_Possession_and_Exorcism_in_Contemporary_Ayurveda/</guid>
      <description>Much of the following is based on research conducted in Kerala in 2002 and 2004. I undertook this research after hearing a rumor from a usually reliable source that a number of āyurvedic physicians and tāntrikas (or mantravādins, as they are called in Kerala) still follow the practices of possession and exorcism outlined in the ĪŚP. On close investigation, I learned that this is not true. Nevertheless, it is likely that some of the current practices are derivative of what is found there or at least from a complex heritage of texts and practices that gave rise to the ĪŚP.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>09 Diagnosing Possession</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/12_Medicalization/09_Diagnosing_Possession/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/12_Medicalization/09_Diagnosing_Possession/</guid>
      <description>Beyond astrology, and beyond our concern with practices in Kerala, it is relevant to ask how is nija unmāda (mental illness with traceable physiological or psychological origins) distinguished from āgantuka unmāda (mental illness believed to be the result of possession)? In the case of nija unmāda, the vaidya takes a case history and undertakes a medical evaluation. In most cases, the cause is readily acknowledged: family problems, a death in the family, financial pressure, a life-threatening illness.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>10 Conclusions: Notes on the Textuality of Āyurveda</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/12_Medicalization/10_Conclusions_Notes_on_the_Textuality_of_Ayurveda/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/12_Medicalization/10_Conclusions_Notes_on_the_Textuality_of_Ayurveda/</guid>
      <description>The recognition of disease-producing spirit possession in South Asia has an epochal history of more than three thousand years and an equally epic variation and complexity. It can be traced from the Atharvaveda, where unmāda was first discussed, to the early canonical texts of Caraka, Susruta, and Vāgbhaṭa, where diagnostics and treatment modalities were more formally discussed. Contemporaneous with these texts, it is discussed in the Mahābhārata and Buddhist medical treatises.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>11 NOTES</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/12_Medicalization/11_NOTES/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/12_Medicalization/11_NOTES/</guid>
      <description>The composition was cumulative, dating from the second or third century B.C.E. to the fourth or fifth century of the Common Era. For a summary of the evidence see Wujastyk 1998:39–41. For a more precise dating of the core of the text to 50–150 C.E. and exhaustive evidence for this date, see Meulenbeld HIML IA:105–115 and references. Caraka-sūtrasthāna (CaSu) 11.54, Caraka-vimānasthāna (CaVi) 8.87; also Aṣṭāṇgasaṃgraha-sūtrasthāna (ASaṃSū) 12.3; and Hārītasaṃhitā 3.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
