<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/gaNapatiH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2005 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/gaNapatiH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>disposing uchChiShTa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/gaNapatiH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-11-11_disposing-uchchishta/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/gaNapatiH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-11-11_disposing-uchchishta/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2005/11/11/disposing-uchchishta/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Lie down comfortably on the bed, (eating a sweet or tAmbUlaM if you&#xA;want) and then repeat the formula 44 times:&lt;br&gt;&#xA;gaM haM klauM glauM uchChiShTagaNeshAya mahAyakShAyAyaM baliH //&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Then without achamanaM he shall go to the outside arena (ideally a&#xA;shmashAna or 4-cross roads) and mark a square area out with his fingers&#xA;and then utter om + namaH for the following names in the ten directions&#xA;in pradakShiNa order facing north, then up+down.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;vakratuNDa, ekadaMShTra, lambodara, vikaTa, dhUmravarNa, vighna,&#xA;gajAnana, vinAyaka, gaNapati, hastidanta.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The vinAyaka saubhAgya krama</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/gaNapatiH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-10-21_the-vinayaka-saubhagya-krama/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Oct 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/gaNapatiH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-10-21_the-vinayaka-saubhagya-krama/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2005/10/21/the-vinayaka-saubhagya-krama/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;vighnas may be crushed with the vidhi of the terrible vinAyaka. It is&#xA;thus performed.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;-The votary makes a haridra biMba of and invokes vinAyaka into it with&#xA;the formula:&lt;br&gt;&#xA;oM AgachCholkAya avAhanaM kariShyAmi/&lt;br&gt;&#xA;-Then sandalwood paste or scent is offered with:&lt;br&gt;&#xA;oM gandholkAya gandhaM samarpayAmi /&lt;br&gt;&#xA;-Then flowers are offered with:&lt;br&gt;&#xA;oM puShpolkAya puShpaM samarpayAmi /&lt;br&gt;&#xA;-Then incense sticks are waved with:&lt;br&gt;&#xA;oM dhUpolkAya dhUpaM AgrApayAmi /&lt;br&gt;&#xA;-The lamp is shown with:&lt;br&gt;&#xA;oM dIpolkAya dIpaM darshayAmi /&lt;br&gt;&#xA;– bali of a gourd or a pumpkin is offered with:&lt;br&gt;&#xA;oM maholkAya baliM samarpayAmi /&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The pumpkin is cleaved and the inner surfaces smeared with kuMkuma.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The primal shrine of vighnadeva</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/gaNapatiH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-02-19_the-primal-shrine-of-vighnadeva/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Feb 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/gaNapatiH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-02-19_the-primal-shrine-of-vighnadeva/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2005/02/19/the-primal-shrine-of-vighnadeva/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We pay obscience to the terrible medholka, who is surrounded by the&#xA;eight extraordinarily beautiful goddesses clad in shimmering blue silks:&#xA;tIvrA, chAlini, nandA, bhogadA, kAmarUpiNi, ugrA, tejovatI, satyA and is&#xA;embraced by vighnanAshini who is seated beside him.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;oM rAyaspoShasya dadhitA nidhido ratnadhAtumAn rakShohaNo valagahano&#xA;vakratuNDAya huM||&lt;br&gt;&#xA;medholkAya svAhA||&lt;br&gt;&#xA;oM hrIM grIM hrIM||&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Having worshipped the awful one-tusked son of rudra by the Punya river,&#xA;the Kashi of the gANapatyas, we saw him in the embrace of the delightful&#xA;madanAvatI. Then we proceeded to the foremost of his shrines in the&#xA;grove of Mayurapuri which has grown decadent as a result of the downward&#xA;turn of the age of kali, eating tasty bhakShaNas that delight the fiery&#xA;one along the way. Having reached the shrine we entered through the gate&#xA;guarded by lakShmI and nArAyaNa. Then we proceeded to see medholka&#xA;accompanied by his two wives siddhi and saMR^iddhi, who are also known&#xA;as madadravA and madanAvatI. Atop his head rests vAsukI, his eyes and&#xA;navel are studded with gems and his trunk is turned left. Having&#xA;worshiped ulka and his wives we proceeded to see the gates guarded&#xA;respectively by umA and rudra, the delightful kAma and ratI, and varAha&#xA;with mahI seated on his lap. Then we saw the 23 idols of vighna and&#xA;pacified him eight times as :&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ekadanta, mahodara, gajAnana, lambodara, vikaTa, vighnarAja, dhumravarNa&#xA;and vakratuNDa, along with his two wives. Then we worshiped the great&#xA;manthAna bhairava who stood at the wall and bhavasharvA. Then we moved&#xA;to see the rat and the peacock of ulka and the vR^iShabha of mahAdeva.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The 4 incarnations of gaNapati</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/gaNapatiH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2004-09-19_the-4-incarnations-of-ganapati/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Sep 2004 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/gaNapatiH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2004-09-19_the-4-incarnations-of-ganapati/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2004/09/19/the-4-incarnations-of-ganapati/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The gaNesha purANa has the 4 fold incarnations of gaNapati. They are:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;vinAyaka in the kR^itayuga. 3 demons dhUmrAkSha, narAntaka and&#xA;devAntaka assume great power and spread terror. So gaNapati is born of&#xA;kAshyapa and his wife. He has a 10 handed form with lion vAhana and&#xA;slays these asuras in a great battle at kAshi.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2)mayureshvara in the tretayuga. A demon called sindhu swallowed a pot&#xA;of amR^ita he had obtained from rudra and became invincible. gaNapati&#xA;assumed a form with 6 hands and captured mayUra a mighty son of vinAta&#xA;and rode him to battle and slew sindhu after making him disgorge the&#xA;amR^ita. It said that he then gave his peacock to his brother kumAra.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Possession by gaNapati</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/gaNapatiH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2004-01-04_possession-by-ganapati/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Jan 2004 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/gaNapatiH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2004-01-04_possession-by-ganapati/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2004/01/04/possession-by-ganapati/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The sUta asked “O great kshatriya narrate to me the effects of&#xA;displeasing the the fierce god gaNapati.”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The descendent of the great manu, the law giver, said ” The displeasure&#xA;of vinAyaka is of terrible consequence. The 6 ferocious vinAyakas,&#xA;namely shAla, kaTa~nkaTa, kUShmANDa, rAjaputra, sammita and devayajana&#xA;can seize a person at anytime. The person immediately shows a variety of&#xA;strange behaviors- he or she may start pounding clumps of soil with the&#xA;hand, cutting grass, writing on ones own body and dreaming of waters,&#xA;men with shaved heads, camels, pigs and asses. They may feel that they&#xA;are floating in air and feel the constant sensation of being pursued by&#xA;someone while walking. A women, even if of great beauty will simply not&#xA;be looked at by any man, when possessed by the vinAyakas. Men even if&#xA;rich or handsome will simply fail to get a woman. Married women will go&#xA;sterile and children will die. A kshatriya will lose his post or kingdom&#xA;even if he has good qualifications. A good teacher will fail to get any&#xA;students and students will repeatedly pull the plug in their studies.&#xA;vaishyas’ fields will lie fallow and they will sink in their trade.&#xA;Death may strike the victims without warning and their crops or vehicles&#xA;may be crushed by rampaging elephants. Rats will devastate their&#xA;granaries and snakes may kill them or their children. They will&#xA;tormented by bites of insects, spiders and scorpions”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>पाञ्चरात्रागमे गणपः</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/gaNapatiH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/pAncharAtrAgame_gaNapaH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/gaNapatiH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/pAncharAtrAgame_gaNapaH/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There are authoritative pA~ncharAtra texts like jayAkhya which do explicitly specify the worship of gaNesha as known in common dharma:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;ध्यायेत् &amp;hellip; स्थूलाङ्गम् एकदंष्ट्रं च लम्ब-क्रोडं गजाननम् |&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The dhyAna is unambiguous and he not conflated with viShvaksena or his pArShada-s&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Ganesha is described in the Hayashirsha Samhita of the Pancharatra was well where he is placed along with other gods in varieties of arrangements surrounding the main vigraha of vAsudeva. In one place it&amp;rsquo;s said that he should be kept along with skanda flanking the two sides of Rudra. Parama samhita also says that vinAyaka can be worshipped for some particular kAmya karma along with other gods. - shArdUla&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ब्रह्मणस्पतिः</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/gaNapatiH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/brahmaNaspatiH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/gaNapatiH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/brahmaNaspatiH/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;With the rise of the new god vinAyaka, the old vedic deity brAhmaNaspati==bR^ihaspati was identified with him. The expansion of this identity was a medieval phenomenon that developed in the region encompassing the modern Mh-TN states. Several bR^ihaspati mantra-s were now systematically recast and reinterpreted as vinAyaka-mantra-s within this burgeoning gANapatya tradition. This additionally had a symbiotic entwining with the growing shrIkula influence on certain sections of smArta-s and beyond.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
