<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/gaNapatiH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2005 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/gaNapatiH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>disposing uchChiShTa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/gaNapatiH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-11-11_disposing-uchchishta/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/gaNapatiH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-11-11_disposing-uchchishta/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
Lie down comfortably on the bed, (eating a sweet or tAmbUlaM if you want) and then repeat the formula 44 times:
gaM haM klauM glauM uchChiShTagaNeshAya mahAyakShAyAyaM baliH //
Then without achamanaM he shall go to the outside arena (ideally a shmashAna or 4-cross roads) and mark a square area out with his fingers and then utter om + namaH for the following names in the ten directions in pradakShiNa order facing north, then up+down.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The vinAyaka saubhAgya krama</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/gaNapatiH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-10-21_the-vinayaka-saubhagya-krama/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Oct 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/gaNapatiH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-10-21_the-vinayaka-saubhagya-krama/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
vighnas may be crushed with the vidhi of the terrible vinAyaka. It is thus performed.
-The votary makes a haridra biMba of and invokes vinAyaka into it with the formula:
oM AgachCholkAya avAhanaM kariShyAmi/
-Then sandalwood paste or scent is offered with:
oM gandholkAya gandhaM samarpayAmi /
-Then flowers are offered with:
oM puShpolkAya puShpaM samarpayAmi /
-Then incense sticks are waved with:
oM dhUpolkAya dhUpaM AgrApayAmi /</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The primal shrine of vighnadeva</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/gaNapatiH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-02-19_the-primal-shrine-of-vighnadeva/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Feb 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/gaNapatiH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-02-19_the-primal-shrine-of-vighnadeva/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
We pay obscience to the terrible medholka, who is surrounded by the eight extraordinarily beautiful goddesses clad in shimmering blue silks: tIvrA, chAlini, nandA, bhogadA, kAmarUpiNi, ugrA, tejovatI, satyA and is embraced by vighnanAshini who is seated beside him.
oM rAyaspoShasya dadhitA nidhido ratnadhAtumAn rakShohaNo valagahano vakratuNDAya huM||
medholkAya svAhA||
oM hrIM grIM hrIM||
Having worshipped the awful one-tusked son of rudra by the Punya river, the Kashi of the gANapatyas, we saw him in the embrace of the delightful madanAvatI.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The 4 incarnations of gaNapati</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/gaNapatiH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2004-09-19_the-4-incarnations-of-ganapati/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Sep 2004 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/gaNapatiH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2004-09-19_the-4-incarnations-of-ganapati/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
The gaNesha purANa has the 4 fold incarnations of gaNapati. They are:
vinAyaka in the kR^itayuga. 3 demons dhUmrAkSha, narAntaka and devAntaka assume great power and spread terror. So gaNapati is born of kAshyapa and his wife. He has a 10 handed form with lion vAhana and slays these asuras in a great battle at kAshi. 2)mayureshvara in the tretayuga. A demon called sindhu swallowed a pot of amR^ita he had obtained from rudra and became invincible.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Possession by gaNapati</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/gaNapatiH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2004-01-04_possession-by-ganapati/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Jan 2004 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/gaNapatiH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2004-01-04_possession-by-ganapati/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
The sUta asked “O great kshatriya narrate to me the effects of displeasing the the fierce god gaNapati.”
The descendent of the great manu, the law giver, said ” The displeasure of vinAyaka is of terrible consequence. The 6 ferocious vinAyakas, namely shAla, kaTa~nkaTa, kUShmANDa, rAjaputra, sammita and devayajana can seize a person at anytime. The person immediately shows a variety of strange behaviors- he or she may start pounding clumps of soil with the hand, cutting grass, writing on ones own body and dreaming of waters, men with shaved heads, camels, pigs and asses.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>पाञ्चरात्रागमे गणपः</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/gaNapatiH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/pAncharAtrAgame_gaNapaH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/gaNapatiH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/pAncharAtrAgame_gaNapaH/</guid>
      <description>There are authoritative pA~ncharAtra texts like jayAkhya which do explicitly specify the worship of gaNesha as known in common dharma:
ध्यायेत् &amp;hellip; स्थूलाङ्गम् एकदंष्ट्रं च लम्ब-क्रोडं गजाननम् |
The dhyAna is unambiguous and he not conflated with viShvaksena or his pArShada-s
Ganesha is described in the Hayashirsha Samhita of the Pancharatra was well where he is placed along with other gods in varieties of arrangements surrounding the main vigraha of vAsudeva.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ब्रह्मणस्पतिः</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/gaNapatiH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/brahmaNaspatiH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/gaNapatiH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/brahmaNaspatiH/</guid>
      <description>With the rise of the new god vinAyaka, the old vedic deity brAhmaNaspati==bR^ihaspati was identified with him. The expansion of this identity was a medieval phenomenon that developed in the region encompassing the modern Mh-TN states. Several bR^ihaspati mantra-s were now systematically recast and reinterpreted as vinAyaka-mantra-s within this burgeoning gANapatya tradition. This additionally had a symbiotic entwining with the growing shrIkula influence on certain sections of smArta-s and beyond.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
