<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/agniH/meta/MT_lekhAH/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 25 Jan 2006 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/agniH/meta/MT_lekhAH/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>The three-headed one</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/agniH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-01-25_the-three-headed-one/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jan 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/agniH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-01-25_the-three-headed-one/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2006/01/25/the-three-headed-one/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;oM drAM dattAtreya namaH&lt;br&gt;&#xA;oM aiM kroM klIM clUM hrAM hrIM hrUM sauH dattAtreyAya svAhA ||&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The three-headed one, also known as the terrifying trishiro-bhairava,&#xA;wandered around carefree in the great forests of himaparvatas. With one&#xA;of his arms was holding the most beautiful madhumati of sweet smiles in&#xA;an embrace around her gold-girt slender waist. In his other hands he&#xA;held a mace, a trident, the blazing sudarshana, and a conch. He was of&#xA;fair complexion, youthful and energetic with ever-smiling faces. The&#xA;delightful madhumati would occassionally cast her arms around him, like&#xA;a jasmine creeper winding around a full-grown khadira tree, and she&#xA;would bring her face close to his. Their eyes would meet, exchanging&#xA;glances of the highest bliss. The great trimukha would hold her face&#xA;with his hand, and it would seem like a lotus sprouting from a pond&#xA;under the pleasant spring sun. In her hands, madhumati held a chalice of&#xA;sweet maireya liqour, which she would playfully quaff. Occasionally she&#xA;would pass the chalice full of mirth to trishiras and they would quaff&#xA;together in eternal Ananda. The bIja eM was constantly resonating around&#xA;madhumati even as she with her dazzling beauty concealed the&#xA;three-headed one from the gaze of on lookers. They might stop in a&#xA;secluded slyvan grotto and engage in kAmakrIDa, nR^itya and aTTahAsa. In&#xA;the highest ecstasy of pleasure the mighty tryAnana offered madhumati&#xA;the premaratna – the gem of love, and having nothing greater to offer in&#xA;return, madhumati, full of rasa, matched it by offering her own breasts.&#xA;The incomparable trimUrtI clasping her breasts in his hands, gently&#xA;placed a camphor flavored betel leaf between her pearl-like teeth. Then&#xA;sporting with nails, polished like the mother-of-sea-pearl, he tickled&#xA;the three folds in her mid-riff. Embraced by madhumati the trideva&#xA;looked like the peaks of the Himalayas girt by snow and pine forests.&#xA;The bIjas AM, hrIM, kroM, klIM, huM and oM filled the air. They spread&#xA;the mAyA.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Musings on the aponaptrIya rite</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/agniH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2005-11-23_musings-on-the-aponaptriya-rite/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Nov 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/agniH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2005-11-23_musings-on-the-aponaptriya-rite/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2005/11/23/musings-on-the-aponaptriya-rite/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The aponaptrIya is an important rite associated with the somayAga and is&#xA;described in detail in the aitareya, the kaushItaki and chAgaleya&#xA;brAhmaNas. The rite seems to be associated with the deities sarasvatI&#xA;and apAM napAt and was probably instituted by kavaSha ailUsha, the&#xA;priest of the pUru king kurushravaNa. Simply told, it is said that the&#xA;other brAhmaNas, the madhymas questioned the legitimacy of kavaSha as a&#xA;brahmin, calling him a cheat and one born through a dAsa&#xA;[proto-Iranian?] mother. They drove kavaSha out in the desert and as&#xA;he departed he composed the hymn “pra devatra brahmaNe..[RV 10.30]”&#xA;and it is said that sarasvatI followed him surrounding him with her&#xA;waters. The madhyamas realizing that he was a great R^ishi favored by&#xA;sarasvati brought him back and had him institute the aponaptrIya rite.&#xA;With these hymns the hotA priest collects water in on the day before the&#xA;sacrifice and this is called the vasatIvarI water. The water collected&#xA;in the morning of the sacrifice is called the ekadhanaA water. The hotA&#xA;then pours these into a goblet with RV 1.83.2 and the adhvaryu mixes&#xA;honey and soma into these waters for the devas. This pouring is supposed&#xA;to aid crushing of the rivals through indra. Then with Rv 1.23.16-18,&#xA;the final pouring of the waters for the water goddess is performed.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>agni, the divine hotars and the adhrigupraiShasaMpraiSha</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/agniH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2005-02-26_agni-the-divine-hotars-and-the-adhrigupraishasampr/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Feb 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/agniH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2005-02-26_agni-the-divine-hotars-and-the-adhrigupraishasampr/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2005/02/26/agni-the-divine-hotars-and-the-adhrigupraishasampraisha/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;pre-sacrifice-chant&#34;&gt;pre-sacrifice chant&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Before the animal sacrifice of the pashubandha the maitravaruNa priest utters the chant (RV 4.15.1-3):&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;agnir hotA no adhvare&lt;br&gt;&#xA;vAjI san pari nIyate/&lt;br&gt;&#xA;devo deveShu yaGNYiyaH //&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;agni, the hotar, being the booty bearing horse, is led around in our sacrifice; a deva to be worshipped amongst the devas.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;a pari triviShTy adhvaraM yAty agnI rathIr iva / A deveShu prayo dadhat //&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;agni, like a car-warrior, goes around 3 times in our sacrifice, distributing amongst the devas the sacrificial offerings.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>jAtavedas</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/agniH/meta/MT_lekhAH/jAtavedas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/agniH/meta/MT_lekhAH/jAtavedas/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://threadreaderapp.com/thread/1648142705095000064.html&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The god agni manifests as several devatA-s in the shruti &amp;amp; the two main ones are agni jAtavedas &amp;amp; agni vaishvAnara. There are other less frequent ones like agni rakShohan, agni anIkavat &amp;amp; the like.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There is a certain theological complementarity between jAtavedas &amp;amp; vaishvAnara. agni jAtavedas is identified by the fire established at the beginning of the ritual burning unbroken through it. In the same sense he is also identified with the agni maintained through the generations by the ritualists &amp;ndash; an old IE tradition. Hence, one may interpret jAtavedas as both: he with knowledge of the birth of the ritual in the proximal sense &amp;amp; he with knowledge of it in the sense of continuity from the primordial making of the fire.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
