<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/agniH/meta/MT_lekhAH/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 25 Jan 2006 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/agniH/meta/MT_lekhAH/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>The three-headed one</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/agniH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-01-25_the-three-headed-one/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jan 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/agniH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-01-25_the-three-headed-one/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
oM drAM dattAtreya namaH
oM aiM kroM klIM clUM hrAM hrIM hrUM sauH dattAtreyAya svAhA ||
The three-headed one, also known as the terrifying trishiro-bhairava, wandered around carefree in the great forests of himaparvatas. With one of his arms was holding the most beautiful madhumati of sweet smiles in an embrace around her gold-girt slender waist. In his other hands he held a mace, a trident, the blazing sudarshana, and a conch.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Musings on the aponaptrIya rite</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/agniH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2005-11-23_musings-on-the-aponaptriya-rite/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Nov 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/agniH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2005-11-23_musings-on-the-aponaptriya-rite/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
The aponaptrIya is an important rite associated with the somayAga and is described in detail in the aitareya, the kaushItaki and chAgaleya brAhmaNas. The rite seems to be associated with the deities sarasvatI and apAM napAt and was probably instituted by kavaSha ailUsha, the priest of the pUru king kurushravaNa. Simply told, it is said that the other brAhmaNas, the madhymas questioned the legitimacy of kavaSha as a brahmin, calling him a cheat and one born through a dAsa [proto-Iranian?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>agni, the divine hotars and the adhrigupraiShasaMpraiSha</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/agniH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2005-02-26_agni-the-divine-hotars-and-the-adhrigupraishasampr/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Feb 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/agniH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2005-02-26_agni-the-divine-hotars-and-the-adhrigupraishasampr/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
pre-sacrifice chant Before the animal sacrifice of the pashubandha the maitravaruNa priest utters the chant (RV 4.15.1-3):
agnir hotA no adhvare
vAjI san pari nIyate/
devo deveShu yaGNYiyaH //
agni, the hotar, being the booty bearing horse, is led around in our sacrifice; a deva to be worshipped amongst the devas.
a pari triviShTy adhvaraM yAty agnI rathIr iva / A deveShu prayo dadhat //
agni, like a car-warrior, goes around 3 times in our sacrifice, distributing amongst the devas the sacrificial offerings.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>jAtavedas</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/agniH/meta/MT_lekhAH/jAtavedas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/agniH/meta/MT_lekhAH/jAtavedas/</guid>
      <description>Source: TW
The god agni manifests as several devatA-s in the shruti &amp;amp; the two main ones are agni jAtavedas &amp;amp; agni vaishvAnara. There are other less frequent ones like agni rakShohan, agni anIkavat &amp;amp; the like.
There is a certain theological complementarity between jAtavedas &amp;amp; vaishvAnara. agni jAtavedas is identified by the fire established at the beginning of the ritual burning unbroken through it. In the same sense he is also identified with the agni maintained through the generations by the ritualists &amp;ndash; an old IE tradition.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
