<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/savitA/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/savitA/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Alternative sAvitrIs</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/savitA/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/alternative-sAvitrIs/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/savitA/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/alternative-sAvitrIs/</guid>
      <description>Today the Sāvitrī is universally used by all dvija-s for their saṃdhyopāsanā/ Savitrupāsanā. However, we know that the saṃdhyā rite goes back to at least the Indo-Iranian period. This raises the question as to whether there was a Savitrupāsanā before the extant Sāvitrī was composed by Viśvāmitra. It is notable that Viśvāmitra himself specifically mentions that the god is worshiped 3 times in a day.
११ हिरण्यपाणिः सविता ...{Loading}... हिर॑ण्यपाणिः सवि॒ता सु॑जि॒ह्वस्</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Deva Savitṛ</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/savitA/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/savitR/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/savitA/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/savitR/</guid>
      <description>While the Sāvitrī remains a popular mantra among modern Hindus, most of them do not know its deity. Even of those who know Savitṛ to be the deity, few have a clear idea of the nature of this god. Most believe that he is none other than the Sun of our solar system. Yet, the RV is quite clear about him not being the same as the sun. The sun is merely one manifestation of his activity.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>सावित्री-प्रयोगाः</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/savitA/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/sAvitrI-prayogAH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/savitA/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/sAvitrI-prayogAH/</guid>
      <description>The ritual of ācamana He sips water 3× with the 3 feet of the Sāvitrī. Thereafter, he performs mārjanam at the appropriate spots on the face and one shoulder with the feet of the āpohiṣṭhiya mantra-s, at other shoulder with the 7 vyāhṛtis, at the chest with the whole sāvitrī and on the head with the brahmaśiras. He may use this ācamana for routine smārta and ekāgni purposes. The only exceptions are Atharvan rituals (where he should use the Atharvavedīya ācamana-vidhi) and the three-fire śrauta rituals.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
