<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/savitA/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/savitA/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Alternative sAvitrIs</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/savitA/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/alternative-sAvitrIs/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/savitA/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/alternative-sAvitrIs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today the Sāvitrī is universally used by all dvija-s for their saṃdhyopāsanā/ Savitrupāsanā. However, we know that the saṃdhyā rite goes back to at least the Indo-Iranian period. This raises the question as to whether there was a Savitrupāsanā before the extant Sāvitrī was composed by Viśvāmitra. It is notable that Viśvāmitra himself specifically mentions that the god is worshiped 3 times in a day.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; includetitle=&#34;false&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;5&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/vishvAsa-prastutiH/03/054/11_hiraNyapANiH_savitA.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h5&gt;११ हिरण्यपाणिः सविता ...{Loading}...&lt;/h5&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;हि᳓रण्यपाणिः &lt;strong&gt;सविता᳓&lt;/strong&gt; सुजिह्व᳓स्&lt;br&gt;&#xA;त्रि᳓र् आ᳓ दिवो᳓ &lt;strong&gt;विद᳓थे+++(=यज्ञे)+++ प᳓त्यमानः&lt;/strong&gt;+++(= पतित्वं कामयमानः)+++ । &lt;br&gt;&#xA;देवे᳓षु च सवितः श्लो᳓कम् &lt;strong&gt;अ᳓श्रेर्&lt;/strong&gt;+++(=प्राप्नुयाः)+++&lt;br&gt;&#xA;आ᳓द्+++(=अनन्तरं)+++ अस्म᳓भ्यम् &lt;strong&gt;आ᳓ सुव&lt;/strong&gt; सर्व᳓-तातिम् ॥&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deva Savitṛ</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/savitA/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/savitR/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/savitA/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/savitR/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;While the Sāvitrī remains a popular mantra among modern Hindus, most of them do not know its deity. Even of those who know Savitṛ to be the deity, few have a clear idea of the nature of this god. Most believe that he is none other than the Sun of our solar system. Yet, the RV is quite clear about him not being the same as the sun. The sun is merely one manifestation of his activity.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>सावित्री-प्रयोगाः</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/savitA/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/sAvitrI-prayogAH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/savitA/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/sAvitrI-prayogAH/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-ritual-of-ācamana&#34;&gt;The ritual of ācamana&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;He sips water 3× with the 3 feet of the Sāvitrī.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Thereafter, he performs mārjanam at the appropriate spots on the face and one shoulder with the feet of the āpohiṣṭhiya mantra-s, at other shoulder with the 7 vyāhṛtis, at the chest with the whole sāvitrī and on the head with the brahmaśiras.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;He may use this ācamana for routine smārta and ekāgni purposes. The only exceptions are Atharvan rituals (where he should use the Atharvavedīya ācamana-vidhi) and the three-fire śrauta rituals.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;saṃdhyopāsanā&#34;&gt;saṃdhyopāsanā&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The Sāvitrī is the essential mantra for the twilight saṃdhyopāsanā or the worship of the god Savitṛ during the day. Every dvija has to receive this mantra from his father or male guardian during his upanayana. If a brāhmaṇa male does not perform this rite at all then the king who observes dharma may employ him a śūdra.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;He should first take a bath if he is an state of impurity before performing the Savitropāsanā. Beyond a bath with water, a dvija should also perform prokṣaṇa.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Having deployed the saṃdhyā preliminaries as ordained in his śruti or that ordained by in the Baudhāyana tradition, he can perform the mantra-practice.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;He does japa (inaudibly) of the Sāvitrī 1008× or 108×.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;If he does not have the time he may perform prāṇāyama with the 7 vyāhṛti-s and the brahmaśiras 10×.&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The most simple form of prāṇāyāma involves inhaling with oṃ bhūḥ.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Retaining the breath with the rest of the mantra and exhaling with the brahmaśiras.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;After concluding the japa or prāṇāyāma he offers arghya 3 ×  + 1 for expiation with his cupped palms or a shell.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;He then invokes Mitra (morning) and Varuṇa (evening) or both if he has missed one. Then he utters the purificatory incantation of Agni, Sūrya or the waters.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;purification&#34;&gt;Purification&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;If a dvija has committed a ghora-pāpa, e.g. abortion, brāhmaṇī-gamanam, puṃścalī-gamanam etc, or has killed a dog, a beaver, a mongoose, a goose or a garden lizard, then he may purify himself after reciting the Sāvitrī 8000× continuously starting before the sun rises.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;If a dvija has had his bath but is uncertain of his ritual purity due to activities he has performed since his bath, he may wear new clothes and perform a japa of the Sāvitrī for a fixed number of times or do prāṇāyāma as described above.&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Then he recites the following incantation of Vasiṣṭha:&lt;br&gt;&#xA;शुची॑ वो ह॒व्या म॑रुतः॒ शुची॑नां॒&lt;br&gt;&#xA;शुचिं॑ हिनोम्य् अध्व॒रं शुचि॑भ्यः ।&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ऋ॒तेन॑ स॒त्यम् ऋ॑त॒साप॑ आय॒ञ्&lt;br&gt;&#xA;छुचि॑-जन्मानः॒ शुच॑यः पाव॒काः ॥&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Pure oblations to you O Marut-s, the pure ones;&lt;br&gt;&#xA;A pure ritual I offer to the pure ones;&lt;br&gt;&#xA;By the ṛta the ṛta-knowers have attained truth,&lt;br&gt;&#xA;of pure birth, they who are pure, the purifiers.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;concluding-ritual&#34;&gt;Concluding ritual&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;After the conclusion of upāsanā the ritualist must invoke Savitṛ for protection. He sprinkles water on the place where he did is upāsanā and having touched the ground with his ring finger, he touches the spot between his eyebrows with the same finger. While doing this action he recites the following Sāvitra incantations of Śyāvāśva Ātreya:&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;अ॒द्या नो॑ देव सवितः&lt;br&gt;&#xA;प्र॒जाव॑त् सावीः॒ सौभ॑गम् ।&lt;br&gt;&#xA;परा॑ दु॒ष्ष्वप्न्यं॑ सुव ॥&lt;br&gt;&#xA;विश्वा॑नि देव सवितर्&lt;br&gt;&#xA;दुरि॒तानि॒ परा॑ सुव ।&lt;br&gt;&#xA;यद् भ॒द्रं तन् न॒ आ सु॑व ॥&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
