<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;स्वमतम् on संस्कारे विश्वासटिप्पणयः</title>
    <link>file:///storage/emulated/0/notesData/saMskAra/kalpaH/general/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;स्वमतम् on संस्कारे विश्वासटिप्पणयः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    
	<atom:link href="file:///storage/emulated/0/notesData/saMskAra/kalpaH/general/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Benefits</title>
      <link>file:///storage/emulated/0/notesData/saMskAra/kalpaH/general/benefits/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>file:///storage/emulated/0/notesData/saMskAra/kalpaH/general/benefits/</guid>
      <description>The study and practice of hindu kalpa-s is quite *addictive* and (thankfully) useful - just as some other performance arts are. Even if you discount purported supernatural benefits, many hindu rituals (with their varied mantra, tantra, svara underpinnings) are incredibly well designed.
The US army flag-hoisting ceremony and the Japanese tea ceremony are examples of very moving rituals in non-hindu contexts which may resonate with your past experience, gentle reader.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Presentations</title>
      <link>file:///storage/emulated/0/notesData/saMskAra/kalpaH/general/presentations/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>file:///storage/emulated/0/notesData/saMskAra/kalpaH/general/presentations/</guid>
      <description>Here we list some relevant presentations discovered online.
Title: ​&amp;quot;Saṁskāras : Hindu self cultivation - it&#39;s is not out of fashion.&amp;rdquo;
​​Abstract:​ A practicing Hindu is a Hindu who observes Hindu rituals and festivals of his choice, with the belief that they make him a happier and a better person, embedded in a joyful and thriving community. These practices, together with their impact on the psyche of the practitioner and his surroundings, are called saṁskāra-s (refinement).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ritual reality</title>
      <link>file:///storage/emulated/0/notesData/saMskAra/kalpaH/general/ritual_reality/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>file:///storage/emulated/0/notesData/saMskAra/kalpaH/general/ritual_reality/</guid>
      <description>Intro  &amp;ldquo;This is how our ritual spaces work and something I hope can be drilled into the heads of the judges who have no erudition about our religion. The deity’s nature (in Southern Agamika &amp;amp; tAntrika temples, this is based on the mantra-s installed in the deity’s icon/vigraha), location of deity’s shrine, nature of rituals done, type of priesthood, kind of food and flower offerings made to deity, nature of people who come to the temple, colors of garments worn by the deity, priests &amp;amp; devotees &amp;amp; many other factors all have to cohere with one another as far as possible.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>भावः</title>
      <link>file:///storage/emulated/0/notesData/saMskAra/kalpaH/general/feeling/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>file:///storage/emulated/0/notesData/saMskAra/kalpaH/general/feeling/</guid>
      <description>&amp;ldquo;उत्तम-कलानुभूतिः→ तत्र भावः&amp;rdquo; इति दृश्यताम् दैवावेशः कल्प्यतेतराम् कर्मसु। सहृदयरसिकोत्तम-साधकोत्तमयोर् अयमपि भेदो महान्।  &amp;ldquo;ज्ञात्वा कर्माणि कुर्वीत&amp;rdquo; इति आर्योक्तिः  Do an aesthetic study and understand the thought and feeling behind practices rather than following arbitrary looking traditional instructions - on the way to developing one&#39;s own favored practice. I do not wish to give up my freedom to sympathetically probe, understand and decide on what my practice should be - the freedom in particular to respectfully disagree in practice with the learned traditional practitioner when the explanation is unsatisfactory &amp;mdash;and face the &amp;ldquo;consequences&amp;rdquo; from the deva-s.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>