<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/jalam/meta/MT_lekhAH/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/jalam/meta/MT_lekhAH/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Sarasvatī Post migration</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/jalam/meta/MT_lekhAH/sarasvatI_post-migration/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/jalam/meta/MT_lekhAH/sarasvatI_post-migration/</guid>
      <description>Possibiities
the sarasvatI channel was a holy river to Harappans from their heydays &amp;amp; they transferred that sanctity to the Arya-s with whom they mixed&amp;amp; the Arya-s identified it with their own ancient riverine traditions. The rain fed river was still active enough for the first 200-300 yrs of Arya settlement. Thereafter the Arya-s witnessed its drying up and recorded the same faithfully in the texts. </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>सरस्वती</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/jalam/meta/MT_lekhAH/sarasvatI/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/jalam/meta/MT_lekhAH/sarasvatI/</guid>
      <description>अप्सम्बन्धः, प्राचीनता च The river is textually identified with the aquatic deity of the Indo-Aryans, sarasvatI who is widely worshiped in the R^igveda and persists to this date in the modern Hindu religions as a consort of brahmA. &amp;hellip;
One of the important themes that emerges from the aponaptrIya ritual is the intimate connection between sarasvati and Agni as worshipped as the son of the waters or apAM napAta. This fiery entity hidden with the water is of ancient IE provenance as is evidenced by the word naptha meaning a fiery substance and the same time bearing a relationship to the word naptar or relative, suggesting that it was essentially derived from the ancestral state ApAM napAt.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
