<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;रुचिरपत्त्राणि on संस्कारे विश्वासटिप्पणयः</title>
    <link>file:///storage/emulated/0/notesData/saMskAra/sanskrit/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;रुचिरपत्त्राणि on संस्कारे विश्वासटिप्पणयः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    
	<atom:link href="file:///storage/emulated/0/notesData/saMskAra/sanskrit/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Miscellaneous questions</title>
      <link>file:///storage/emulated/0/notesData/saMskAra/sanskrit/misc-faq/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>file:///storage/emulated/0/notesData/saMskAra/sanskrit/misc-faq/</guid>
      <description>Elsewhere  quora अत्र।  Sanskrit villages  jihrI (2015 report)  Samskrit OR Samkritam OR Sanskrit OR Sanskrut?  Depends on how you say the sa, the m and the r in संस्कृतम्।, rather than how you write really (since it is impossible to losslessly encode the highly specific devanAgarI sounds in the very limited latin alphabet without adapting clear conventions such as these). To appreciate the difference, you should understand the difference between the way म् and ं sounds (the latter does not include a reverberation in the mouth cavity); and between ऋ and रि/ रु.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Misconceptions</title>
      <link>file:///storage/emulated/0/notesData/saMskAra/sanskrit/misconceptions/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>file:///storage/emulated/0/notesData/saMskAra/sanskrit/misconceptions/</guid>
      <description>Sanskrit Phobia  Other analyses:  [Rajiv Malhotra does a more thorough job.]    Sanskrit is a dead language.  Some limited decline:  Q15.   Lay use  Despite contrary socio-economic forces, it is vitally alive. For numbers, see this thread. Just search Youtube for Sanskrit videos - even omitting ancient hymns, you will find a lot. &amp;ldquo;Sanskrit villages&amp;rdquo; -  mattUru 1.     Thriving literary scene and scholarship  200-300 Mahakavyas composed in Sanskrit since independence.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why?</title>
      <link>file:///storage/emulated/0/notesData/saMskAra/sanskrit/why/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>file:///storage/emulated/0/notesData/saMskAra/sanskrit/why/</guid>
      <description>Why Sanskrit?  Most of all, to attain and preserve the pinnacles of the hindu way (in social and self cultivation). To preserve the dharma which protected our virile ancestors and enabled them to thrive accross a stunning span of time and space.  Just as pANini&#39;s system (checked and approved by the sagely tradition) is a peg for Sanskrit - keeping it from deviating too far from the shiShTa-usage for 2500+ years, sanskrit itself is large part of a peg for the classical Indo-Aryan memeplex which keeps it from deviating too far from the sages&amp;rsquo; vision.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>प्रभुत्वम् Dominance</title>
      <link>file:///storage/emulated/0/notesData/saMskAra/sanskrit/supremacy/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>file:///storage/emulated/0/notesData/saMskAra/sanskrit/supremacy/</guid>
      <description>Intro सङ्क्षेपेण वक्तव्यं चेद् एवं मन्यमानैर् ब्राह्मणप्रधानैर् दक्षैर् भाषाशिक्षकैस् तद्रक्षणं प्रचारश्च –
 &amp;ldquo;वेदोऽखिलो धर्ममूलम्।&amp;rdquo; इत्यादिः। वेदादीनां रक्षा, पोषणञ्च संस्कृतेनेति- &amp;ldquo;भाषां वाऽपि जनं वाऽपि धर्मो रक्षिति रक्षितः।&amp;rdquo; संस्कारेणार्ष-मार्ग-ग्रहणं श्रेयस इति। तत्र पद्यम् कुतश्चिदुद्धृतम्-  चलनाद् वलनान् नृत्यं गानं
क्वणनाद् वचनात् काव्यं यस्मात्।
संस्कार त्वं लीलायुक्तस्
स्थेया व्याप्तस् सर्वस्वे मे॥

&amp;ldquo;Sanskrit as a supreme language&amp;rdquo; by Ashok Aklujkar [Arch] is a very pertinent read. Some excerpts follow, with some added formatting.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>लङ्कायां संस्कृतम्</title>
      <link>file:///storage/emulated/0/notesData/saMskAra/sanskrit/lanka_education/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>file:///storage/emulated/0/notesData/saMskAra/sanskrit/lanka_education/</guid>
      <description>&amp;ldquo;Buddhist monks from their early Samanera age, are “required” to learn Sanskrit alongside Pali &amp;hellip; it is Pali – not Sanskrit – that is expected to sustain the local version of Theravada Buddhism on this land.&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;The academic contexts where Sanskrit is taught in support of the study of disciplines such as the Sinhala and Tamil languages and literature, History, Religious Studies, Archaeology, and Philosophy often confine Sanskrit scholarship to the basics.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>