<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;2 New and Inherited Paradigms on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/2_Modernity_and_the_Languages_of_Possession/2_New_and_Inherited_Paradigms/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;2 New and Inherited Paradigms on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/2_Modernity_and_the_Languages_of_Possession/2_New_and_Inherited_Paradigms/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 Classical Study and Ethnography</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/2_Modernity_and_the_Languages_of_Possession/2_New_and_Inherited_Paradigms/01_Classical_Study_and_Ethnography/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/2_Modernity_and_the_Languages_of_Possession/2_New_and_Inherited_Paradigms/01_Classical_Study_and_Ethnography/</guid>
      <description>Although possession as a religious and sociocultural phenomenon in ancient and classical India has been understudied, in fact rarely mentioned in the secondary literature (to a great extent because it has been regarded as absent in the primary literature),1 the opposite is the case for modern India, for which studies of possession abound. Indeed, it is no exaggeration to say that possession is one of the most studied topics in anthropology and is beginning to find its way into the academic study of religion.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>02 Definitions and Typologies</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/2_Modernity_and_the_Languages_of_Possession/2_New_and_Inherited_Paradigms/02_Definitions_and_Typologies/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/2_Modernity_and_the_Languages_of_Possession/2_New_and_Inherited_Paradigms/02_Definitions_and_Typologies/</guid>
      <description>The definition of possession cited earlier by Boddy in her review article on the literature of possession has the advantage of both conceptual precision and elasticity. This definition bears repeating. Possession, Boddy says, is a broad term referring to an integration of spirit and matter, force, or power and corporeal reality, in a cosmos where the boundaries between an individual and her environment are acknowledged to be permeable, flexibly drawn, or at least negotiable.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>03 The Devil’s Work</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/2_Modernity_and_the_Languages_of_Possession/2_New_and_Inherited_Paradigms/03_The_Devils_Work/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/2_Modernity_and_the_Languages_of_Possession/2_New_and_Inherited_Paradigms/03_The_Devils_Work/</guid>
      <description>Because possession is deeply embedded in the complexities of local culture and ritual, it is important to exercise caution in formulating general theories about it.23 Although it is not my intention to present a general theory, it is nevertheless necessary to present different viewpoints regarding possession, particularly because most available theories have been applied to possession in India. To begin, the interpretation of possession as the work of demonic, ungodly beings is characteristically the property of certain Western Christian, usually Protestant, denominations, though, as shown below, South Asians themselves often enough accuse tantrikas in the temporary employ of local enemies of setting malevolent spirits on family members afflicted with mental illness.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>04 Psychiatric and Psychoanalytic Interpretations</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/2_Modernity_and_the_Languages_of_Possession/2_New_and_Inherited_Paradigms/04_Psychiatric_and_Psychoanalytic_Interpretations/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/2_Modernity_and_the_Languages_of_Possession/2_New_and_Inherited_Paradigms/04_Psychiatric_and_Psychoanalytic_Interpretations/</guid>
      <description>As others have noted before me, spirit (or deity) possession must be viewed from within the cultural systems of which it is a part. In such systems, as Loring Danforth points out, “people who are seriously disturbed are generally not able to express or resolve their idiosyncratic problems through the cultural symbols provided by the idiom of spirit possession.” Spirit possession is, therefore, “an adaptive response through which they are able to resolve social and psychological problems in a widely accepted, and sometimes well-respected, cultural idiom.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>05 Possession as a Form of Social Control</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/2_Modernity_and_the_Languages_of_Possession/2_New_and_Inherited_Paradigms/05_Possession_as_a_Form_of_Social_Control/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/2_Modernity_and_the_Languages_of_Possession/2_New_and_Inherited_Paradigms/05_Possession_as_a_Form_of_Social_Control/</guid>
      <description>Possession is often interpreted as an expression of social control, or at least its attempt, a category that includes political power. Within this broad category of interpretation are almost innumerable variations that have been much pursued by anthropologists in the past several decades. Although control is exercised both actively and passively through political enforcement and cultural ideology, these interpretations have emphasized the active or performative aspects of possession and their roles within implicit psychological, social, and political contexts.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>06 Possession and Shamanism</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/2_Modernity_and_the_Languages_of_Possession/2_New_and_Inherited_Paradigms/06_Possession_and_Shamanism/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/2_Modernity_and_the_Languages_of_Possession/2_New_and_Inherited_Paradigms/06_Possession_and_Shamanism/</guid>
      <description>Possession is often identified or compared to shamanism.115 The most important theorist of this relationship is I. M. Lewis, whose book Ecstatic Religion remains mandatory reading in the field. Lewis asserts that “possession is a culturally normative experience”116 in many places, a statement with which I concur with respect to South Asia. Like most anthropologists, he seeks to determine the social etiology and meaning of possession as well as its culturally determined psychological dimensions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>07 Possession as Ontological Reality</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/2_Modernity_and_the_Languages_of_Possession/2_New_and_Inherited_Paradigms/07_Possession_as_Ontological_Reality/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/2_Modernity_and_the_Languages_of_Possession/2_New_and_Inherited_Paradigms/07_Possession_as_Ontological_Reality/</guid>
      <description>Possession is understood as ontological or veridical reality by those who undergo the experience, which is to say as imposition or investiture on an individual personality of an independent and unseen external agent. This, of course, is the emic view, the narrative of indigenous tradition, the interpretation given to possession by the groups or individuals studied. This stands opposed to nearly all academic theorizing—to the emic narrative of scholarship. Nevertheless, it is an interpretation not wholly discarded by many ethnographers and others engaged in the issue.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>08 Śakti, the Localization of Divinity, and the Possessed</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/2_Modernity_and_the_Languages_of_Possession/2_New_and_Inherited_Paradigms/08_shakti_the_Localization_of_Divinity_and_the_Possessed/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/2_Modernity_and_the_Languages_of_Possession/2_New_and_Inherited_Paradigms/08_shakti_the_Localization_of_Divinity_and_the_Possessed/</guid>
      <description>We must now discuss some specifications of possession in South Asia, including, first, the possibility of possession as a gendered phenomenon. In South Asia, as elsewhere, more women than men appear to experience possession. Important to understanding why this is the case, and perhaps always has been, is an evaluation of the constitution of personhood and sacred space in South Asia, for these are intimately linked in the physical and metaphysical complex of South Asian women’s possession.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>09 Performative and Biographical Context</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/2_Modernity_and_the_Languages_of_Possession/2_New_and_Inherited_Paradigms/09_Performative_and_Biographical_Context/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/2_Modernity_and_the_Languages_of_Possession/2_New_and_Inherited_Paradigms/09_Performative_and_Biographical_Context/</guid>
      <description>A major feature of possession known from ethnographic literature is its frequent occurrence in either religious drama or religious ritual (or both together). One need look no further than the recent work of Alf Hiltebeitel and Richard Frasca on South Indian street theater,185 Kathleen Erndl’s work on goddess worship in Panjab,186 and William Sax’s work on the Pāṇḍav Līlā in Garhwal to recognize the prominence of possession in contemporary religious drama.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>10 Conclusions</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/2_Modernity_and_the_Languages_of_Possession/2_New_and_Inherited_Paradigms/10_Conclusions/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/2_Modernity_and_the_Languages_of_Possession/2_New_and_Inherited_Paradigms/10_Conclusions/</guid>
      <description>After reviewing various definitions of possession, methodological approaches including those that study possession (1) as a negatively inspired religious phenomenon, (2) as a psychological event, (3) as a social or sociopolitical event that trades in power relations, (4) as a type of shamanism, and (5) as a “real” incursion of spirits or deities to be taken at face value and addressed with a full cosmological arsenal, and after examining possession as a gendered, situated, and performative experience, we are in a position to move forward in our study.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>11 NOTES</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/2_Modernity_and_the_Languages_of_Possession/2_New_and_Inherited_Paradigms/11_NOTES/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/2_Modernity_and_the_Languages_of_Possession/2_New_and_Inherited_Paradigms/11_NOTES/</guid>
      <description>A recent exception is Padoux 1999.
Boddy 1994 cites 221 anthropological and ethnographic studies of possession, and this is far from complete as she cites only English-language sources.
Humphrey and Laidlaw 1994:261. The authors add, with respect to the notion that the purpose of ritual is cultural communication: “Our theory suggests that this is a mistake” (ibid.).
I am grateful to Scott Schnell, an anthropologist, for this observation.
I return to this theme periodically.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
