<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;2 New and Inherited Paradigms on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/2_Modernity_and_the_Languages_of_Possession/2_New_and_Inherited_Paradigms/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;2 New and Inherited Paradigms on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/2_Modernity_and_the_Languages_of_Possession/2_New_and_Inherited_Paradigms/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 Classical Study and Ethnography</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/2_Modernity_and_the_Languages_of_Possession/2_New_and_Inherited_Paradigms/01_Classical_Study_and_Ethnography/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/2_Modernity_and_the_Languages_of_Possession/2_New_and_Inherited_Paradigms/01_Classical_Study_and_Ethnography/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Although possession as a religious and sociocultural phenomenon in ancient and classical India has been understudied, in fact rarely mentioned in the secondary literature (to a great extent because it has been regarded as absent in the primary literature),1 the opposite is the case for modern India, for which studies of possession abound. Indeed, it is no exaggeration to say that possession is one of the most studied topics in anthropology and is beginning to find its way into the academic study of religion.2 Its attractiveness as a subject of study is often due to its exotic character (which is to say its spiritual distance from academe), its evident irrational Otherness, and its frequent presence in ritual. Caroline Humphrey and James Laidlaw, who have studied possession and exorcism among largely educated middle-class people at the Padampura Jain temple near Jaipur, assert, “Ethnographers have displayed an almost puzzle-solving pleasure in ‘decoding’ rituals: the more bizarre and serpentine the better. Behind this lies the idea that rituals contain hidden messages about the societies in which they are performed.”3 This, they believe, is the consuming passion of anthropologists; yet they see the scholar’s analysis of ritual (especially that in which possession is contextualized) as usually neglecting the participant’s view. This emic viewpoint is something I attempt to engage in this volume, as a parallel discourse to the etic viewpoints that constitute and regulate contemporary academics (though one may argue that the practice of an etic discourse in thinking about the Other is simultaneously the practice of an emic discourse within the tribe of scholars).4 Conferring at least limited credibility to emic viewpoints is, in my experience of contemporary scholarship (in opposition to Humphrey and Laidlaw’s observation), finding an increasingly prominent place in more recent studies of possession. Furthermore, in defense of those of us who study possession (including Humphrey and Laidlaw), it must be said that public performance of possession is nearly always thrilling and exotic for those who are enculturated. Thus anthropologists and other observers and researchers must not be faulted too severely for yielding to that same odd attractiveness, for succumbing to the spell of possession.5&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02 Definitions and Typologies</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/2_Modernity_and_the_Languages_of_Possession/2_New_and_Inherited_Paradigms/02_Definitions_and_Typologies/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/2_Modernity_and_the_Languages_of_Possession/2_New_and_Inherited_Paradigms/02_Definitions_and_Typologies/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The definition of possession cited earlier by Boddy in her review article on the literature of possession has the advantage of both conceptual precision and elasticity. This definition bears repeating. Possession, Boddy says, is a broad term referring to an integration of spirit and matter, force, or power and corporeal reality, in a cosmos where the boundaries between an individual and her environment are acknowledged to be permeable, flexibly drawn, or at least negotiable.7&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03 The Devil’s Work</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/2_Modernity_and_the_Languages_of_Possession/2_New_and_Inherited_Paradigms/03_The_Devils_Work/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/2_Modernity_and_the_Languages_of_Possession/2_New_and_Inherited_Paradigms/03_The_Devils_Work/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Because possession is deeply embedded in the complexities of local culture and ritual, it is important to exercise caution in formulating general theories about it.23 Although it is not my intention to present a general theory, it is nevertheless necessary to present different viewpoints regarding possession, particularly because most available theories have been applied to possession in India. To begin, the interpretation of possession as the work of demonic, ungodly beings is characteristically the property of certain Western Christian, usually Protestant, denominations, though, as shown below, South Asians themselves often enough accuse tantrikas in the temporary employ of local enemies of setting malevolent spirits on family members afflicted with mental illness. Commenting on studies of possession, though not singling out Christian perspectives, Nicholas Dirks comments: “Most of the literature on possession deals with the nasty kind, when it is the devil rather than the lord who has taken up residence within our mortal coil.”24 This may be stretching it a bit, especially given the explosion of possession studies among anthropologists since the 1960s. But it does constitute a well-represented viewpoint commonly invoked until the mid-twentieth century, one that has not been completely abandoned. It is more accurate to agree with Isabelle Nabokov, who observes that despite Christian missionary accounts of possession as “replete with prejudicial interpretations and factual errors, they still disclose a vibrant, well-established tradition of boundary transgressions between this world and the hereafter.”25&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04 Psychiatric and Psychoanalytic Interpretations</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/2_Modernity_and_the_Languages_of_Possession/2_New_and_Inherited_Paradigms/04_Psychiatric_and_Psychoanalytic_Interpretations/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/2_Modernity_and_the_Languages_of_Possession/2_New_and_Inherited_Paradigms/04_Psychiatric_and_Psychoanalytic_Interpretations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As others have noted before me, spirit (or deity) possession must be viewed from within the cultural systems of which it is a part. In such systems, as Loring Danforth points out, “people who are seriously disturbed are generally not able to express or resolve their idiosyncratic problems through the cultural symbols provided by the idiom of spirit possession.” Spirit possession is, therefore, “an adaptive response through which they are able to resolve social and psychological problems in a widely accepted, and sometimes well-respected, cultural idiom.”41 Thus the question of labeling spirit or deity possession a form of deviant behavior or psychologically definable pathology must be answered within the context of the local culture. This is no less true in South Asia than anywhere else. In spite of (or perhaps because of) a suspected (or suspect) normalcy, and because of the extensive time frame of the topic as I approach it here, it is necessary to engage in a fairly thorough review of the psychological and psychoanalytic interpretations of possession as I see them and their relevance to the topic at hand.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05 Possession as a Form of Social Control</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/2_Modernity_and_the_Languages_of_Possession/2_New_and_Inherited_Paradigms/05_Possession_as_a_Form_of_Social_Control/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/2_Modernity_and_the_Languages_of_Possession/2_New_and_Inherited_Paradigms/05_Possession_as_a_Form_of_Social_Control/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Possession is often interpreted as an expression of social control, or at least its attempt, a category that includes political power. Within this broad category of interpretation are almost innumerable variations that have been much pursued by anthropologists in the past several decades. Although control is exercised both actively and passively through political enforcement and cultural ideology, these interpretations have emphasized the active or performative aspects of possession and their roles within implicit psychological, social, and political contexts. This political influence in South Asia, however, is hardly felt because, despite the widespread practice of possession, it has not gained sufficiently broad formal recognition to influence religious or political bodies, as it has, for example, in certain places in Africa where possession argues much more visibly a politics of identity based on a sense of colonialist victimization,105 or in Tibet where the Nechung oracle has had a history of influencing the politics of the Dalai Lamas.106&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>06 Possession and Shamanism</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/2_Modernity_and_the_Languages_of_Possession/2_New_and_Inherited_Paradigms/06_Possession_and_Shamanism/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/2_Modernity_and_the_Languages_of_Possession/2_New_and_Inherited_Paradigms/06_Possession_and_Shamanism/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Possession is often identified or compared to shamanism.115 The most important theorist of this relationship is I. M. Lewis, whose book Ecstatic Religion remains mandatory reading in the field. Lewis asserts that “possession is a culturally normative experience”116 in many places, a statement with which I concur with respect to South Asia. Like most anthropologists, he seeks to determine the social etiology and meaning of possession as well as its culturally determined psychological dimensions. He examines trance, ecstasy, hypnosis, and shamanism, ultimately concluding that the latter shares an important process with possession—a reciprocity between gods and humans. He posits a homogeneity between shamanism and spirit possession, arguing, contra Eliade, that “the Tungus evidence makes nonsense of the assumption that shamanism and spirit possession are totally different phenomena, belonging necessarily to different cosmological systems and to separate historical stages of development.”117 In drawing this equivalence, Lewis, whose model strikes me as excessively deterministic despite many virtues,118 delineates a wholly presumed and uncompromising functionalist sociology of possession states.119 In this he develops two contrasting psychosocial loci of possession, which he labels “central” and “peripheral.” Central possession, generally highly valued, supports prevailing political, moral, and religious beliefs and views spirits as sympathetic to these. Peripheral possession, an invasion of evil, amoral spirits, is undesirable and dangerous. Central possession, understandably, is a preserve of those of high status and power, while peripheral possession is generally associated with those who lack power and status. Although peripheral possession appears to be historically the preserve of women and those of lower social rank, it is definitively less so in recent times, as democratization, modernity, and the disappearance of Christian-dominated colonialism have freed educated middle- and even upper-class individuals and families to embrace the peripheries, bringing them closer to the center. In this way, economics, rather than ideology, caste, or other markers of purity or impurity, defines and situates power and status, at least in this orbit, by collapsing the boundaries between the periphery and the center.120&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>07 Possession as Ontological Reality</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/2_Modernity_and_the_Languages_of_Possession/2_New_and_Inherited_Paradigms/07_Possession_as_Ontological_Reality/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/2_Modernity_and_the_Languages_of_Possession/2_New_and_Inherited_Paradigms/07_Possession_as_Ontological_Reality/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Possession is understood as ontological or veridical reality by those who undergo the experience, which is to say as imposition or investiture on an individual personality of an independent and unseen external agent. This, of course, is the emic view, the narrative of indigenous tradition, the interpretation given to possession by the groups or individuals studied. This stands opposed to nearly all academic theorizing—to the emic narrative of scholarship. Nevertheless, it is an interpretation not wholly discarded by many ethnographers and others engaged in the issue. For most scholars who recognize, if grudgingly, the possibility of possession, this recognition is tactical, as a contribution to other theoretical agendas. The underlying assumptions of the social constructivist approaches that characterize most academic theorizing about possession—that issues and ambiguities concerning power and authority lie at the basis of much spirit belief and nearly all claims of unmediated possession experience—are being increasingly softened by scholars willing to find a way for their approaches to reconcile with indigenous notions that they find are all too often summarily dismissed. These scholars, most of whom occupy university positions in religion, psychology, and anthropology, are themselves, perhaps, rebelling against the possession–or, to put it more mildly, the enchantment–of their disciplines by modernity (or postmodernity). To transpose Geertz’s observation of cultures as possessing a “curious mixture of borrowed fragments of modernity and exhausted relics of tradition,” we might speak of contemporary academics sorting out for itself exhausted relics of modernity and borrowed fragments of tradition.143&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>08 Śakti, the Localization of Divinity, and the Possessed</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/2_Modernity_and_the_Languages_of_Possession/2_New_and_Inherited_Paradigms/08_shakti_the_Localization_of_Divinity_and_the_Possessed/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/2_Modernity_and_the_Languages_of_Possession/2_New_and_Inherited_Paradigms/08_shakti_the_Localization_of_Divinity_and_the_Possessed/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We must now discuss some specifications of possession in South Asia, including, first, the possibility of possession as a gendered phenomenon. In South Asia, as elsewhere, more women than men appear to experience possession. Important to understanding why this is the case, and perhaps always has been, is an evaluation of the constitution of personhood and sacred space in South Asia, for these are intimately linked in the physical and metaphysical complex of South Asian women’s possession. It is also necessary to discuss possession as performance, as this is also linked with the constitution of the person and relational space.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>09 Performative and Biographical Context</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/2_Modernity_and_the_Languages_of_Possession/2_New_and_Inherited_Paradigms/09_Performative_and_Biographical_Context/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/2_Modernity_and_the_Languages_of_Possession/2_New_and_Inherited_Paradigms/09_Performative_and_Biographical_Context/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A major feature of possession known from ethnographic literature is its frequent occurrence in either religious drama or religious ritual (or both together). One need look no further than the recent work of Alf Hiltebeitel and Richard Frasca on South Indian street theater,185 Kathleen Erndl’s work on goddess worship in Panjab,186 and William Sax’s work on the Pāṇḍav Līlā in Garhwal to recognize the prominence of possession in contemporary religious drama.187 In the Pāṇḍav Līlā, for example, the actors or dancers are regarded as possessed by the characters whom they represent, such as Arjuna, Kṛṣṇa, or Draupadī. Indeed, as in the Kṛṣṇa and Rām līlās in Vrindaban, Varanasi, and elsewhere, the deities are themselves believed to be physically present, temporarily but fully manifested in the performers. This display of power and presence of the sacred permits the deities to be worshipped directly. Also documented is possession judged as higher and lower, positive and negative, not at all unlike the general distinction noted above between ā√viś and pra√viś in “Sanskritic possession.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>10 Conclusions</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/2_Modernity_and_the_Languages_of_Possession/2_New_and_Inherited_Paradigms/10_Conclusions/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/2_Modernity_and_the_Languages_of_Possession/2_New_and_Inherited_Paradigms/10_Conclusions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;After reviewing various definitions of possession, methodological approaches including those that study possession (1) as a negatively inspired religious phenomenon, (2) as a psychological event, (3) as a social or sociopolitical event that trades in power relations, (4) as a type of shamanism, and (5) as a “real” incursion of spirits or deities to be taken at face value and addressed with a full cosmological arsenal, and after examining possession as a gendered, situated, and performative experience, we are in a position to move forward in our study. As should be clear from the above remarks, I am not bound to any single methodological approach; indeed, I find all of them problematic, especially for a study that emerges for the most part from the literary record. Most of this record does not satisfy the requirements of thick description, as this was never the intention of the authors. Furthermore, possession as mentioned and described in India is exceptionally diverse in its perspectives and dates. Therefore, we cannot expect a unity of vision to emerge, nor a single methodological approach to work for all the material.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>11 NOTES</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/2_Modernity_and_the_Languages_of_Possession/2_New_and_Inherited_Paradigms/11_NOTES/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/2_Modernity_and_the_Languages_of_Possession/2_New_and_Inherited_Paradigms/11_NOTES/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A recent exception is Padoux 1999.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Boddy 1994 cites 221 anthropological and ethnographic studies of possession, and this is far from complete as she cites only English-language sources.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Humphrey and Laidlaw 1994:261. The authors add, with respect to the notion that the purpose of ritual is cultural communication: “Our theory suggests that this is a mistake” (ibid.).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I am grateful to Scott Schnell, an anthropologist, for this observation.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I return to this theme periodically. See also Kapferer 1997:83, on the attraction to the anthropologist of sorcery in general. For a very different reaction, see Nabokov (2000), who admits to being so intrigued by possession and a séance that she witnessed one night at the beginning of her fieldwork in Tamilnadu that she spent the remainder of her research year attempting to understand what she had seen (pp. 3–4). By the end of the year, however, she claims to have “acquired none of the fascination that anthropologists working on possession sometimes develop for states of trance” (pp. 179–80). Her illuminating book provides the reasons for this; indeed, the reasons are embedded in the title, Religion Against the Self.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
