<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;13 Conclusions - Identity Among the Possessed and the Dispossessed on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/13_Conclusions_-_Identity/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;13 Conclusions - Identity Among the Possessed and the Dispossessed on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/13_Conclusions_-_Identity/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 Variation and Vocabulary</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/13_Conclusions_-_Identity/01_Variation_and_Vocabulary/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/13_Conclusions_-_Identity/01_Variation_and_Vocabulary/</guid>
      <description>Having worked our way through this whirlwind tour—this grand if sometimes bewildering tapestry of Indic literature and ethnography, emotions big and small, ritual formations, health and disease, initiatory trauma and transformation, and much more—we now offer reactions and a few conclusions. First, however, summary descriptions of various kinds of possession are in order. Possession may be destructive (Kali possessing Nala and childsnatchers invading the bodies of pregnant women), instructional (the possession by gandharvas of the daughter and wife of Patañcala Kāpya in the Bṛhadāraṇyaka Upaniṣad (BĀU) in what must have been a semipublic séance, and Śaṅkara’s possession of the dead king in order to obtain knowledge of erotics and defeat Ubhayabhāratī, the wife of Maṇḍana Misra, in debate), healing or unifying (possession by Soma, transfer of essences described in the Upaniṣads, tantric śaktipāta initiation), protective (Vipula Bhārgava possessing Ruci), symptomatic of perfected devotion (the līlāveśa or bhagavadāvesa of Vallabhācārya and Rūpa Gosvāmī), a tool used by advanced yogins to influence others (Yogasūtras, Brahmasūtras), or indicative of a state of immersion in erotic love, in the cycle of rebirth, in the Lord’s love games, or even in the Lord’s very body (again bhagavadāveśa, saṃsārāveśa, līlāveśa).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>02 Possession and Embodiment</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/13_Conclusions_-_Identity/02_Possession_and_Embodiment/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/13_Conclusions_-_Identity/02_Possession_and_Embodiment/</guid>
      <description>Among the prominent images in the Upaniṣads is that of the body as a locus for external forces. Although the early Upaniṣads are best known for their discussions of interior topography, they also display a sure knowledge of and deep concern for the physical body. Their knowledge of organs and other aspects of human physiology is derived largely from the antecedent Brāhmaṇa literature, in most cases indicating that this knowledge served purposes other than health.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>03 Sudden and Gradual</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/13_Conclusions_-_Identity/03_Sudden_and_Gradual/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/13_Conclusions_-_Identity/03_Sudden_and_Gradual/</guid>
      <description>I cannot disagree with Gombrich’s statement that “brahmanism inculcates control,” but I believe that such a notion must be nuanced based on the foregoing discussions. We have established that possession is a liminal state of mind,35 with mundane concerns and discourse reconfigured though not ignored. We have also seen that “positive” possession almost always emerges from ritual. Such ritual works in one of two basic ways. The first, brahmanical, inculcates a controlled state of possession through the observance of complicated and precise processes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>04 Questions and (a Few) Answers</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/13_Conclusions_-_Identity/04_Questions_and_a_Few_Answers/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/13_Conclusions_-_Identity/04_Questions_and_a_Few_Answers/</guid>
      <description>In Chapter 2, I inquired as to what extent we can equate possession as discourse with possession as event. My answer(s) to this difficult question should have become clear in the course of this study. Essentially, the wealth of evidence both textual and ethnographic demonstrates that the link between discourse and event is so proximate that it is nearly indistinguishable. The discourse of possession in India is not just verbal or linguistic but performative as well.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>05 Bringing It All Back Home: The Mahābhārata and Traditions of Possession</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/13_Conclusions_-_Identity/05_Mahbhrata_and_Traditions_of_Possession/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/13_Conclusions_-_Identity/05_Mahbhrata_and_Traditions_of_Possession/</guid>
      <description>As pointed out earlier, most Indic possession can be spun from the MBh: from the tales of two kings, Nala and Kalmāṣapāda, who experienced very different kinds of possession; from the story of Asvatthāman, arguably the most heinous villain in an epic with an outsized cast of reprehensible characters; from the protective possession of Ruci by Vipula Bhārgava, the composed and dutiful, yet inscrutably uncertain, pupil of the powerful sage Devaśarman; and from the tale of the birth of Skanda, which for millennia has served as the exemplar for certain demonologies in āyurvedic and tantric texts and, doubtless, in popular culture as well.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>06 NOTES</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/13_Conclusions_-_Identity/06_NOTES/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/13_Conclusions_-_Identity/06_NOTES/</guid>
      <description>Trans. van Buitenen 1975:335. To the best of my knowledge, no text actively distinguishes samāveśa from samādhi. The former, it appears, indicates blissful pervasion by an external force, while the latter, in the Yogasūtras, the key text that defines it, suggests an internal pervasion that transcends relation. Many other equivalent passages are found in the Yoga Upaniṣads; see the edition by A. Mahadeva Sastri. See Brown 1921:153ff. for further references.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
