<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;13 Conclusions - Identity Among the Possessed and the Dispossessed on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/13_Conclusions_-_Identity/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;13 Conclusions - Identity Among the Possessed and the Dispossessed on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/13_Conclusions_-_Identity/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 Variation and Vocabulary</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/13_Conclusions_-_Identity/01_Variation_and_Vocabulary/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/13_Conclusions_-_Identity/01_Variation_and_Vocabulary/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Having worked our way through this whirlwind tour—this grand if sometimes bewildering tapestry of Indic literature and ethnography, emotions big and small, ritual formations, health and disease, initiatory trauma and transformation, and much more—we now offer reactions and a few conclusions. First, however, summary descriptions of various kinds of possession are in order. Possession may be destructive (Kali possessing Nala and childsnatchers invading the bodies of pregnant women), instructional (the possession by gandharvas of the daughter and wife of Patañcala Kāpya in the Bṛhadāraṇyaka Upaniṣad (BĀU) in what must have been a semipublic séance, and Śaṅkara’s possession of the dead king in order to obtain knowledge of erotics and defeat Ubhayabhāratī, the wife of Maṇḍana Misra, in debate), healing or unifying (possession by Soma, transfer of essences described in the Upaniṣads, tantric śaktipāta initiation), protective (Vipula Bhārgava possessing Ruci), symptomatic of perfected devotion (the līlāveśa or bhagavadāvesa of Vallabhācārya and Rūpa Gosvāmī), a tool used by advanced yogins to influence others (Yogasūtras, Brahmasūtras), or indicative of a state of immersion in erotic love, in the cycle of rebirth, in the Lord’s love games, or even in the Lord’s very body (again bhagavadāveśa, saṃsārāveśa, līlāveśa). When humans possess others, as in the case of Vipula Bhārgava or Śaṅkara, the purpose is viewed as benign. It is regarded similarly when the possessing agent is a substance, an abstraction, or an essence (soma, medhas, etc.). When negative spirits (bhuta, piśāca, etc.) are the agents of possession, it is considered destructive. But when the agent is a semidivine being with a preponderance of good qualities, such as a gandharva, ambiguous results are weighted toward the positive.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02 Possession and Embodiment</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/13_Conclusions_-_Identity/02_Possession_and_Embodiment/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/13_Conclusions_-_Identity/02_Possession_and_Embodiment/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Among the prominent images in the Upaniṣads is that of the body as a locus for external forces. Although the early Upaniṣads are best known for their discussions of interior topography, they also display a sure knowledge of and deep concern for the physical body. Their knowledge of organs and other aspects of human physiology is derived largely from the antecedent Brāhmaṇa literature, in most cases indicating that this knowledge served purposes other than health. Principally, the purpose was to describe animals fit for sacrifice. This vision is modified in the Yoga, Śaiva, and other, later subgenres of Upaniṣads, when interest in the vedic sacrifices had begun to wane, to one in which the body is seen to encase nāḍīs (channels that circulate within the body) and cakras (subtle energy centers that are lined up vertically from the perineum to the crown of the head). Thus, the tantric vision of the body led to modifications in the Upaniṣadic view (e.g., Dhyānabindu Upaniṣad 50–72, Yogacūḍāmaṇi Upaniṣad).3 Increasingly, through various practices of yoga (āsana and prāṇāyāma), the body was viewed as transmutable. Although this is most evident in the later Upaniṣads, the early ones foreshadow them in this regard. In the waking state, the “self” (ātman) is said to abide in the heart, but in deep sleep and dream it wanders in the nāḍīs (BĀU 2.1.17). Sometimes it exits the body entirely, leaving the prāṇas in charge. At death, according to the later Upaniṣads, it leaves the body via the suṣumnā nāḍī (central upwardly flowing channel) (Yogaśikha Upaniṣad 6.5, etc.). The chief function of the body, then, is to house the life force (jīva) and, according to some Upaniṣads, the ātman. Brahmā, the Taittirīya (2.1.1) and Muṇḍaka (3.1.7) Upaniṣads state, dwells in the guhā, the space in the heart. Similarly, according to the Kaṭha (2.20) and Śvetāśvatara (3.11) Upaniṣads, the deity dwells in the guhā of all creatures. The Muṇḍaka (2.1.8,10) and Svetāsvatara (3.20) add that puruṣa is placed in it, while the Maitrāyaṇi Upaniṣad (26) states that ātman enters into it. The Kaṭha (4.6) says that the firstborn of Brahmā and Āditya enter and abide there, while many later Upaniṣads list a number of possible deities who assume residence in this secret place. The late Subala Upaniṣad (7.8), for example, states that Nārāyaṇa dwells there, while the Kaivalya Upaniṣad (3) states that the mendicant (yati) enters (visānti) what shines in the secret place.4 As explicated in Chapter 5, the Indic body was ripe for possession.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03 Sudden and Gradual</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/13_Conclusions_-_Identity/03_Sudden_and_Gradual/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/13_Conclusions_-_Identity/03_Sudden_and_Gradual/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I cannot disagree with Gombrich’s statement that “brahmanism inculcates control,” but I believe that such a notion must be nuanced based on the foregoing discussions. We have established that possession is a liminal state of mind,35 with mundane concerns and discourse reconfigured though not ignored. We have also seen that “positive” possession almost always emerges from ritual. Such ritual works in one of two basic ways. The first, brahmanical, inculcates a controlled state of possession through the observance of complicated and precise processes. The second, typically non-brahmanical in the sense of non-Sanskritic (this was never a disincentive to brahman participation),36 encourages possession by inculcating strategies for release rather than control. The former amounts to a guided gradual transformation through metamorphosis, while the latter amounts to a guided sudden release. In both cases we are speaking of ritual that depicts the tension between freedom and discipline. Although the gradualists are beset with a greater number of formal rules, in both cases style and structure are important, conferring a sense of rigorousness that is essential for materialization of the process.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04 Questions and (a Few) Answers</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/13_Conclusions_-_Identity/04_Questions_and_a_Few_Answers/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/13_Conclusions_-_Identity/04_Questions_and_a_Few_Answers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In Chapter 2, I inquired as to what extent we can equate possession as discourse with possession as event. My answer(s) to this difficult question should have become clear in the course of this study. Essentially, the wealth of evidence both textual and ethnographic demonstrates that the link between discourse and event is so proximate that it is nearly indistinguishable. The discourse of possession in India is not just verbal or linguistic but performative as well. Possession is not just an inner experience defined by one’s intensity of feeling and focus, dissociative powers, and linguistic and performative capabilities; it is an event that is publicly negotiable and verifiable. Standards and paradigms of possession are available in South Asian public culture, both contemporary and ancient, and may be verified in the ethnographies and classical texts. The issue of discourse is closely tied in with the nature of individuality and the individual in South Asia and whether possession can contribute to a greater understanding or unveiling of that nature. I ask, in effect, whether a partially or fully manifested and attributed deity or spirit, within the locally constructed nexus of discourse and event, destroys the fabric of the individual. I have also wondered, apropos of these questions, whether it is a mistake to assume an autonomous individual in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05 Bringing It All Back Home: The Mahābhārata and Traditions of Possession</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/13_Conclusions_-_Identity/05_Mahbhrata_and_Traditions_of_Possession/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/13_Conclusions_-_Identity/05_Mahbhrata_and_Traditions_of_Possession/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As pointed out earlier, most Indic possession can be spun from the MBh: from the tales of two kings, Nala and Kalmāṣapāda, who experienced very different kinds of possession; from the story of Asvatthāman, arguably the most heinous villain in an epic with an outsized cast of reprehensible characters; from the protective possession of Ruci by Vipula Bhārgava, the composed and dutiful, yet inscrutably uncertain, pupil of the powerful sage Devaśarman; and from the tale of the birth of Skanda, which for millennia has served as the exemplar for certain demonologies in āyurvedic and tantric texts and, doubtless, in popular culture as well. Fictional though these characters may be, they connect directly to enduring features of South Asian religious and narrative culture, both Sanskritic and non-Sanskritic. Possession by the Skandas, the bālagrahas or childsnatchers, or other allied invasive agents of negative possession are not addressed further here, as I have dealt with them sufficiently. Nor do I address further the topic of possession identified as escalation of emotional engagement, except to emphasize, first, that it too can be traced in considerable measure to epic discourse and, second, that devotional possession, a form of intense emotional engagement that has its origins in a culture of mixed classicism, folk religion, and a probable early layer of shamanistic practice, has been explained in Sanskritic and certain folk cultures in terms of Sanskritic aesthetic categories.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>06 NOTES</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/13_Conclusions_-_Identity/06_NOTES/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/13_Conclusions_-_Identity/06_NOTES/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Trans. van Buitenen 1975:335.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;To the best of my knowledge, no text actively distinguishes samāveśa from samādhi. The former, it appears, indicates blissful pervasion by an external force, while the latter, in the Yogasūtras, the key text that defines it, suggests an internal pervasion that transcends relation.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Many other equivalent passages are found in the Yoga Upaniṣads; see the edition by A. Mahadeva Sastri.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;See Brown 1921:153ff. for further references.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Cf. Csordas 1990.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;See the articles by Koller, Larson, and Dissanayake in Kasulis et al. 1993. These articles, which do little more than examine well-known canonical doctrines, abundantly reveal the truth of Gombrich’s observations often cited here that “brahmanism inculcates control.”&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Dissanayake 1993:39–40.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Staal 1993:71. See also Goodman 1990, who makes a strong case for a positive correlation between physical posture, spirit or deity possession, and states of altered consciousness.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The body as conceptualized in the ṚV and in India in general, as we have seen, occupied a surprisingly liminal space. Based on his analysis of the afterlife in the ṚV, Reat notes, “in Vedic thought the most essential element of the human being is his individual identity, which resides primarily in the quasi-material tanū” (1990:63). (In spite of the general absence of historical and linguistic surety in this book, Reat’s observations on tanū, at least, are sound.) This individual identity is a composite entity called ātmán in the ṚV and Yajurveda Saṃhitās. This is to be distinguished from the ātman of the Upaniṣads, where it becomes the microcosmic equivalent of the absolute brahman.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Staal 1993. His writing on ritual (e.g., 1983, 1990a) also demonstrates this point.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Tambiah speaks of Western “notions of bounded self and atomistic individualism” (1990:133) opposing the more fluid, transactional, and interactional notions of the self in Indian thought. On “fluidity” of the self in India, see Daniel 1984.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;See the discussion in Chapter 2 on the equal attraction of possession performance to ethnographers and enculturated peoples.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Cf., e.g., Kakar 1982:238ff.; Koller 1993:52ff.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Cf. Heesterman’s felicitous statement on the Vedic ritualist’s conception of the universe: “In this world of floating forms there are no hard and fast lines; conceptually different entities and notions interchange with bewildering ease. All things, entities, notions, powers, are connected with each other. Nevertheless this world is not the chaos it appears to be at first sight. The point at issue for the Vedic thinker is not to disentangle and differentiate conceptually different entities and notions but to realize, to know, their connections” (1957:6). See also Chapter 5, n. 80.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;This corporeal liminality is seemingly built into the Vedic language itself. Gonda observes with respect to the enigmatic power expressed by the word bráhman that it belongs to a type of Indo-European terminology that blurs the distinction between “nomen actionis and nomen rei” (1950:72), that is between action and object. This blurring, which is in fact a blurring of identity, is a characteristic of Vedic thought, and it is most visible in bandhutās such as these.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Cf. Csordas 1990:1ff.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Cf. Gupta and Ferguson 1992 for the related term, “free-floating monad.”&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Marriott and Inden 1977; see also Marriott 1990.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Appadurai 1986:755.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Cf. Swami Vivekananda’s “vedāntafication” of the Ramakrishna Mission, amply demonstrated in Kripal 1995. See also Appadurai, who, summarizing Ashis Nandy’s argument (1983), writes that Swami Vivekananda “largely succumbed to the androcentric, linear, protestant, and activist strands in the dominant colonial culture” (1986:748).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Gupta 1995:10.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Robinet 1993:103.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Eck 1993:59.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Ibid.:59–60.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Ibid.:60.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Jung 1990:495, cited by Glucklich 1997:53.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Glucklich 1997:53.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;See also Orsi: “Western styles of knowledge, which typically give priority to detachment over engagement, to textuality over vocality, to mind over body, are to be exposed to radically different ways of constructing and inhabiting reality” (2001:109). This, he asserts, runs counter to the priorities of the “once-dominated” and “once-oppressed” other. Doubtless this is largely true. However, one of the facets of Indian orthodoxy is that this allegedly Western style of knowledge is also true of it, though one may argue that the facets of Indian orthodoxy that interested Christian-inspired Western intellectuals were the ones most framed in this manner. The reliance of mainstream brahmanical śāstra on reason and logic appealed to Western intellectuals, especially the discourses of Nyāya, Vedānta, and Theravada Buddhism. Poetics (alaṃkāraśāstra) was taken slightly less seriously, as was Purāṇa, and, of course, Tantra and bhakti literature. All of these were more embodied, vocal, and engaged, and were it not for the intriguing character of their antiquity, most of the vedic literature would have met with the same fate, as the oft-cited derogatory comments of Max Müller, Julius Eggeling, and others testify. For these, see Tull 1989, ch. 1.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Cf. Kjaerholm, who states: “We do not really believe that a person can be possessed by spirits or the devil or what have you. Although this was a common belief in medieval Europe it is not generally held now, certainly not by social scientists” (1982:184).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;See Bynum 2001, which examines twelfth- and thirteenth-century narratives of metamorphosis and hybridity.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Recall Varahamihira’s warning (Chapter 11) to astrologers against the use of possession.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Yocum 1982:193.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Kripal 1995:271. Kripal does not distinguish between possession and ecstatic vision (72, passim). The Kathāmṛta 4.232 contains “a self-description of how the saint’s ecstatic states used to possess him like ghosts until he finally could expel them out through his bowels” (Kripal 1995:335).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Bhattacharyya (1986) also demonstrates this in her work on cultural configurations of insanity.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;I have used the word “intermedial” for this state; see F. Smith 2004.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;In spite of the active participation of brahmans in non-brahmanic possession ritual, certain artifacts of brahmanical inhibitions remain in their performance. William Sax informs me that the bodies of low-caste people in possession gyrate more wildly than those of upper-caste members.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Bynum 2001:31.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Thus Gombrich can argue that “both brahmanism and Buddhism oppose possession and commend self-control, while the communal religion of the Sinhalese, as of the Indian, village centres, and has probably always centred, on a cult of local deities whose priests become possessed and so act as mediums to help villagers solve their problems” (1988:145).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Humphrey and Laidlaw see this at work in contemporary India as well, in the Jain stance towards emotional engagement in religious practice. They write, “The more puritan of our informants disapproved of [episodes of emotional engagement], in the same way, one imagines, that ‘enthusiasm’ was frostily dismissed in the eighteenth-century Church of England” (1994:228).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Pollock 1990:333.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Biardeau 1989a:21–22.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;White discusses “vernacular ritual strategies” in his undated and not yet published paper. This is not quite identical to what I am positing here, but the article presents more evidence of the influence of “vernacular” practices on Sanskrit textuality, thus broadening the perimeters of Sanskritic culture beyond what many, including Pollock, might contend. This effectively broadens the discourse of power in Sanskritic culture, reshaping at least these elements of it to reach beyond the Mīmāṃsā-laden orthodoxy.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Hiltebeitel 1989b:450. We might also here consider Haberman’s description (1988:98ff., 137ff.) of male practitioners of rāgānugabhakti sadhana who wear women’s clothes. This is not mentioned in any Sanskrit text before the eighteenth century, but its presence as part of the local tradition supports and strengthens Rūpa Gosvāmī’s textuality of this sādhana in the Bhaktirasāmṛtasindhu.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Thus, textual, performative, and religious traditions like those arising out of the Nāṭyaśāstra and certain Purāṇas and Tantras, as well as vernacular literatures expressing the same human religious concerns, may thus be correct in envisioning themselves as the fifth Veda. On this, see F. Smith 1994.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Miles 1997:59.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Shulman 1994:1.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Ibid.:25.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;See the descriptions of the nāga in Chapter 12, from bhutavidyā accounts in Sanskrit and Tibetan medical texts. These, however, do not square with what we have here. This is not the place to enter into a study of nāgas; it is sufficient to note that they occupy a place of great importance in the MBh. Generally, they are depicted as water spirits who also possess the secrets of the earth. They are alternately dangerous, poisonous, and helpful, with a reputation for divination. They may be exotic serpents or half-human and half-serpent (as appears to be the case here). In Tibet the iconography is somewhat clearer. There a nāga is typically depicted with a divination arrow and a jewel in its hands (cf. Nebesky-Wojkowitz 1956:305).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The story is much less complete in the Rāmāyaṇa; cf. Rām 144.15ff., esp. verse 18, and Goldman 1984:210 and notes.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Cf. Wadley 1999. This is perhaps not so odd, as the peripheral nature of this episode (ākhyāna) to the main action of the epic renders this aspect of it dispensable. Nor is it depicted in Draupadī epic performances in Tamilnadu or Garhwal. Neither Nala nor Damayantī are mentioned by Hiltebeitel in his Draupadī volumes or by Sax in Dancing the Self. As mentioned earlier, the Jain story of Nala excises the possession completely; he is an archetypal good king who ends up renouncing the world.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Shulman 1994:27.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
