<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;0 on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/tantric-divine-feminine/0/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;0 on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/tantric-divine-feminine/0/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 Acknowledgments</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/tantric-divine-feminine/0/01_Acknowledgments/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/tantric-divine-feminine/0/01_Acknowledgments/</guid>
      <description>I first became aware of the group of Hindu goddesses known as the ten Mahavidyas while conducting research on the goddess Kali in Calcutta during the academic year 1968-69. Kali is nearly always listed as the first of this group often unusual goddesses and in many ways is the exemplary Mahavidya. It was not until 1983-84 in Varanasi, however, that I began to undertake detailed research on this group. With the help of a fellowship from the Canadian Social Sciences and Humanities Research Council, I investigated literary sources and did field research on Mahavidya temples, iconography, and worship.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>02 Introduction</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/tantric-divine-feminine/0/02_Introduction/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/tantric-divine-feminine/0/02_Introduction/</guid>
      <description>What is one to make of a group of goddesses that includes a goddess who cuts her own head off, another who prefers to be offered polluted items by devotees who themselves are in a state of pollution, one who sits on a corpse while pulling the tongue of a demon, another who has sex astride a male consort who is lying on a cremation pyre, another whose couch has as its legs four great male gods of the Hindu pantheon, another who prefers to be worshiped in a cremation ground with offerings of semen, and yet another who is a haglike widow?</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
