<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;अधिदैवम् Meta-God on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;अधिदैवम् Meta-God on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Benefits</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/benefits/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/benefits/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;na vā are devānāṃ kāmāya devāḥ priyā bhavanti&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ātmanastu kāmāya devāḥ priyā bhavanti |&lt;br&gt;&#xA;na vā are vedānāṃ kāmāya vedāḥ priyā bhavanti&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ātmanastu kāmāya vedāḥ priyā bhavanti |&lt;br&gt;&#xA;(Bṛhadāraṇyaka Upaniṣad 4.5.6)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Devās are loved, not for their sake,&lt;br&gt;&#xA;but for the sake of the Self&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vedas are loved, not for their sake,&lt;br&gt;&#xA;but for the sake of the Self&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;A poetic imaginative way of thinking is involved in abstracting and shaping thought in terms of devatA-s, mantra-s, nyAsa-s, yajJNa-s and &lt;a href=&#34;../myth/&#34;&gt;stories&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;deva-s are very powerful forces in their capacity to help us intellectually and emotionally distinguish the noble from the ignoble (the emotional cultivation being the dominant contribution). It helps us develop positive qualities and good aspirations in a very deliberate, yet very enjoyable way. As an example, consider the following mundane example: &amp;ldquo;For a straight back, imagine your head hangs from a thread (ballerinas do).&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Among other things, this reverence of awesome nature and upholders of dharma engenders reverence for nature, and renews of faith in the grandest ideals of this dharma.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;It may even improve our performance at various tasks.&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Example: The ancestor effect: Thinking about our genetic origin enhances intellectual performance (article &lt;a href=&#34;http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/ejsp.778/abstract&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Not answering prayer stuff (considered in a separate subsection).&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Personal note: - To me, the influence of (connection with) the deva-s is limited to being the influence of concepts, symbols and perception on minds (and ultimately behavior) - yet what satisfying influence that can be!&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;answering-prayers-or-not&#34;&gt;Answering prayers, or not.&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The greatest value of deva-s is in the realm of feelings and sentiment, as explained elsewhere. Answering material requests (like some ATM) is secondary.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Importantly, the deva-s mostly do not alter or abort the laws of the universe (which makes sense because they are themselves part of Rta framework). As GA said: &amp;ldquo;Too many people think tantra is about churning out supernatural effects that defy the operating laws of the universe at an extremely visible, public level. NO. Such effects are known &amp;amp; do exist, albeit at a private level.&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;An illustrative example: From bhAgavata-purANa 10.24, the central message of kRShNa is &amp;ldquo;Indra does not cause rains; it is karma and natural processes. You ought to adore karma instead.&amp;rdquo;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;He then asks the cowherds to adore the hillock and cattle. This, considering the preceding message, is but symbolic and about as meaningful emotionally (to the cowherds) as appeasing the clouds.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;So, at best, the govardhana incident can be considered an argument against deities that answer to material requests of humans; while endorsing the continuation of pUja as an emotional and symbolic act.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Choosing</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/choosing/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/choosing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;one-vs-many&#34;&gt;One vs many&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Pros and cons in either case:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Adoring the many:&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;More accommodating of other cults&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Better explanation of vagaries of nature:&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Illustration from Illiad, where the devatAs themselves take sides in desperate battles on behalf of their human kin! That this happens is telling. Jupiter clearly reigns as the first among equals, rather than as puppet-master.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Focusing on the one supreme:&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;There is an essential regularity in the universe. There is the question of the ultimate cause.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;But it can be more monotonous.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;dharma-subversion-danger&#34;&gt;dharma subversion danger&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;शास्त्रेषु विहिता एव स्युः पूजनीया देवता इति न। किन्तु, शास्त्रेतर-दैवतेषु पूजायोग्यता चिन्तनीयैव।&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;तत्राऽपि मानुषाणाम् आधुनिकानाम्। यथोन्मत्तानाम् अब्राह्म-मूलानां म्लेच्छानां पूज्यो राक्षसो न पूजामर्हत्य् आर्याणाम्, यथा च हिरण्यकशिपुर् नार्हत् परमपूजां पितृत्वेन प्रह्लादपूजापात्रञ्चेदपि तथैव सायिम्लेच्छस्यपूजायाम् अस्त्येवापत्तिः। किन्नाम - सा पूजा ऽऽर्य-म्लेच्छ-भेद-भावनां निवारयति, कपटेन वैदिकता+उन्मादयोस् साम-रस्यं सम्पादयति जन-मनस्स्व् इत्य् अस्मासु जनयेद् भीतिम् महतीम् राष्ट्र-धर्म-हितकाङ्क्षिषु। यथा शबरीमल-यात्रायां वावर-पूजाम् अन्यथा व्याख्यान्त एवम् एव कुर्वन्तो दृश्यन्ते।&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;अत्र देहस्य &amp;ldquo;immune system&amp;rdquo; निदर्शनरूपेण गृह्यताम्। AIDS-रोग-ग्रस्थानां देहेषु निजपरतत्त्वभेदशक्तिर् भवति नष्टा। ओषध्यभावे शीघ्रमेव परजीवाणुभिर् आक्रान्तास् तद्देहा मिर्यन्ते।&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;nastika-deities&#34;&gt;nAstika deities&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Some nAstika deities are represented as trampling Astika ones, and protecting the inimical buddha-shAsana. Astika-s should approach the bauddha deva-s only if  they are strong, confident and mature enough to clearly understand this and even deploy the so called &amp;ldquo;buddha-shAsana-rakShaka-s&amp;rdquo; against the bauddha-s themselves.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Connection</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/connection/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/connection/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Gods are conscious entities with whom we can connect (given mutual desire and effort).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Connecting with them can elevate us in myriad ways (See &lt;a href=&#34;benefits&#34;&gt;benefits&lt;/a&gt; page).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The Gods gain NOTHING from connecting to us, or receiving our adoration. They don&amp;rsquo;t &amp;ldquo;feed&amp;rdquo; on our adulation. They are perfectly satisfied and complete - even if no human exists.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;We can be disconnected from the Gods due to spread of mental diseases (atheisms including so-called monotheisms). In such a case one has to work hard for generations to reestablish solid connection (like 20th century western pagan revivalists).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;deva-bhakta-relationship&#34;&gt;Deva-bhakta relationship&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We emphasize that to a practicing hindu, they are not remotely abstract entities like Jupiter, Mars, Neptune, Juno are to (sadly) Christianized Italians; rather they are alive and immediate in the artistic experience that is the hindu way of thought. One propitiates them regularly with various rituals (In fact, I am more observant than most) as if they were wilful entities, and questions about their imaginary nature never enter my mind when involved with hindu rituals. It is a primeval way of looking at nature and life. IshAna still lives in our rage, Indra in our stength, prithivI/ Earth in our body, herbs in our hair, sarasvatI on the tip of my tongue, agni in my speech and so on. (A lament on the fools that chose to leave this for the monotony and paleness of Abrahamisms &lt;a href=&#34;http://agnimaan.wordpress.com/2015/01/13/the-fools-that-converted/&#34;&gt;is here&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generality</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/generality/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/generality/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Every God (or God family) is capable of doing all things for the devotee. This is inpsite of being closely associated with a particular trait (Eg. bRhaspati as the guru, indra as warrior, savitR as the impeller).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Just because a doctor heals well, it does not mean that he disappears as soon as he removes his coat. He can fight and engineer as well.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In a sense, the basic essence of other Gods is present in every God - there is just a difference in emphasis. So, in inspired hymns, God X may say: &amp;ldquo;I am Agni, I am Indra etc..&amp;rdquo; When Agni is &amp;ldquo;angry&amp;rdquo;, it is as if the rudra aspect shines forth through him - or as if rudra fully cooperates with him, lending his features (in line with the &lt;a href=&#34;../harmony&#34;&gt;harmony&lt;/a&gt; of the Gods).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Harmony</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/harmony/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/harmony/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;intro&#34;&gt;Intro&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Key thing is cognizance of harmony among the deva-s - hierarchy or respect for other possible hierarchies is hair-splitting which mostly only serves polemics.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The hard &amp;ldquo;good vs evil&amp;rdquo; dichotomy is absent in the hindu milieu, as described &lt;a href=&#34;../non-evil/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Rather, there is the &amp;ldquo;higher&amp;rdquo; vs &amp;ldquo;lower&amp;rdquo; gradation.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;reconciling-mythic-superiority-claims&#34;&gt;Reconciling mythic superiority claims&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;If subrahmaNya is subordinate to shiva or indra or if durgA is created by other deities, it is because he/ she consents to it (in the context of the particular myth). So, this willing subordination in a particular context does not necessarily imply lower power - just condescension.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Ideas such as moha-shAstra, lower-vidyA etc.. help reconciliation.&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;arthavAda and nahi-nindA-nyAya&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The nature of myth. Even though myths meant to help devotional practice and adoration centered on a certain deity show conflicts and even denigration of deities - they are not to be taken literally.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The idea of &lt;a href=&#34;../generality&#34;&gt;generality&lt;/a&gt; implies that the &amp;ldquo;essence or emphasis&amp;rdquo; of God A is anyway in God B - so praise of God A is indirect praise for even God B.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;meaning-as-cult-competition&#34;&gt;Meaning as cult-competition&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Myths / imagery of one deity killing or trampling other may be understood as serving cult competition. This does not affect factual harmony amongst the Gods when understood as:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multiplicity</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/multiplicity/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/multiplicity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Polytheism is the art of discovering divine multiplicity &amp;amp; is perfectly compatible with monism, pantheism, panentheism, henotheism &amp;amp; even monolatry in some forms. - GA&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Gods are multiple (whether or not they arose from a single being before time). This is clear from the experience they granted to our ancestors the Arya-s - with different names, lores and rituals. There is no good reason to reduce them to &amp;ldquo;angels&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;demigods&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;facets&amp;rdquo; of the same entity - it suffices to acknowledge their &lt;a href=&#34;../generality&#34;&gt;generality&lt;/a&gt; and the provisional nature of their &lt;a href=&#34;../myth&#34;&gt;myths&lt;/a&gt;. They may even be innumerable - with more Gods revealing themselves to us under changing spatio-temporal and social circumstances. Tradition holds that their number is large in comparison to everyday numbers.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Myths</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/myth/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/myth/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The particular stories of deva-s (such as battles with asura-s) are not to be taken literally, according to the veda-s and upaniShats themselves.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;To derive benefits from the deva-s, one does not need epistemological belief in peripheral things like flying yogi-s, texts composing themselves and the like (even, from the perspective of brahma-jnana - reincarnation, deities proffering boons).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;At the same time, the hindu need not let questions like &amp;ldquo;How can monkeys talk?&amp;rdquo; hinder his enjoyment of the rAmAyaNa epics or his observance of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rama_Navami&#34;&gt;rAmanavamI&lt;/a&gt; rituals. The wise should know what the Gods and sages intend to communicate in the language of myth.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;implications&#34;&gt;Implications&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The nature of myths easily implies non-absoluteness/ non-literalness of texts (More in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AgamaH/AryaH/hinduism/sAmya-vaiShamye/bases&#34;&gt;bases/books page&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;benefits&#34;&gt;Benefits&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;These stories intend to teach us other things, such as&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;how to visualize and adore the deva-s&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;how to think and feel about our own (internal and social) conflicts and situations.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;In &lt;a href=&#34;http://musingsofhh.wordpress.com/2012/09/23/german-christian-in-dialogue-with-balinese-on-ramayanas-historicity/&#34;&gt;this conversation&lt;/a&gt; between a bAlinese hindu and a German christian about the historicity of rAMa, the pestered hindu asks: “Do you want to know whether the story is true, or merely whether it occurred?” [Orientalism and Religion: Post-Colonial Theory, India and “The Mystic East” By Richard King, pp. 39-40].&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;राम-तापिन्याम् अपि -&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-evil</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/non-evil/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/non-evil/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The hard &amp;ldquo;good vs evil&amp;rdquo; dichotomy is absent in the hindu milieu. Rather, there is the &amp;ldquo;higher&amp;rdquo; vs &amp;ldquo;lower&amp;rdquo; gradation.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Yet, Hindu tradition is quite clear in Astika traditions being &amp;ldquo;higher&amp;rdquo; - eg. shatravo anindrA in shruti [&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/blog_supplement/status/777684561954242572&#34;&gt;MT16&lt;/a&gt;].&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;There is no hard &amp;ldquo;good vs evil&amp;rdquo; dualism seen in dichotomoies such as:&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;the semitic God vs Devil.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Zoroastrian ahura mAzDa vs anghri mainyu or asura-adorers vs deva-adorers.&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;daeva-s and asura-s came from the same pantheon. But - &amp;ldquo;Some deities have been sharply bifurcated. For instance: indra. indra as such is a despised &amp;ldquo;daeva&amp;rdquo; while verethragna (vRtrAghna/vRtrahan, an epithet of indra) is a revered yazata.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;asura-s-raxasa-s&#34;&gt;asura-s, rAxasa-s&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Texts mention asura-s (including daitya-s like hiraNyakashipu and bali, dAnava-s like maya) and rAxasa-s (like rAvaNa)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;asura is used as an apithet of varuNa, rudra and, wait, indra himself in the Rgveda&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;one of the classic (but obscure to modern hindu) synonyms for asura-s is &amp;ldquo;पूर्वदेव&amp;rdquo; (= former deva-s, now fallen into a corrupt station)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Stories of asura-deva-battles are not to be taken literally, according to the veda-s themselves (eg: &lt;a href=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/11/01/6/&#34;&gt;shatapatha-brAhmaNa asura-parAbhava part in 11.1.6.8-10&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/eggeling/11/01/6/&#34;&gt;eggling&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;adoration&#34;&gt;Adoration&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Even many demons are ultimately redeemable (often at the cost of being terminated by a deva)!&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Aspects of asura-s, rAkShasa-s etc.. are adored, without rejecting the deva-s (who are presumed to be at the top anyway).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;niRRti is the dikpAla of the South West.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Many are the oblations to various bhUta-s. Then there are oblations to pUtana etc.. during the jAtakarma ritual&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;mahiShAsura is adored, having been syncretized with mhasoba (&lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2003/08/30/kasar-gavlis/&#34;&gt;MT&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/blog_supplement/status/703648579211149312&#34;&gt;MT_TW&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Despite their many bad qualities, rAvaNa (and several rAkShasa-s) had many great qualities - devotion, ability to do great penance, vigor etc.. All this is acknowledged. In fact, rAvaNa too is adored as a minor deity in certain shaiva systems.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;distinctions&#34;&gt;Distinctions&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;In several works, the distinction between asura-s and rAxasa-s is clear.&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;rAmAyaNa &lt;a href=&#34;https://imgur.com/BTgmS4S&#34;&gt;IMG&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;amarakosha&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;असुरा दैत्यदैतेयदनुजेन्द्रारिदानवाः। शुक्रशिष्या दितिसुताः पूर्वदेवाः सुरद्विषः॥&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;राक्षसः कौणपः क्रव्यात्क्रव्यादोऽस्रप आशरः॥&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;asura and rAxasa-s don&amp;rsquo;t seem functionally different. We have a vRtra juxtaposed with a rAvaNa, a prahlAda juxtaposed with vibhIShaNa. Some asura-s and some rAxasa-s are venerated.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;subversive-use&#34;&gt;Subversive use&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;In modern times, people have used this absence of dichotomy to subvert hindus.&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;JNU fiction about the &amp;ldquo;asur&amp;rdquo; tribe and durga: &lt;a href=&#34;https://trueindology.wordpress.com/2016/02/27/jnu-and-the-saga-of-calumny/&#34;&gt;TI16&lt;/a&gt;. However, their clear anti-hindu antecedents make it easy for orthodox hindu-s to avoid confusion [&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/GhorAngirasa/status/703922268376846336&#34;&gt;TW16&lt;/a&gt;].&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Polycentric field</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/polycentric_field/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/polycentric_field/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;intro&#34;&gt;Intro&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Definition: Mutual acknowledgement of certain multiple Gods (whatever the center) and intimate entanglement between their lores and cults defines a polycentric social field.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;At a population level, that there is a &amp;ldquo;multiplicity of positive existential commitments&amp;rdquo; regarding the supreme deity is an empirical fact beyond dispute. Eg. Hinduism.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;examples&#34;&gt;Examples:&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Acknowledgement of multiple deities who can each be treated as the center is clear in the vedic lore. [&lt;a href=&#34;http://indiafacts.org/polycentrism-many-one-problem-roots-yoga/#.VF0zlBFGjUZ&#34;&gt;MT&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Of a dramatist-philosopher-logician from 10th century, jayanta bhaTTa whose work serves as a prototype for the religion/counter-religion distinction and also alludes to the &amp;rsquo;tacit recognition&amp;rsquo; we speak of&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Provability by science</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/provability_by_science/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/provability_by_science/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;problem&#34;&gt;Problem&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Gods have two kinds of activities - impersonal (by which they &amp;ldquo;run&amp;rdquo; the universe) and personal (by which they grace their devotees). The former can subsumed by the scientific laws of nature, leaving the latter to be questioned by skeptics. Here we consider possible justifications for the latter from a quasi-scientific point of view.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;potential-data---divine-experiences&#34;&gt;Potential data - Divine experiences&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;siddhi-s.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;rAmAnujan&amp;rsquo;s dreams&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;sagely inspiration&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;samAvesha with the deities (This is highly valued and actively sought after by practitioners.)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
