<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;अधिदैवम् Meta-God on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;अधिदैवम् Meta-God on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 26 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Benefits</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/benefits/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/benefits/</guid>
      <description>Summary na vā are devānāṃ kāmāya devāḥ priyā bhavanti
ātmanastu kāmāya devāḥ priyā bhavanti |
na vā are vedānāṃ kāmāya vedāḥ priyā bhavanti
ātmanastu kāmāya vedāḥ priyā bhavanti |
(Bṛhadāraṇyaka Upaniṣad 4.5.6)
Devās are loved, not for their sake,
but for the sake of the Self
Vedas are loved, not for their sake,
but for the sake of the Self
A poetic imaginative way of thinking is involved in abstracting and shaping thought in terms of devatA-s, mantra-s, nyAsa-s, yajJNa-s and stories.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Choosing</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/choosing/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/choosing/</guid>
      <description>One vs many Pros and cons in either case:
Adoring the many: More accommodating of other cults Better explanation of vagaries of nature: Illustration from Illiad, where the devatAs themselves take sides in desperate battles on behalf of their human kin! That this happens is telling. Jupiter clearly reigns as the first among equals, rather than as puppet-master. Focusing on the one supreme: There is an essential regularity in the universe.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Connection</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/connection/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/connection/</guid>
      <description>Gods are conscious entities with whom we can connect (given mutual desire and effort). Connecting with them can elevate us in myriad ways (See benefits page). The Gods gain NOTHING from connecting to us, or receiving our adoration. They don&amp;rsquo;t &amp;ldquo;feed&amp;rdquo; on our adulation. They are perfectly satisfied and complete - even if no human exists. We can be disconnected from the Gods due to spread of mental diseases (atheisms including so-called monotheisms).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Generality</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/generality/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/generality/</guid>
      <description>Every God (or God family) is capable of doing all things for the devotee. This is inpsite of being closely associated with a particular trait (Eg. bRhaspati as the guru, indra as warrior, savitR as the impeller).
Just because a doctor heals well, it does not mean that he disappears as soon as he removes his coat. He can fight and engineer as well.
In a sense, the basic essence of other Gods is present in every God - there is just a difference in emphasis.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Harmony</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/harmony/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/harmony/</guid>
      <description>Intro Key thing is cognizance of harmony among the deva-s - hierarchy or respect for other possible hierarchies is hair-splitting which mostly only serves polemics. The hard &amp;ldquo;good vs evil&amp;rdquo; dichotomy is absent in the hindu milieu, as described here. Rather, there is the &amp;ldquo;higher&amp;rdquo; vs &amp;ldquo;lower&amp;rdquo; gradation. Reconciling mythic superiority claims If subrahmaNya is subordinate to shiva or indra or if durgA is created by other deities, it is because he/ she consents to it (in the context of the particular myth).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Multiplicity</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/multiplicity/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/multiplicity/</guid>
      <description>Polytheism is the art of discovering divine multiplicity &amp;amp; is perfectly compatible with monism, pantheism, panentheism, henotheism &amp;amp; even monolatry in some forms. - GA
The Gods are multiple (whether or not they arose from a single being before time). This is clear from the experience they granted to our ancestors the Arya-s - with different names, lores and rituals. There is no good reason to reduce them to &amp;ldquo;angels&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;demigods&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;facets&amp;rdquo; of the same entity - it suffices to acknowledge their generality and the provisional nature of their myths.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Myths</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/myth/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/myth/</guid>
      <description>Summary The particular stories of deva-s (such as battles with asura-s) are not to be taken literally, according to the veda-s and upaniShats themselves. To derive benefits from the deva-s, one does not need epistemological belief in peripheral things like flying yogi-s, texts composing themselves and the like (even, from the perspective of brahma-jnana - reincarnation, deities proffering boons). At the same time, the hindu need not let questions like &amp;ldquo;How can monkeys talk?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Non-evil</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/non-evil/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/non-evil/</guid>
      <description>The hard &amp;ldquo;good vs evil&amp;rdquo; dichotomy is absent in the hindu milieu. Rather, there is the &amp;ldquo;higher&amp;rdquo; vs &amp;ldquo;lower&amp;rdquo; gradation. Yet, Hindu tradition is quite clear in Astika traditions being &amp;ldquo;higher&amp;rdquo; - eg. shatravo anindrA in shruti [MT16]. There is no hard &amp;ldquo;good vs evil&amp;rdquo; dualism seen in dichotomoies such as: the semitic God vs Devil. Zoroastrian ahura mAzDa vs anghri mainyu or asura-adorers vs deva-adorers. daeva-s and asura-s came from the same pantheon.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Polycentric field</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/polycentric_field/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/polycentric_field/</guid>
      <description>Intro Definition: Mutual acknowledgement of certain multiple Gods (whatever the center) and intimate entanglement between their lores and cults defines a polycentric social field.
At a population level, that there is a &amp;ldquo;multiplicity of positive existential commitments&amp;rdquo; regarding the supreme deity is an empirical fact beyond dispute. Eg. Hinduism. Examples: Acknowledgement of multiple deities who can each be treated as the center is clear in the vedic lore. [MT]
Of a dramatist-philosopher-logician from 10th century, jayanta bhaTTa whose work serves as a prototype for the religion/counter-religion distinction and also alludes to the &amp;rsquo;tacit recognition&amp;rsquo; we speak of&amp;hellip;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Provability by science</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/provability_by_science/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/provability_by_science/</guid>
      <description>Problem The Gods have two kinds of activities - impersonal (by which they &amp;ldquo;run&amp;rdquo; the universe) and personal (by which they grace their devotees). The former can subsumed by the scientific laws of nature, leaving the latter to be questioned by skeptics. Here we consider possible justifications for the latter from a quasi-scientific point of view.
Potential data - Divine experiences siddhi-s.
rAmAnujan&amp;rsquo;s dreams
sagely inspiration
samAvesha with the deities (This is highly valued and actively sought after by practitioners.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
