<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;3 INTRODUCTION on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/0/3_INTRODUCTION/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;3 INTRODUCTION on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/0/3_INTRODUCTION/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 Veda</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/0/3_INTRODUCTION/01_Veda/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/0/3_INTRODUCTION/01_Veda/</guid>
      <description>After explorations of the ethnography and linguistics of possession in (mostly) postclassical South Asia, we turn to the Sanskrit texts. First, we consider the extensive evidence for possession and models of thought based on possession in the vedic literature (Chapter 5). References to possession begin in the Ṛgveda itself, where we first encounter the word āveśa (and other forms derived from the root ā√viś) in the ninth maṇḍala, the book that includes most of the soma hymns.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>02 Itihāsas</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/0/3_INTRODUCTION/02_ItihAsas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/0/3_INTRODUCTION/02_ItihAsas/</guid>
      <description>Possession comes into its own as a literary motif with accompanying procedural specificity in the Mahābhārata, a subject addressed in Chapter 6. Among the possession stories in this great epic are
the well-known tale of Nala’s possession by Kali; another in which Vipula Bhārgava protected Ruci, the wife of his guru, Devaśarman, against the sexual advances of the notorious womanizer Indra by entering (anupravisya) the body of Ruci through his yoga-power;+++(5)+++ the account in the Sauptikaparvan of Asvatthaman’s destructive possession by Rudra/śiva; and the account near the end of the epic in which Vidura, an incarnation of Dharma, employs his yogic abilities to leave his own body, permanently, and enter that of Yudhiṣṭhira.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>03 Purāṇas</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/0/3_INTRODUCTION/03_PurANas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/0/3_INTRODUCTION/03_PurANas/</guid>
      <description>Taking rhetorical leads from the epics, many of the Purāṇas frame possession in the same way; indeed, possession in the same key appears in the Purāṇas with remarkable regularity. It is no exaggeration to say that the Mahābhārata is the most influential text in Indian history, and the tone and timbre of possession, in both its positive and negative manifestations, is established in the Sanskrit epics.+++(4)+++ Because of certain important conceptual links between the epics and the Purāṇas, specifically the way devotion frames possession, it is essential to have a brief look at possession in the Purāṇas as well.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>04 Darśanas</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/0/3_INTRODUCTION/04_Darshanas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/0/3_INTRODUCTION/04_Darshanas/</guid>
      <description>Among the most visible manifestations of early Indian thought are Vedānta, classical Yoga, Buddhism, and Jainism, all of which are nuanced reactions to the perceived excesses of vedic ritualism. Chapter 7 discusses possession in these important branches of knowledge. Although possession is not a primary concern of the literature of these schools, which, on the whole, avoids discussion of personal experience except in the vaguest, most normative, and most fragmentary ways, it is nevertheless mentioned and occasionally discussed at some length in their foundational philosophical texts.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>05 Classical fiction</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/0/3_INTRODUCTION/05_Classical_fiction/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/0/3_INTRODUCTION/05_Classical_fiction/</guid>
      <description>Chapter 8 explores possession in Sanskrit and other classical Indic fiction, drama, and aesthetic theory. In the same way that the 1973 film The Exorcist and Henry James’s 1898 novella The Turn of the Screw influenced (and were influenced by) the Western—particularly the Anglophone—imaginaire in its views and experience of possession as a nasty and terrifying phenomenon (discussed in Chapters 2 and 3), stories of possession in India influenced its experience and occupied a major place in the Indian imaginaire.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>06 bhakti</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/0/3_INTRODUCTION/06_bhakti/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/0/3_INTRODUCTION/06_bhakti/</guid>
      <description>Chapter 9 places possession in the context of devotional practice. This is perhaps the most important aspect of possession, as the intensity of personal engagement is revealed in both text and practice to be the signal determining feature in personality identification. And in India bhakti it is nearly always linked to an intensity driven by a single-minded love for the deity. Thus, in the context of devotional practice, personal identification with a deity is often interpreted as possession.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>07 Tantra and Āyurveda</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/0/3_INTRODUCTION/07_Tantra_and_Ayurveda/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/0/3_INTRODUCTION/07_Tantra_and_Ayurveda/</guid>
      <description>Chapters 10–13 address possession in Tantra and Āyurveda, discourses that must be examined together to some extent because they increasingly share the same intellectual context. It is here, for the most part, that the notion of possession as “grasping” or “seizing” (grahaṇa) is highlighted, “negative” possession brought on by a malevolent spirit (the influence of the Mahābhārata is also felt here). But this is only a part of the story, as it shares conceptual territory with the “positive” possession most often associated with deities, as well as with interpersonal possession found in texts ranging from the Ṛgveda to the Upaniṣads, the Mahābhārata (again), the Purāṇas, the texts of classical Yoga, and most other texts encountered in the earlier chapters.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>08 Medicalization</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/0/3_INTRODUCTION/08_Medicalization/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/0/3_INTRODUCTION/08_Medicalization/</guid>
      <description>The usual way in which the Sanskrit texts dealt with negative possession was to identify and classify invasive spirits in demonologies, then to medicalize their possession. The most important and influential texts undertaking this are the foundational works of Āyurveda, as well as a number of Tantras. I offer new translations of the relevant sections of the three primary Āyurvedic texts—the Caraka, Suśruta, and Aṣṭāṅgahṛdaya Saṃhitās—which provide specific demonologies in the context of discussions of insanity (unmāda).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>09 Astrology</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/0/3_INTRODUCTION/09_Astrology/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/0/3_INTRODUCTION/09_Astrology/</guid>
      <description>Because of the importance of astrology in Indian culture for at least two millennia, and because of the perception of planets as graspers or possessors (indeed, the Sanskrit word for “planet” is graha), I must also discuss passages from astrological texts, notably the Praśnamārga, dealing with possession. In summarizing the ritual and pharmacological aspects of exorcism recommended by various āyurvedic, tantric, and astrological texts, I bring into the discussion my own fieldwork on possession among these traditions as they are constituted in present-day Kerala.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>10 Conclusions</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/0/3_INTRODUCTION/10_Conclusions/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/0/3_INTRODUCTION/10_Conclusions/</guid>
      <description>The final chapter offers a few conclusions based on my years of living with this topic. The first identifies typologies of possession that are correlated with language use in order to elucidate the semantics, constituted within the sociolinguistics, of possession. Then follows a discussion of the influence of possession on notions of corporality and personal identity. Essentially, I conclude that possession was both a cause and a result of the generally accepted South Asian notion of a permeable embodiment.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
