<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;2 The Individual Mahāvidyās on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/tantric-divine-feminine/2_The_Individual_mahAvidyAs/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;2 The Individual Mahāvidyās on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/tantric-divine-feminine/2_The_Individual_mahAvidyAs/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 Kālī</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/tantric-divine-feminine/2_The_Individual_mahAvidyAs/01_kAlI/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/tantric-divine-feminine/2_The_Individual_mahAvidyAs/01_kAlI/</guid>
      <description>***The **Black **Goddess ***
She is the terrible one who has a dreadful face. She should be meditated upon as having disheveled hair and a garland of freshly cut human heads. She has four arms. In her upper left hand she holds a sword that has just been bloodied by the severed head that she holds in her lower left hand. Her upper right hand makes the gesture of assurance and her lower right hand, the sign of granting favors.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>02 Tārā</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/tantric-divine-feminine/2_The_Individual_mahAvidyAs/02_tArA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/tantric-divine-feminine/2_The_Individual_mahAvidyAs/02_tArA/</guid>
      <description>***The **Goddess **Who **Guides **through **Troubles ***
In lists of the Mahavidyas, Tara almost always follows Kali. This suggests a certain importance in the group. Indeed, she is more like Kali in appearance than any of the other Mahavidyas. As we shall see below, interpretations of her significance often come close to those of Kali.
Tara occupies a central place in Tibetan Buddhism and to a great extent plays the role of a Tibetan national deity.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>03 Tripura-sundarī</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/tantric-divine-feminine/2_The_Individual_mahAvidyAs/03_tripura-sundarI/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/tantric-divine-feminine/2_The_Individual_mahAvidyAs/03_tripura-sundarI/</guid>
      <description>***She **Who **Is **Lovely **in **the **Three **Worlds ***
Tripura-sundari, who also appears in lists of the Mahavidyas under the names Sodasi, Lalita, Kamesvari, Srividya, and Rajarajesvari, is often cited third, after Kali and Tārā. She is also sometimes said to be, along with Kali and Tārā, an *adi *(primordial) Mahavidya, which suggests that she occupies a high place in the group, that she, like them, represents a complete vision of reality.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>04 Bhuvaneśvarī</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/tantric-divine-feminine/2_The_Individual_mahAvidyAs/04_bhuvaneshvarI/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/tantric-divine-feminine/2_The_Individual_mahAvidyAs/04_bhuvaneshvarI/</guid>
      <description>***She **Whose **Body **Is **the **World ***
Her complexion is vermillion in color. She has three eyes and wears a crown resplendent with jewels. She has the disk of the moon on her brow and has a smiling face. Her breasts are high and firm. In her two hands she holds a red lotus and a bowl filled with jewels. She is very peaceful and amiable. Her right foot rests on a jeweled jar.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>05 Chinnamastā</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/tantric-divine-feminine/2_The_Individual_mahAvidyAs/05_ChinnamastA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/tantric-divine-feminine/2_The_Individual_mahAvidyAs/05_ChinnamastA/</guid>
      <description>***The **Self-Decapitated **Goddess ***
Victory to the light of the world, giver of a good ending to the universe, to her whose forehead is lovely with charming locks.1
I meditate upon the Goddess Chinnamasta who is seated in the centre of the Sun&amp;rsquo;s disk and holds in her left hand her own severed head with gaping mouth, her hair is dishevelled and she is drinking the stream of blood gushing out from her own neck.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>06 Bhairavī</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/tantric-divine-feminine/2_The_Individual_mahAvidyAs/06_bhairavI/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/tantric-divine-feminine/2_The_Individual_mahAvidyAs/06_bhairavI/</guid>
      <description>***The **Fierce **One ***
She has a luminous complexion like a thousand rising suns. She wears silken red clothes and a garland of severed heads. Her breasts are smeared with blood. She has four arms: in two of her hands she holds a rosary and a book, and with her other two hands she makes the gestures of assurance and conferring boons. She has three eyes that resemble large lotuses. On her forehead is the half-moon and on her head a jeweled crown.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>07 Dhūmāvatī</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/tantric-divine-feminine/2_The_Individual_mahAvidyAs/07_dhUmAvatI/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/tantric-divine-feminine/2_The_Individual_mahAvidyAs/07_dhUmAvatI/</guid>
      <description>***The **Widow **Goddess ***
Dhumavati is ugly, unsteady, and angry. She is tall and wears dirty clothes. Her ears are ugly and rough, she has long teeth, and her breasts hang down. She has a long nose. She has the form of a widow. She rides in a chariot that has a banner on top decorated with a crow emblem. Her eyes are fearsome, and her hands tremble. In one hand she holds a winnowing basket, and with the other hand she makes the gesture of conferring boons.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>08 Bagalāmukhī</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/tantric-divine-feminine/2_The_Individual_mahAvidyAs/08_bagalAmukhI/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/tantric-divine-feminine/2_The_Individual_mahAvidyAs/08_bagalAmukhI/</guid>
      <description>***The **Paralyzer ***
In the middle of the ocean is a pavilion of jewels with an altar inside it. On the altar is a lion throne on which the goddess Bagalamukhi is seated. Her complexion is completely yellow, perfectly yellow, and she wears a yellow dress, yellow ornaments, and a yellow garland. I call to mind she who holds the tongue of the enemy in her left hand and a raised club in her right hand.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>09 Mātaṅgī</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/tantric-divine-feminine/2_The_Individual_mahAvidyAs/09_mAtangI/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/tantric-divine-feminine/2_The_Individual_mahAvidyAs/09_mAtangI/</guid>
      <description>***The **Outcaste **Goddess ***
She is seated on a corpse. Her clothes and all her ornaments are red. She wears a garland of *gunja *seeds [a small forest seed]. She is sixteen years old and has full breasts. She holds a skull and a sword in her two hands. She should be offered leftovers *[uccista].1 *
She is blue in color and has the disc of the moon on her forehead.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>10 Kamalā</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/tantric-divine-feminine/2_The_Individual_mahAvidyAs/10_kamalA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/tantric-divine-feminine/2_The_Individual_mahAvidyAs/10_kamalA/</guid>
      <description>***The **Lotus **Goddess ***
She has a beautiful golden complexion. She is being bathed by four large elephants who pour jars of nectar over her. In her four hands she holds two lotuses and makes the signs of granting boons and giving assurance. She wears a resplendant crown and a silken dress. I pay obeisance to her who is seated on a lotus in a lotus posture.1
Let Kamala protect us by her wonderful side-glances that delight the heart of Visnu.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
