<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/marutaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 25 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/marutaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Viṣṇu, the Marut-s and Rudra</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/marutaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2020-05-25_vie1b9a3e1b987u-the-marut-s-and-rudra/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/marutaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2020-05-25_vie1b9a3e1b987u-the-marut-s-and-rudra/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
This note might be read as a continuation of the these two earlier ones:
The Aśvin-s and Rudra The roots of Vaiṣṇavam: a view from the numerology of Vedic texts In the Ṛgveda (RV), the Marut-s are seen associating with Viṣṇu on several occasions. This often occurs in the context of the epithets evaya or eṣa (meaning swift or ardent) being applied to them. This association is not per say out of place or surprising because it might be seen in the context of Viṣṇu accompanying Indra in the battle against Vṛtra, where the Marut-s too accompany Indra as his troops (gaṇa-s).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>iShmin and the raudra devatA-s</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/marutaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2012-07-02_ishmin-and-the-raudra-devata-s/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jul 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/marutaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2012-07-02_ishmin-and-the-raudra-devata-s/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
[disclaimer: I tend to use Indicized spellings in most cases, which do not necessarily capture the Iranian pronunciation exactly. For my own Iranian studies I use the text of the avesta printed in an extended devanAgarI script which tends to capture the Iranian sound values well and also gives a sense of “script familiarity” while comparing it to the shruti].
For background: Iranian miscellany-1
pra ye me bandhveShe gAM vochanta sUrayaH pR^ishniM vochanta mAtaram |</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>maruts as &#34;para-skanda&#34; and other elements of their mythology</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/marutaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2007-07-25_maruts-as-para-skanda-and-other-elements-of-their-mythology/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jul 2007 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/marutaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2007-07-25_maruts-as-para-skanda-and-other-elements-of-their-mythology/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
Many deities undergo drastic changes when they move across the veda-purANa transition: Some lose status: e.g. indra; others lose status and change character e.g. varuNa; others rise to exalted heights e.g. viShNu and rudra. But their mythology is still rooted in large part in their vedic antecedents. The marut-s are one of the most important deities of the veda-s, praised by all clans of R^iShi-s in various hymns and rituals.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>VirUpAxa-dantAnjiH</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/marutaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/virUpAxa-dantAnjiH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/marutaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/virUpAxa-dantAnjiH/</guid>
      <description>Source: TW
The Virūpākṣa Dantāñji and related incantations of the Sāmavedin-s (to be elaborated later)
तपश् च तेजश् च श्रद्धा च ह्रीश् च सत्यं चा क्रोधश् च त्यागश् च धृतिश् च धर्मश् च सत्वं च वाक् च मनश् चात्मा च ब्रह्म च
तानि प्रपद्ये
तनि माम् अवन्तु ।
भूर् भुवः स्वर् ॐ । महान्तम् आत्मानं प्रपद्ये ॥
The heat (of asceticism), splendor, reverence, modesty, truth, wrath, forsaking, constancy, observance, goodness, speech, mind, consciousness, and mantra-power,</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>अञ्जि-सम्बन्धः</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/marutaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/anji-sambandhaH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/marutaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/anji-sambandhaH/</guid>
      <description>Vedic sense of a~nji has some mystery to it. It has a clear connection to the marut-s.
For e.g. we have in the RV: ye pR^iShatIbhir R^iShTibhiH sAkaM vAshIbhir a~njibhiH | ajAyanta svabhAnavaH || It is normally translated as unguent. In fact has an IE pedigree with that word. However, it is mentioned here with the weapons of the marut-s R^iShTi (spear) and vAshI (battle pickaxe).
Here again it is mentioned with the battle axe, armor and gauntlets: ye a~njiShu ye vAshIShu svabhAnavaH srakShu rukmeShu khAdiShu | &amp;hellip; The a~nji of the marut-s is also notably said to be brilliant white in color.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
