<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/indraH/meta/MT_lekhAH/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 19 Dec 2006 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/indraH/meta/MT_lekhAH/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Knowing indra</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/indraH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-12-19_knowing-indra/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Dec 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/indraH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-12-19_knowing-indra/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
The primary object of the Arya is to know indra:
satyaM hIndraH |
indra is verily the truth
taM hendra uvAcha mAm eva vijAnIhi |
And he told [pratardana daivodAsi] just perceive me
etad evAhaM manuShyAya hitatamaM manye yan mAM vijAnIyAt |
What I consider to be most beneficial to a human is that he should perceive me.
trishIrShANaM tvAShTram ahanam |
I killed the 3-headed son of tvaShTR^i.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>saH janAsaH indraH</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/indraH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-02-24_sah-janasah-indrah/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Feb 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/indraH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-02-24_sah-janasah-indrah/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
yáH sháshvato máhy éno dádhAnAn ámanyamAnAñ ChárvA jaghAna |
yáH shárdhate nAnudádAti shR^idhyAM yó dásyor hantA sá janAsa índraH ||
He who struck the evildoers, before even they realized, by shooting his arrow;
He who forgives not the boldness of those who provoke him, who kills the dasyu, he oh men is indra!
R brought to my attention the translation by Oldenburg, a grand old hero of the Indologists, of the hymn 4.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>In abode of the greatest one</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/indraH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-01-26_in-abode-of-the-greatest-one/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jan 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/indraH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-01-26_in-abode-of-the-greatest-one/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
vishvasmAd indra uttaraH |
indra is greater than all!
vishvAmitro ha vA indrasya priyaM dhAmopjagAma shastreNa cha vratacharyayA |
vishvAmitra indeed went to the dear abode of indra due to his vedic compositions and rites.
taM hendra uvAcha vishvAmitra varaM vR^iNIShveti |
To him indra said, “vishvAmitra, choose a boon”.
sa hovAcha vishvAmitras tvAM eva vijAIyAM iti |
vishvAmitra said: “let me know you”.
dvitIyaM iti | tvAm eveti | tR^itIyaM iti | tvAM eveti |</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I am indra</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/indraH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2003-11-27_i-am-indra/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2003 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/indraH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2003-11-27_i-am-indra/</guid>
      <description>I am indra ...{Loading}... Source: here.
I am indra,
I made divodAsa triumph over his foes.
I handed over the vItahavyas to pratardana,
I gave sumitra a 1000 rods to slay dirghajihvI of a 1000 orifices.
I am indra,
the drinker of soma, without limit.
In the sumada of soma I slew namuchi with my vajra concealed in foam.
I am Indra,
the brahman known by R^ishis, the entire universe.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>aindra-xAtra</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/indraH/meta/MT_lekhAH/aindra-xAtra/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/indraH/meta/MT_lekhAH/aindra-xAtra/</guid>
      <description>As I&amp;rsquo;ve said many times here, sometimes drawing the howls of the dull-witted, the aindra system of the core RV is superior to others. That, unlike the late Vedic prAjApatya system, privileges kShatra spirit inspired by the fort-breaking god himself. The sUkta of apratiratha aindra or the gautama&amp;rsquo;s long string of gAyatrI-s starting with &amp;ldquo;nakirindra…&amp;rdquo; is largely more inspiring than a prAjApatya lesson.
Another is the teaching of indra. What is more inspiring than indra cutting down the likes of trishiras tvAShTra or hurling shambara off the mountain for his Arya votary, the atithigva.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Realm of Indra</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/indraH/meta/MT_lekhAH/indra-realm/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/indraH/meta/MT_lekhAH/indra-realm/</guid>
      <description>The Realm Of Indra
Manasatarangini T May 10, 2022
(This article was published by IndiaFacts in 2015)
Indra is the Indo-Aryan version of the preeminent deity of the ancestral Indo-European pantheon. In the Vedic texts, we see remnants of what might have been an ancient tripartition of this deity, as manifest on the earth, in the atmosphere and in the heavens.+++(5)+++
In the first realm, he is manifest as a warrior who inspires men in battle and comes to the aid of his ārya worshipers who offer him rituals: in this form he is typically called Indra or Maghavan or Vṛtrahan.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>vajra</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/indraH/meta/MT_lekhAH/vajra/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/indraH/meta/MT_lekhAH/vajra/</guid>
      <description>vajra vs hammer Coming to the mace as you may have notice their euhemeric urge springs from the &amp;ldquo;earthly&amp;rdquo; representations in the Iranic world of the vazra as a ram-headed mace (again a conflation with the battering ram of indra mentioned in the RV) &amp;amp; Mjollnir of your folks. However, even in this a key Germanic peculiarity which illuminates the matter is ignored: the unexpected cognancy of hammer the weapon with word for sky Ger Himmel &amp;amp; Nordic himinn.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vedic tales</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/indraH/meta/MT_lekhAH/vedic-tales/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/indraH/meta/MT_lekhAH/vedic-tales/</guid>
      <description>aruNa section of the AraNyaka of the taittirIya-s includes the yajuSh-es on which the famous subrahmaNya sAman inviting indra to the soma offering is based:
indra who appeared as a ram to medhAtithi kANva; as a woman to vR^iShaNashva; who prances like a gaur bull; who became the lover of ahalyA; who became a brAhmaNa of the kaushika clan; who was called gautama. The anindra tradition that engulfed later H though misinterpret the original meanings of these special exploits of the supreme god by which the R^itvik pleases indra with singing of the subrahmaNya sAman.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
