<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;Limited devatas on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/limited_devatAs/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;Limited devatas on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/limited_devatAs/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>mantresha-s</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/limited_devatAs/mantreshaH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/limited_devatAs/mantreshaH/</guid>
      <description>Embodiment in text In one point of view, the dEvatAs are actually concepts (and associated powers) which exist in the form of mantras and even entire texts - see citations in V&amp;rsquo;s mantra page). Consonance with modern views - Vishwa Adluri - &amp;ldquo;Rama is in the rAmAyaNa&amp;rdquo; YT, AR. &amp;ldquo;रसो वै सः&amp;rdquo; इति श्रुतिः। Sound-body consciousness Via MT:
I would say the mantra-s are conscious (rather than living) with shabda-tanu just as a living being is conscious with an ANava-tanu.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Near Humans</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/limited_devatAs/near-humans/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/limited_devatAs/near-humans/</guid>
      <description>Among hindu-s Superhuman sky-travellers siddha-s, chAraNa-s, vidyAdhara-s gandharva-s yakSha-s asura-s and rAxasa-s (../also see non-evil page) vAnara-s and the like Possible inspiration from other coexisting homo-species Neanderthals and trolls and giants in Europe - NA16. Among non-hindu-s Titans Mostly imprisoned in Tartarus, but some were revered &amp;ldquo;Saturn is identified with Kronos, a Titan, and yet has an important cult in Rome. Rhea, when she is identified with Kybele, also has important cultus in the Hellenistic era.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Objects of wonder</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/limited_devatAs/objects_of_wonder/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/limited_devatAs/objects_of_wonder/</guid>
      <description>Intro Objects of wonder are worthy &amp;ldquo;bodies&amp;rdquo; for the Gods - good portals to access them. kRShNa says in the exceptionally brilliant chapter 10 bhagavad-gItA, after identifying himself with a long series of awesome things (such as &amp;ldquo;दण्डो दमयतामस्मि नीतिरस्मि जिगीषताम्&amp;rdquo;) : &amp;ldquo;यद्यद्विभूतिमत्सत्त्वं श्रीमदूर्जितमेव वा । तत्तदेवावगच्छ त्वं मम तेजोंऽशसम्भवम् ॥ ४१ ॥&amp;rdquo; - &amp;ldquo;All that is endowed with glory, grace, grandeur, has sprung from a mere flare of my radiance&amp;rdquo; (Dr.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
