<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;11 Tantra and the Diaspora of Childhood Possession on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/11_Childhood_Possession/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;11 Tantra and the Diaspora of Childhood Possession on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/11_Childhood_Possession/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 The Śaiva and Buddhist Tantras and the South Indian Texts</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/11_Childhood_Possession/01_The_shaiva_and_Buddhist_Tantras_and_the_South_Indian_Texts/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/11_Childhood_Possession/01_The_shaiva_and_Buddhist_Tantras_and_the_South_Indian_Texts/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Himalayan Śaiva and Buddhist Tantras that mention svasthāvesa are primarily dedicated to descriptions of the worship of Śiva and various goddesses. The Śaiva texts fall within a class called Siddhānta, rather than under the better-known but highly suspect designation “Kashmir Saivism.”3 Thus, the texts are not the commonly cited ones (by Abhinavagupta, Kṣemarāja, Utpaladeva, and their predecessors), but the lesser-known Jayadrathayāmala, Tantrasadbhāva, Sekoddeśa, Niśvāsaguhya, Bṛhatkālottara, and Cakrasaṃvarapiṇḍārtha.4 None of these except the Sekoddesa has been edited or published;5 the remaining ones exist in manuscript form only and have been examined almost solely by Alexis Sanderson.6 These texts undoubtedly represent but a few of what must have been a much greater number of Sanskrit texts that mentioned this and other similar apotropaic rituals current at the time. What is striking about svasthāvesa, and what occupies us here in part, is the remarkable continuity of these texts with certain early Chinese Buddhist tantric texts cited by Edward L. Davis in his recent volume Society and the Supernatural in Song China and Michel Strickmann in Mantras et Mandarins and, much more extensively, in Chinese Magical Medicine,7 as well as in later manuscripts written in Sanskrit and mixed Sanskrit and Telugu in South India dating to perhaps seven or eight centuries later.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02 Svasthāveśa and the Prasenā</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/11_Childhood_Possession/02_SvasthAvesha_and_the_Prasena/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/11_Childhood_Possession/02_SvasthAvesha_and_the_Prasena/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Of the two primary divisions of possession, involuntary and voluntary, the former found textual bases principally in the specialized fields of āyurvedic and tantric exorcistic literature.24 However, voluntary possession, particularly that with an oracular component, appears to have been regarded as more suitable material for textuality. Two reasons may be cited for this. First, because it could be practiced, hence prescribed—and, in general, prescription was formalized through literary production. Precedents for the commission of such material to the written word are found in the literature on omens and portents, dating back to the Vedic vidhāna literature,25 scattered passages from the Sanskrit epics, and the landmark works of the astrologer and mathematician Varāhamihira around 550 C.E.26 In addition, possession was experienced as a symptom of tantric initiation, as we have seen, and for this reason it took on greater soteriological, hence literary, urgency.27 Its commission to textuality was part of an ongoing process of domesticating the ever-receding fringe, part of the expansion of Sanskritic culture into new areas of discourse that extended from the periphery to the center. This is likely a case of Sanskritization in which popular practice was brought into the realm of brahmanical orthodoxy, albeit to a place on the fringe of such orthodoxy. Sanskritization in this case might have also mitigated the threat possession presented to more normative brahmanical orthodoxy.28 This threat was of a total and unrecognizable transcendence that undermined orthodox notions of purity and an independent and impermeable ātman or self. Transcendence achieved during a state of full possession, known to many but experienced by relatively few,29 not only eroded confidence in a stable self, which now hosted other voices, but also annihilated the wellformed and complex personality, the carefully, if culturally, crafted person that served as custodian to the self. Thus, possession negated both the metaphysical and social entities, the self and the person.30&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03 Epigraphical Evidence for the Practice of Svasthāveśa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/11_Childhood_Possession/03_Epigraphical_Evidence_for_the_Practice_of_SvasthAvesha/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/11_Childhood_Possession/03_Epigraphical_Evidence_for_the_Practice_of_SvasthAvesha/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We now turn to the Himalayan and eastern rite of svasthāvesa, not losing sight of our objective of comparing it to the manuscript material from China of the same period and southern India of later epochs. Although the relevant Tantras are themselves undated, Sanderson suggests that one of the earliest, the Nisvāsaguhya, could be a product of the sixth century, though it can be dated with certainty only to a single ninth-century Nepalese manuscript. Thus, Sanderson states that, though the Nisvāsaguhya “seems to be one of the very earliest Tantras of the Siddhānta,” it is nevertheless representative of “a tradition for which we have epigraphical evidence from the sixth century onwards.”59 Sanderson’s remaining texts, which describe svasthāvesa in greater complexity and variation, were composed at various times up to the twelfth century. The epigraphical evidence to which Sanderson refers is important because it helps establish a general dateline for the diffusion of svasthāvesa to China. This evidence exposes a Śaiva tradition from Central and South India that appears to have entered Kashmir only in the first few decades of the eighth century with the ascendancy of Lalitāditya, the wealthiest and most successful of Kashmir’s imperial monarchs. It is worth noting that Lalitāditya and his successors patronized both brahmanical sects and Buddhism, establishing a climate conducive for intellectual exchange. Given the strong tantric presence in Kashmir at that time, this active exchange of ideas quickly engendered a common tantric foundation for Hindu and Buddhist sects.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04 The Ritual of Svasthāveśa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/11_Childhood_Possession/04_The_Ritual_of_SvasthAvesha/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/11_Childhood_Possession/04_The_Ritual_of_SvasthAvesha/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;With this in mind, then, let us now turn again, briefly, to the Śaiva and Buddhist Tantras and to the ritual employment of the prasenā. The Niśvāsaguhya, the Tantrasadbhāva, the Cakrasaṃvarapiṇḍārtha, the Sekoddeśa, the Bṛhatkālottara, and, most importantly, the Jayadrathayāmala (JY), the latest and most compendious of these texts, present a complex intertextuality.68 So, it is fair to present a composite account of the ritual of svasthāveśa.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The texts state that the prasenā is a divinatory form assumed by a female deity (vidya) that appears before the practitioner during a ritual performed at a site sacred to Maheśvara (rudrasthāna) or in a temple to the goddess (mātṛgṛham). The practitioner, called mantrin, māntrika, or simply sādhaka, repeats (japa) relevant mantras one hundred, one hundred and eight, one hundred thousand, or five hundred thousand times. This empowers him to undertake the āvesa. In these Tantras this ritual is always presented by Śiva, sometimes called Bhairava, as a great and wondrous secret, in response to queries from his dialogic counterpart, the Goddess, who is given a large number of names. As a result of these mantra repetitions, a conjunction (saṃyoga) is forged with a prasenā, classified as a Vidyā or Mahāvidyā goddess. This assumes a kind of communication, in which the mantrin either becomes fully identified with the prasenā or gains control of her. The JY declares that the mantrin possesses a special reverence, which is a result of meditation properly performed on this highest śakti (feminine energy). In a statement reminiscent of later Tibetan esoteric Buddhist initiatory practice, the JY states that this śakti arises in one’s belly on the disk of the moon, and it is here that the mantrin accesses her, in waves.69 The practitioner becomes established in a divine body (divyakāyasthitaḥ) and is able to perceive the expanded significance of a single point (bindumandiram).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05 Possession Across the Himalayas</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/11_Childhood_Possession/05_Possession_Across_the_Himalayas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/11_Childhood_Possession/05_Possession_Across_the_Himalayas/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The question arises as to whether we can justly assume that the primary Indian source materials are in fact the basis of the practice of svasthāvesa found in China or whether China had its own indigenous sources quite apart from the Indian ones. To take this one step further, we can ask whether the advent of svasthāvesa and similar divinatory practices in India might be explained as borrowings from China, which, it is well known, had a rich history of such practices. Although I believe that we may preemptively reject this, the question arises because Davis cites Tang texts of the seventh and eighth centuries that agree almost verbatim with the Indian Śaiva and Buddhist texts that may be slightly later in composition. Furthermore, the epigraphical evidence cited above, though clearly linking the northern Saiddhāntika tradition with similar traditions farther south, fails to specify practices, as we have seen. An objection might then be raised concerning the provenance of these practices, especially because the earliest reference to svasthāvesa in South Asia, in the absence of other data, appears to be in the Harṣacarita, a text almost precisely contemporaneous with the earliest Chinese material. With this in mind, we should settle any lingering doubts regarding the matter of the direction of transmission.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>06 Aweishe: The Indic Character of Chinese Possession</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/11_Childhood_Possession/06_Aweishe_The_Indic_Character_of_Chinese_Possession/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/11_Childhood_Possession/06_Aweishe_The_Indic_Character_of_Chinese_Possession/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Strickmann and Davis cite several texts that contain material strongly reminiscent of Indic and Tibetan āveśa and svasthāvesa. Indeed, the Chinese employ the word aweishe  a direct transcription of āvesa, “to designate possession rites in which a spirit was invoked into the living body of a medium. The term might also apply to procedures in which the spirit of a living person was co-opted, so to speak, into the pantheon.”94 Strickmann and Davis cite a large number of passages, including one from the Amoghapāśasūtra,95 which strikingly resemble Orofino’s description of childhood possession in the Tibetan Subāhuparipṛcchānāmatantra. According to Strickmann, the Amoghapāśasūtra, which was translated from Sanskrit into Chinese around the end of the seventh century, was the first Chinese Buddhist text to give instructions for inducing deity possession. It was at this point, says Strickmann, that a “new Tantric synthesis was about to become known in China”96 The purpose of this aweishe ritual, which invokes Guanyin (=Avalokitesvara), was therapeutic, to heal an individual suffering from spirit-induced illness. The passage is not an isolated ritual option, but occurs in a more general discussion of ritual healing. The entire passage is worth citing:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>07 Svasthāveśa in South India</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/11_Childhood_Possession/07_SvasthAvesha_in_South_India/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/11_Childhood_Possession/07_SvasthAvesha_in_South_India/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We must now briefly examine a few Sanskrit āveśa manuscripts found in the South Indian libraries. These manuscripts are quite ordinary in that they prescribe the construction of easily inscribed yantras or maṇḍalas that were likely in common use.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Other normative features are the recitation of bija mantras found in nearly all mantra collections (though they have their own unique order here), and brief statements of purpose and fruits to be gained (saṇkalpa). Although they have a standard format and structure, these manuscripts have unique content, as shown by a composite summary.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>08 The Mantramahodadhi</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/11_Childhood_Possession/08_The_Mantramahodadhi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/11_Childhood_Possession/08_The_Mantramahodadhi/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The procedures for employing children for divinatory purposes in India were not limited to a shadowy presence in a few obscure, regionally specific texts. This is similar to the situation in China, where it was relatively widespread, as Davis’s extensive documentation shows. However, even if the practice was not as widespread in India as in China, corroborative evidence from other Tantras shows that it spread beyond the confines of a few local cults. At any rate, knowledge of it appears to have entered into more mainstream Tantra sastra.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The Mantramahodadhi (MM), a popular and diffuse compendium of both dakṣiṇācāra and vāmācāra tantric practice composed in the sixteenth century by Mahīdhara,&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; includes several verses on this practice or on an adaptation of it.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>09 The Tantrarāja</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/11_Childhood_Possession/09_The_TantrarAja/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/11_Childhood_Possession/09_The_TantrarAja/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The term svasthāvesa is attested in the sixteenth-century tantric compendium Tantrarāja (TR), brought to public notice by Sir John Woodroffe in 1918.132 This text presents a fairly close, if highly condensed, depiction of at least some of the material found in the early tantric materials and the South Indian manuscripts. The TR describes two yantras of the goddess and a ritual (TR 9.61–101), the most important part of which is the act of situating on one of the yantras a young girl who is to be guided into and out of svasthāveśa. The text speaks of the “performance” of svasthāveśa, an admission that should not be overlooked. The relevant verses state, “one should perform svasthāveśa” (9.76–78) on the first of the two yantras, because it is over this that the officiant recites the relevant possession mantras. The girl should then become identified with the deity, after which the officiant should burn a kind of incense called sarjjarasa. When she enters into the possession, the girl is worshipped reverently and with appropriate ceremony. Afterward, the client should ask for whichever objects are desired, upon which the girl will always reply fittingly. After being worshipped suitably, the deity becomes her, and after rites, such as sprinkling water, are performed on the first yantra the officiant causes the girls to disembark from their condition in which they are controlled by others.133 The Tantrarāja does not specify who these “others” are, and the commentary states, rather aimlessly, “piśāca, etc.,” apparently to qualify his previous assertion that it is a devatā.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>10 Indian Āveśa and Chinese Aweishe: A Comparison</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/11_Childhood_Possession/10_Indian_Avesha_and_Chinese_Aweishe_A_Comparison/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/11_Childhood_Possession/10_Indian_Avesha_and_Chinese_Aweishe_A_Comparison/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;To complete the comparative aspect of this topic, an examination of svasthāveśa not only as a term for nonpathological possession but, more specifically, as oracular possession of children, we must offer more examples of this phenomenon in Chinese literature. Only then can the extent to which the Chinese material is derivative of the Indian be determined.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Some compilations of Tang dynasty stories tell of children possessed by the spirits (shen) of learned men. Glen Dudbridge explicates several such accounts from a genre called zhiguai ( tales of the marvelous), one exemplar of which is the eighth-century Guangyi ji ( The Book of Marvels). In Dudbridge’s first story, a girl named Wang Fazhi from the town of Tonglu serves the spirit of a young man called Teng Quanyin, with whom she had an affinity in a previous birth; she begins to experience regular possession of his spirit before the age of five. In frequent meetings with the county magistrate, writers and poets, and Buddhist monks, Quanyin, speaking through Fazhi, demonstrates his literary, scholarly, and religious erudition, composing poetry extemporaneously.134&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>11 Conclusions</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/11_Childhood_Possession/11_Conclusions/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/11_Childhood_Possession/11_Conclusions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In lieu of decisive conclusions on this vast material, I instead pose a question: Why was possession induced in prepubescent youths? I cannot produce a confident reply; the answers lie in addressing both the nature of childhood and its various Indian and Chinese cultural constructions; in other words, both nature and culture. My initial impulse is to tread lightly on questions of culturally constituted psychology and the applicability of psychoanalytic theory, an impulse that should be evident from my earlier methodological explorations. I believe that, in spite of the efforts of Kakar and others, these areas have been insufficiently explored and I am particularly unqualified to offer a mature opinion on them.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>12 NOTES</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/11_Childhood_Possession/12_NOTES/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/11_Childhood_Possession/12_NOTES/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I am particular grateful to Alexis Sanderson, who brought the unpublished Śaiva texts to my attention, shared with me his copious transcriptions and notes on them, and eventually went through a draft of this chapter, offering many positive suggestions, some of which are worthy of specific attribution. I am also indebted to E. Muralidhara Rao and H. V. Nagaraja Rao for help in transcribing a number of Sanskrit manuscripts from Telugu script into Nāgarī; to the participants of a conference on Tantra and Daoism held at Boston University in April 2002, especially John Lagerwey, David Germano, and Ronald Davidson; and to Wendi Adamek for explicating the Chinese and patiently answering many questions that must have seemed basic to her.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
