<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;11 Tantra and the Diaspora of Childhood Possession on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/11_Childhood_Possession/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;11 Tantra and the Diaspora of Childhood Possession on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/11_Childhood_Possession/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 The Śaiva and Buddhist Tantras and the South Indian Texts</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/11_Childhood_Possession/01_The_shaiva_and_Buddhist_Tantras_and_the_South_Indian_Texts/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/11_Childhood_Possession/01_The_shaiva_and_Buddhist_Tantras_and_the_South_Indian_Texts/</guid>
      <description>The Himalayan Śaiva and Buddhist Tantras that mention svasthāvesa are primarily dedicated to descriptions of the worship of Śiva and various goddesses. The Śaiva texts fall within a class called Siddhānta, rather than under the better-known but highly suspect designation “Kashmir Saivism.”3 Thus, the texts are not the commonly cited ones (by Abhinavagupta, Kṣemarāja, Utpaladeva, and their predecessors), but the lesser-known Jayadrathayāmala, Tantrasadbhāva, Sekoddeśa, Niśvāsaguhya, Bṛhatkālottara, and Cakrasaṃvarapiṇḍārtha.4 None of these except the Sekoddesa has been edited or published;5 the remaining ones exist in manuscript form only and have been examined almost solely by Alexis Sanderson.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>02 Svasthāveśa and the Prasenā</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/11_Childhood_Possession/02_SvasthAvesha_and_the_Prasena/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/11_Childhood_Possession/02_SvasthAvesha_and_the_Prasena/</guid>
      <description>Of the two primary divisions of possession, involuntary and voluntary, the former found textual bases principally in the specialized fields of āyurvedic and tantric exorcistic literature.24 However, voluntary possession, particularly that with an oracular component, appears to have been regarded as more suitable material for textuality. Two reasons may be cited for this. First, because it could be practiced, hence prescribed—and, in general, prescription was formalized through literary production. Precedents for the commission of such material to the written word are found in the literature on omens and portents, dating back to the Vedic vidhāna literature,25 scattered passages from the Sanskrit epics, and the landmark works of the astrologer and mathematician Varāhamihira around 550 C.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>03 Epigraphical Evidence for the Practice of Svasthāveśa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/11_Childhood_Possession/03_Epigraphical_Evidence_for_the_Practice_of_SvasthAvesha/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/11_Childhood_Possession/03_Epigraphical_Evidence_for_the_Practice_of_SvasthAvesha/</guid>
      <description>We now turn to the Himalayan and eastern rite of svasthāvesa, not losing sight of our objective of comparing it to the manuscript material from China of the same period and southern India of later epochs. Although the relevant Tantras are themselves undated, Sanderson suggests that one of the earliest, the Nisvāsaguhya, could be a product of the sixth century, though it can be dated with certainty only to a single ninth-century Nepalese manuscript.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>04 The Ritual of Svasthāveśa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/11_Childhood_Possession/04_The_Ritual_of_SvasthAvesha/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/11_Childhood_Possession/04_The_Ritual_of_SvasthAvesha/</guid>
      <description>With this in mind, then, let us now turn again, briefly, to the Śaiva and Buddhist Tantras and to the ritual employment of the prasenā. The Niśvāsaguhya, the Tantrasadbhāva, the Cakrasaṃvarapiṇḍārtha, the Sekoddeśa, the Bṛhatkālottara, and, most importantly, the Jayadrathayāmala (JY), the latest and most compendious of these texts, present a complex intertextuality.68 So, it is fair to present a composite account of the ritual of svasthāveśa.
The texts state that the prasenā is a divinatory form assumed by a female deity (vidya) that appears before the practitioner during a ritual performed at a site sacred to Maheśvara (rudrasthāna) or in a temple to the goddess (mātṛgṛham).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>05 Possession Across the Himalayas</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/11_Childhood_Possession/05_Possession_Across_the_Himalayas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/11_Childhood_Possession/05_Possession_Across_the_Himalayas/</guid>
      <description>The question arises as to whether we can justly assume that the primary Indian source materials are in fact the basis of the practice of svasthāvesa found in China or whether China had its own indigenous sources quite apart from the Indian ones. To take this one step further, we can ask whether the advent of svasthāvesa and similar divinatory practices in India might be explained as borrowings from China, which, it is well known, had a rich history of such practices.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>06 Aweishe: The Indic Character of Chinese Possession</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/11_Childhood_Possession/06_Aweishe_The_Indic_Character_of_Chinese_Possession/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/11_Childhood_Possession/06_Aweishe_The_Indic_Character_of_Chinese_Possession/</guid>
      <description>Strickmann and Davis cite several texts that contain material strongly reminiscent of Indic and Tibetan āveśa and svasthāvesa. Indeed, the Chinese employ the word aweishe a direct transcription of āvesa, “to designate possession rites in which a spirit was invoked into the living body of a medium. The term might also apply to procedures in which the spirit of a living person was co-opted, so to speak, into the pantheon.”94 Strickmann and Davis cite a large number of passages, including one from the Amoghapāśasūtra,95 which strikingly resemble Orofino’s description of childhood possession in the Tibetan Subāhuparipṛcchānāmatantra.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>07 Svasthāveśa in South India</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/11_Childhood_Possession/07_SvasthAvesha_in_South_India/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/11_Childhood_Possession/07_SvasthAvesha_in_South_India/</guid>
      <description>We must now briefly examine a few Sanskrit āveśa manuscripts found in the South Indian libraries. These manuscripts are quite ordinary in that they prescribe the construction of easily inscribed yantras or maṇḍalas that were likely in common use.1
Other normative features are the recitation of bija mantras found in nearly all mantra collections (though they have their own unique order here), and brief statements of purpose and fruits to be gained (saṇkalpa).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>08 The Mantramahodadhi</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/11_Childhood_Possession/08_The_Mantramahodadhi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/11_Childhood_Possession/08_The_Mantramahodadhi/</guid>
      <description>The procedures for employing children for divinatory purposes in India were not limited to a shadowy presence in a few obscure, regionally specific texts. This is similar to the situation in China, where it was relatively widespread, as Davis’s extensive documentation shows. However, even if the practice was not as widespread in India as in China, corroborative evidence from other Tantras shows that it spread beyond the confines of a few local cults.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>09 The Tantrarāja</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/11_Childhood_Possession/09_The_TantrarAja/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/11_Childhood_Possession/09_The_TantrarAja/</guid>
      <description>The term svasthāvesa is attested in the sixteenth-century tantric compendium Tantrarāja (TR), brought to public notice by Sir John Woodroffe in 1918.132 This text presents a fairly close, if highly condensed, depiction of at least some of the material found in the early tantric materials and the South Indian manuscripts. The TR describes two yantras of the goddess and a ritual (TR 9.61–101), the most important part of which is the act of situating on one of the yantras a young girl who is to be guided into and out of svasthāveśa.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>10 Indian Āveśa and Chinese Aweishe: A Comparison</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/11_Childhood_Possession/10_Indian_Avesha_and_Chinese_Aweishe_A_Comparison/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/11_Childhood_Possession/10_Indian_Avesha_and_Chinese_Aweishe_A_Comparison/</guid>
      <description>To complete the comparative aspect of this topic, an examination of svasthāveśa not only as a term for nonpathological possession but, more specifically, as oracular possession of children, we must offer more examples of this phenomenon in Chinese literature. Only then can the extent to which the Chinese material is derivative of the Indian be determined.
Some compilations of Tang dynasty stories tell of children possessed by the spirits (shen) of learned men.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>11 Conclusions</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/11_Childhood_Possession/11_Conclusions/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/11_Childhood_Possession/11_Conclusions/</guid>
      <description>In lieu of decisive conclusions on this vast material, I instead pose a question: Why was possession induced in prepubescent youths? I cannot produce a confident reply; the answers lie in addressing both the nature of childhood and its various Indian and Chinese cultural constructions; in other words, both nature and culture. My initial impulse is to tread lightly on questions of culturally constituted psychology and the applicability of psychoanalytic theory, an impulse that should be evident from my earlier methodological explorations.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>12 NOTES</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/11_Childhood_Possession/12_NOTES/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/11_Childhood_Possession/12_NOTES/</guid>
      <description>I am particular grateful to Alexis Sanderson, who brought the unpublished Śaiva texts to my attention, shared with me his copious transcriptions and notes on them, and eventually went through a draft of this chapter, offering many positive suggestions, some of which are worthy of specific attribution. I am also indebted to E. Muralidhara Rao and H. V. Nagaraja Rao for help in transcribing a number of Sanskrit manuscripts from Telugu script into Nāgarī; to the participants of a conference on Tantra and Daoism held at Boston University in April 2002, especially John Lagerwey, David Germano, and Ronald Davidson; and to Wendi Adamek for explicating the Chinese and patiently answering many questions that must have seemed basic to her.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
