<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;अधिगणपति on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/gaNapatiH/meta/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;अधिगणपति on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/gaNapatiH/meta/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>मरुत्-सम्बन्धः</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/gaNapatiH/meta/marut-sambandhaH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/gaNapatiH/meta/marut-sambandhaH/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;वरपकष-दनतञज&#34;&gt;विरूपाक्षो दन्ताञ्जि&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;virūpāksha dantāñji formula from sāmavedic texts is interesting. The mantras as per Chāndogya brāhmaņa as well as jaiminiya gŕhyasūtra - &amp;ldquo;japantam mā mā prati jāpsïh. juhvantam mā mā pratihauşīh. kurvantam mā mā pratkārşīh&amp;rdquo;.&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;In a sāmavedic homa this mantra is uttered just after placing praņītā pot to the north of fire and prastara (darbha bundle) in the south.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Gobhila gŕhya mentions that this formula is muttered before all homas.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;It adds a special rule for kāmya sacrifices. The performer does a prāņāyāma - while holding the breath, he mutters the prapada formula (right next to the virupaksha formula).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;dantA~njin should be either interpreted as marked with a tusk or a tusk which is like that special attribute of the marut-s. When breathing out, he mutters the virupaksha formula.   - मरुतां सम्बन्धे वेदेष्व् अञ्जिशब्दः+++(=चिक्कनतयोज्ज्वलम्)+++ &lt;a href=&#34;../../../marutaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/anji-sambandhaH/&#34;&gt;प्रयुज्यते&lt;/a&gt; ।&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Virupaksha most likely is a form of rudra. However he seems to have aspects of time in this mantra. He has 12 sons who year after year sacrifice to him and commence brahmacharya. The 12 sons are 12 months (as per commentator) possibly the equation of samvatsara = yajña is alluded. The mantra says his bed is of leaves. His station is in antariksha with golden shed And iron jar with &amp;lsquo;devānām hŕdaya&amp;quot; - hearts of the Gods. Compare rudrānuvāka - &amp;ldquo;namaH parņāya cha parņashadyāya cha&amp;rdquo;.. &amp;ldquo;devānāM hŕdayebhyo..&amp;rdquo;. Both the leaf motif and &amp;ldquo;hearts of Gods&amp;rdquo; motif present. - कस्तूरिः&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
