<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;Articles on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/rudraH/meta/articles/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;Articles on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 09 Nov 2008 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/rudraH/meta/articles/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>ChaNDesha</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/rudraH/meta/articles/chaNDesha/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/rudraH/meta/articles/chaNDesha/</guid>
      <description>As a young boy, Chandesha found that cows were poorly cared for and started taking care of a small herd. To pass the time, he made a sand Shiva lingam and would pour some milk on it as a simple offering. When Datta, his father, heard about this, he came to the field to scold his son. Chandesha was deep in meditation in front of the sand lingam, and he did not notice his father.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>gaNa-s</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/rudraH/meta/articles/gaNas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/rudraH/meta/articles/gaNas/</guid>
      <description>A humorous shArdulavikrIDita of tu~Nga indicating the presence of charchikA in rudra&amp;rsquo;s retinue -
चर्चायाः कथम् एष रक्षति सदा सद्यो नृ-मुण्ड-स्रजं
चण्डी-केशरिणो वृषं च भुजगान् सूनोर् मयूराद् अपि ।
इत्य् अन्तः परिभावयन् भगवतो दीर्घं धियः कौशलं ।
कूष्माण्डो धृति-संभृताम् अनुदिनं पुष्णाति तुन्द-श्रियम् ॥
How does he ever protect his garland of fresh human heads from Carcā? Also his bull from Candi&amp;rsquo;s lion and his snakes from his son&amp;rsquo;s peacock? Thus, wondering to himself about the lord&amp;rsquo;s deep mental skill KūşmāņDa daily nourishes the growing satisfaction of his belly&amp;rsquo;s corpulence.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Phallic symbol</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/rudraH/meta/articles/phallic-symbol/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/rudraH/meta/articles/phallic-symbol/</guid>
      <description>Source: GhorAngirasa on Twitter
Incorporeality What kind of face has 3 eyes? What kind of body has more than 2 arms? Liṅga is no ordinary human body part. While Śiva in Śaivam does not have any body or form, he assumes forms for our sake &amp;amp; Liṅga has a phallic significance &amp;amp; scriptures have explained its deep meaning too.
Upamanyu&amp;rsquo;s passage I care for the opinion of Śrī-Upamanyu-Ṛṣi who states in Mahābhārata that Śiva-Devī are the only deities whose signs/insignia are found on the very persons of all humans &amp;amp; even beasts.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>siddhAnta view</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/rudraH/meta/articles/siddhAnta-view/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/rudraH/meta/articles/siddhAnta-view/</guid>
      <description>Source: GA
Śrīkaṇṭharudra is the Rudra in Rudraloka at top of the Brahmāṇḍa &amp;amp; descends to Kailāśa to bless us. He is the Rudra you see in Purāṇa stories &amp;amp; is distinct from Paramaśiva, who operates through Śrīkaṇṭharudra in this world for the sake of bonded souls like us.
Those who have read my tweets regarding the distinction between Paramaśiva &amp;amp; Śrīkaṇṭha will know that I always attribute the literal acts to Śrīkaṇṭha &amp;amp; never Paramaśiva.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>व्युत्पत्तयः</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/rudraH/meta/articles/vyutpattayaH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/rudraH/meta/articles/vyutpattayaH/</guid>
      <description>रुद्र —
१. रोदयति सर्वमन्तकाले इति
२. रुत् संसाराख्यं दुःखं। तत् द्रावयति अपगमयति विनाशयति इति
३. रुतः शब्दरूपाः उपनिषदः। ताभिर्द्रूयते गम्यते प्रतिपाद्यते इति
४. रुणद्धि आवृणोति इति रुत् अन्धकारादि। तत् दृणाति विदारयतीति
५. पापिनो नरान् दुःखभोगेन रोदयति इति
६. रोदयति शत्रून् इति
७. रवणं रुत् ज्ञानं राति ददाति इति
८. रुत् शब्दात्मिका वाणी। तत्प्रतिपाद्या आत्मविद्या वा। तामुपासकेभ्यो राति ददाति इति
९. रौति शब्दायते तारकं ब्रह्म उपदिशतीति
१०. शब्दब्रह्मात्मना रोरूयमाणो द्रवति सर्वप्राणिहृदये वर्तत इति</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
