<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/shaktayaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 08 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/shaktayaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>rise of the mātṛkās</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/shaktayaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2022-02-08_on-the-rise-of-the-matRka-s-and-the-goddess-chamuN/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/shaktayaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2022-02-08_on-the-rise-of-the-matRka-s-and-the-goddess-chamuN/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2022/02/08/on-the-rise-of-the-mat%e1%b9%9bka-s-and-the-goddess-camu%e1%b9%87%e1%b8%8da/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;On the rise of the mātṛkā-s and the goddess Cāmuṇḍā&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;ancient-roots&#34;&gt;Ancient roots&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The roots of the mātṛkā-s in the śruti and the Kaumāra tradition&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The standard list of 7/8 goddesses known as the mātṛkā-s is a hallmark feature of the classical religion: Brāhmī, Māheśvarī, Kaumārī, Vaiṣṇavī, Vārāhī, Indrāṇī, Cāmuṇḍā, sometimes with the central Caṇḍikā (Mahālakṣmī), to make a list of 8. Most of them are the female counterparts of the prominent gods of the classical pantheon. These goddesses have a relatively constant iconography throughout the Indosphere, starting from the Gupta age.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>mantra of trailokyavijayA</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/shaktayaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2007-01-16_mantra-of-trailokyavijaya/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Jan 2007 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/shaktayaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2007-01-16_mantra-of-trailokyavijaya/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2007/01/16/mantra-of-trailokyavijaya/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The mantra of the goddess trailokyavijayA is provided by the&#xA;yuddha-jayArNava tantraM. A somewhat corrupt version of this tantra is&#xA;incorporated into the agni purANa. Stand-alone manuscripts of the YJA&#xA;also exist, though they have not been edited or published. In addition&#xA;to the version of the agni-purANa I had access to a hand-written&#xA;transcript on paper. The Dutch explorers have recovered a corrupt&#xA;version of the same in their collection of Hindu mantras known as&#xA;stuti-s and stava-s from Indonesia (now only surviving in Bali). All&#xA;these with a single input from oral tradition help to obtain the&#xA;critical version of the trailokyavijayA mantra as per the available&#xA;traditions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The AmnAya-krama for the dual worship of shArikA and tripurA</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/shaktayaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-10-21_the-amnaya-krama-for-the-dual-worship-of-sharika-and-tripura/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Oct 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/shaktayaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-10-21_the-amnaya-krama-for-the-dual-worship-of-sharika-and-tripura/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2006/10/21/the-amnaya-krama-for-the-dual-worship-of-sharika-and-tripura/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;R and I finally got to moving ahead with the initial part of laying out&#xA;the formulae related to the dual worship of shArikA and tripurA that was&#xA;prevalent with the Himalayan tantrics. The shArikA-tripurA krama of&#xA;aghora-shiva is related in terms of the formulae to dakShiNa-mUrti&#xA;virachita uddhAra-kosha, a famous work on mantra shAstra that contains&#xA;most of these formulae. The aghora-shiva here is the south-face of rudra&#xA;or dakShiNa-mUrti. Many similar or same formulae are also found in the&#xA;well-known devI-rahasya tantra. The central manifestation of the shakti&#xA;are shArikA and tripurA, and then there are the faces of the cardinal&#xA;directions comprised of the mantras of the AmnAya krama. Note that in&#xA;this procedure the base tripurA mantra is derived from kAdi-vidyA and&#xA;not the hAdi-vidyA.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Wanderings in oDDiyAna</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/shaktayaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-09-26_wanderings-in-oddiyana/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Sep 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/shaktayaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-09-26_wanderings-in-oddiyana/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2006/09/26/wanderings-in-oddiyana/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Long ago the great old vaiShNava wandered in the hallowed oDDiyAna&#xA;pITha, when he reached an old desolate prAsada towards the evening hour.&#xA;There he seated himself and concentrated ThaM bIja. Then the divine&#xA;boar-faced mistress of the 5th lunar digit graced him. She of most&#xA;beautiful waist appeared there with curly locks and bearing two shining&#xA;tusks on her snout. Her awesome hips were draped by a most excellent&#xA;blue and golden vesture and she held the still-bloody pestle with which&#xA;she had smashed the skull of visha~Nga. She who is called the&#xA;sa~nketA, who is seated in the Aj~nAchakra of the enlightened ones,&#xA;had lustrous bangles that shone like rings of light and her shapely&#xA;breasts, like jewel pots, were smeared with sweet-smelling saffron. The&#xA;glorious sa~nketA also held a halAyudha that was washed with the blood&#xA;of daityas slain by her in combat. The twang of her deadly bow filled&#xA;the sky with thunder-like roars and their reverberations. On sa~nketA’s&#xA;car fluttered banners bearing buffaloes, deer and lions. In front of her&#xA;marched a vanguard of dreaded bhairava-s, dark as collyrium in&#xA;complexion, with tawny locks of hair and led by the four handed&#xA;terrifying chaNDochChaNda. She was followed by an army of boar-faced&#xA;goddesses with shapely bodies colored like the dark bark of tamAla tree&#xA;(Xanthochymus pictorius). They had tawny hair and ruthless eyes, and&#xA;held terrible weapons similar to those of samayasa~nketA. Smoke and&#xA;flames shot forth from their snouts. and the curved tusks illuminated&#xA;the darkness like crescent moons.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;They rode on charging buffaloes, while a few of these sow-faced&#xA;goddesses diffused away guarding the flanks prancing around with their&#xA;swords and shields. They advanced before them a fleet of siege engines&#xA;known as talavR^inta-s that formed a barricade for their division.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The circle of yakShiNI-s</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/shaktayaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-08-17_the-circle-of-yakshini-s/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Aug 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/shaktayaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-08-17_the-circle-of-yakshini-s/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2006/08/17/the-circle-of-yakshini-s/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We bow to the great goddess of the trotalottaraM and pay worship to the&#xA;great throng of yakShiNI-s that emerge from her. The yakShiNI-s are of&#xA;diverse forms, all very wonderful and amazing. They bear many diverse&#xA;facets of knowledge — he who can acquire them all becomes sarva-vyApin.&#xA;But the knowledge is not easily acquired from the yakShiNI. There are so&#xA;many ways in which they slip away after it has been shown to you by her.&#xA;After you land from the flight of the yakShiNI, it may evaporate from&#xA;you. Or in the delusion of the wonderous form of the yakShiNI, the&#xA;knowledge might escape from you. Some wonderous yakShiNI-s carry what&#xA;may be called “useless knowledge”. It can be endlessly fascinating but&#xA;cannot be acquired by those not fit for it, or knowing it takes you down&#xA;a path a failure.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>kubjikA and the pa~nchavaktra mahAdeva</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/shaktayaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-07-20_kubjika-and-the-panchavaktra-mahadeva/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Jul 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/shaktayaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-07-20_kubjika-and-the-panchavaktra-mahadeva/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2006/07/20/kubjika-and-the-panchavaktra-mahadeva/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://photos1.blogger.com/blogger/2010/410/1600/kubjikA1.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;figure class=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &lt;a href=&#34;https://i2.wp.com/photos1.blogger.com/blogger/2010/410/320/kubjikA1.jpg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;img src=&#34;https://i2.wp.com/photos1.blogger.com/blogger/2010/410/320/kubjikA1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &#xA;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The great tradition of paschimAmnAya goddess, our hallowed mother&#xA;kubjikA, had a number of streams that are now largely forgotten. One of&#xA;the older streams before its standardization in the tradition of the&#xA;kubjikAmata and ShaTsAhasra streams was the worship of kubjikA conjoined&#xA;with the five headed shiva (distinct from the other representations&#xA;where she is conjoined with shiva as navAtman (also alluded to in the&#xA;saundaryalahari; while mainly devoted to kulasundarI, 34, 39 and 41&#xA;refer to kubjikA) or has paramashiva above her) . This tradition is&#xA;associated with ancient pre-matsyendra siddha guru-s like,&#xA;bhR^igvAnandanAtha, rA~ngulAnandanAtha, samvartAnandanAtha and their&#xA;wives, and others whose feet are offered tarpaNaM-s in the guru-maNDala.&#xA;Here she is worshipped with shiva showing all his five faces sadyojAta,&#xA;vAmadeva, tatpuruSha, aghora and IshAna. He holds a trident and a&#xA;Damaru. The hallowed mother kubjikA has 6 faces; the cobras karoTaka as&#xA;a waist band, takShaka as a mid-riff ornament, vAsuki as garland and the&#xA;venomous cobra kulika as an ear ornament. The great tortoise is her ear&#xA;stud. She holds in her arms as skull, a king-cobra, a crystal-bead&#xA;rosary, skull-topped rod, a conch, a book, a trident, a mirror, a&#xA;straight sword, a gem necklace, an a~NkuSha and a bow. She is of fair&#xA;complexion like a young jasmine flower. The yantra of this worship is&#xA;provided above.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Some notes of the ShaTsAhasra tradition</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/shaktayaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-07-10_some-notes-of-the-shatsahasra-tradition/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Jul 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/shaktayaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-07-10_some-notes-of-the-shatsahasra-tradition/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2006/07/10/some-notes-of-the-shatsahasra-tradition/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://photos1.blogger.com/blogger/2010/410/1600/vAgIshvarI.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;figure class=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &lt;a href=&#34;https://i0.wp.com/photos1.blogger.com/blogger/2010/410/320/vAgIshvarI.jpg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;img src=&#34;https://i0.wp.com/photos1.blogger.com/blogger/2010/410/320/vAgIshvarI.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &#xA;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When in gavalkuNDa, R1 and A saved us from the pangs of hunger. R1, A&#xA;and our clan had similar histories with peregrinations through the&#xA;length of jambudvIpa over time in the practice and quest of the&#xA;mantra-shAstra. R1’s clan had moved back recently to the Southern realms&#xA;after 2.5 centuries in the land of the malla rAjas. R1 who treated us as&#xA;son also opened our eyes to some remarkable matters- she us acquainted&#xA;with her father, who was one the last holders of the vidyA’s of the&#xA;ShaTsAhasra tradition (since R1 was cashing her brahminical check).&#xA;Thus, I learnt some of these rahasyas that I wish to record as they are&#xA;in danger of extinction.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The mahAmantras of the urvashI prayoga and saubhAgya sarasvatI</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/shaktayaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-07-04_the-mahamantras-of-the-urvashi-prayoga-and-saubhagya-sarasvati/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Jul 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/shaktayaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-07-04_the-mahamantras-of-the-urvashi-prayoga-and-saubhagya-sarasvati/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2006/07/04/the-mahamantras-of-the-urvashi-prayoga-and-saubhagya-sarasvati/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The most glorious urvashI is invoked by her mahAmantra:&lt;br&gt;&#xA;oM hrIM eM | abhi na iLA yUthasya mAtA sman nadIbhir urvashI vA&#xA;gR^iNAtu | oM hrIM eM | urvashI vA bR^ihad-divA gR^iNAnA .abhyUrNvAnA&#xA;prabhR^ithasyAyoH | huM svAhA&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The mantras of urvashI and tillotamA are unparalled in the bliss they&#xA;give. The highest joys of svarga may be glimpsed by the invocation of&#xA;the glorious apsaras of great power. The might of the pa~nchachoDA of&#xA;the apsaras protects him from his bhrAtR^ivyas.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The bhinnayoni vidyA</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/shaktayaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-07-02_the-bhinnayoni-vidya/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Jul 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/shaktayaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-07-02_the-bhinnayoni-vidya/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2006/07/02/the-bhinnayoni-vidya/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Since I was asked of the famed bhinna yoni vidyA, which powers the mahA&#xA;mAtR^ikA nyAsa I have written it down. Of course its prakaTa as&#xA;pratya~NgirA needs the inter-twining with the atharvamukha, of which&#xA;the bhinna yoni is itself a prakaTa rUpa. Its manifestation as&#xA;parameshvarI is can be seen in the stand alone bhinna yoni vidyA, though&#xA;a practioner of the bhrigu-A~Ngirasa shruti notes the deep concordance&#xA;with the atharvamukha constantly. Its manifestation as mAlinI, as stated&#xA;from the mouth of trishiro-bhairava is in the form of the mahordhva&#xA;li~Nga and the laghu-yoni. “Oh girl of pretty hips, whose firm breasts&#xA;are the mounds of manmatha-kalA, how many shrikaNThas and shiva-yuvati-s&#xA;manifest when we triangulate the great upward li~Nga with 3 equal&#xA;sides, 6-fold times ? There is one more shiva-yuvati than those of the&#xA;shrikaNThas. He who knows this knows the vidyA”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The tilottamA prayoga</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/shaktayaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-03-09_the-tilottama-prayoga/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Mar 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/shaktayaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-03-09_the-tilottama-prayoga/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2006/03/09/the-tilottama-prayoga/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The bhUta tantras recommend the worship of apasaras and provide the&#xA;outlines for these rites. However, their proper deployment remains&#xA;unknown except to one who has mastered the true rahasyas. The mantras of&#xA;the practioners of the chInAchAra are nowhere in the league of these&#xA;rahasya mantras. 8 principal apsaras may be invoked with apasara maNDala&#xA;though tillotamA may be offered a special sacrifice for the highest&#xA;purpose. The apasaras who are invoked are:&lt;br&gt;&#xA;shashidevI, tillotamA, kA~nchanamAlA, kuNDalahAriNi, ratnamAlA, rambhA,&#xA;urvashI and bhUshiNI.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ekAnamshA: a deity of tantric vaiShNavism</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/shaktayaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-02-04_ekanamsha-a-deity-of-tantric-vaishnavism/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Feb 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/shaktayaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-02-04_ekanamsha-a-deity-of-tantric-vaishnavism/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2006/02/04/ekanamsha-a-deity-of-tantric-vaishnavism/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://photos1.blogger.com/blogger/2010/410/1600/ekAnamshA.0.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;figure class=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &lt;a href=&#34;https://i1.wp.com/photos1.blogger.com/blogger/2010/410/320/ekAnamshA.0.jpg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;img src=&#34;https://i1.wp.com/photos1.blogger.com/blogger/2010/410/320/ekAnamshA.0.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &#xA;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;intro&#34;&gt;Intro&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The core pantheon of the pA~ncharAtra texts is the chaturvyuha or the serial emanations of nArAyaNa. The primary manifestation of nArAyaNa is vAsudeva, from whom emerge saMkarShaNa and pradyumna. From pradyumna emerges aniruddha. This pantheon appears to be a unique feature of the yadu tribes that subsequently seems to have spawned the classical pA~ncharAtra. However, the early texts suggest that there was another parallel system that appears to have largely passed out of subsequent vaiShNavism. That was the cult of the goddess ekAnamshA. Who is she ?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>karNamoTini vidyA</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/shaktayaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2005-12-08_karnamotini-vidya/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Dec 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/shaktayaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2005-12-08_karnamotini-vidya/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2005/12/08/karnamotini-vidya/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://photos1.blogger.com/hello/133/1300/640/karNamoTini.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;figure class=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &lt;a href=&#34;https://i2.wp.com/photos1.blogger.com/hello/133/1300/400/karNamoTini.0.jpg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;img src=&#34;https://i2.wp.com/photos1.blogger.com/hello/133/1300/400/karNamoTini.0.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &#xA;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;oM chaNDAyai namaH| oM ghaNDAyai namaH| oM karAlyai namaH| oM&#xA;sumukhyai namaH| oM durmukhyai namaH| oM revatyai namaH| oM&#xA;prathamAyai namaH| oM ghorAyai namaH|&lt;br&gt;&#xA;vayu-tattvAtmikAyai namaH|| iti vayu maNDalaM&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;mama shatrUn shoShaya shoShaya |&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;oM saumyAyai namaH| oM bhiShaNyai namaH| oM jayAyai namaH| oM&#xA;vijayAyai namaH| oM ajitAyai namaH| oM aparAjitAyai namaH| oM&#xA;mahAkoTyai namaH| oM raudryai namaH|&lt;br&gt;&#xA;rupa-teja-tattvAtmikAyai namaH|| iti rupa-teja maNDalaM&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;mama shatrUn vidrAvaya vidrAvaya |&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;oM virUpAkShyai namaH| oM parAyai namaH| oM divyAyai namaH| oM&#xA;AkAshamAtre namaH| oM samharyai namaH| oM daMShTrAlAyai namaH| oM&#xA;shuShkarevatyai namaH|&lt;br&gt;&#xA;jala-tattvAtmikAyai namaH|| iti jala maNDalaM&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The mahAvidyA of karNamoTini</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/shaktayaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2005-12-07_the-mahavidya-of-karnamotini/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Dec 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/shaktayaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2005-12-07_the-mahavidya-of-karnamotini/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2005/12/07/the-mahavidya-of-karnamotini/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;shrI karNamoTinI devI &lt;a href=&#34;http://picasa.google.com/blogger/&#34;&gt;&lt;figure class=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &lt;a href=&#34;https://i1.wp.com/photos1.blogger.com/pbp.gif&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;img src=&#34;https://i1.wp.com/photos1.blogger.com/pbp.gif&#34; alt=&#34;Posted by&#xA;Picasa&#34; title=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &#xA;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://photos1.blogger.com/hello/133/1300/640/karNamoTini2.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;figure class=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &lt;a href=&#34;https://i2.wp.com/photos1.blogger.com/hello/133/1300/400/karNamoTini2.jpg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;img src=&#34;https://i2.wp.com/photos1.blogger.com/hello/133/1300/400/karNamoTini2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &#xA;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Not far from the from the town of Tenali from where hailed the great&#xA;jester of Vijayanagaran court, in direction of the other little town of&#xA;Narasaraopetai, is the hamlet of Nandindla. It is here that my ancestors&#xA;through my maternal grandmother roamed, a clan graced with number of&#xA;notable shrauta sacrificers. One of that clan was a well-learned tantric&#xA;had attained siddhi of numerous mantras and was deeply proficient in the&#xA;mantra shAstra. In course of his secular duties he was wending his way&#xA;towards another town, when he came across the spot, where the choLa&#xA;governor of the Telugu country, known by the title, giripaschima-rAja,&#xA;had held his court. During the high reign of the reign of king&#xA;kullotu~Nga, this governor had built a temple of the great deity&#xA;karNamoTini and planted an Acacia tree in the compound. He attained the&#xA;siddhi of the mantras of the deity. The place is now in ruins and in the&#xA;grip of the practioners of adharma. Yet those of the clan that think of&#xA;her see her fiery manifestation completely subduing all before them. The&#xA;learned vaiShNava with whom we conversed in our native city told us of&#xA;his remarkable journey to the most glorious Oddiyana Pitha, where he&#xA;realized that great Mongol adept of the chInAchAra tantras, shri jahana&#xA;vajra khaan had attained a siddhi of her mantra. Moving on to Mongolia&#xA;he saw the idol of shrI mahAdevI karNamoTini and having placed her image&#xA;in his heart he he retraced his path to Oddiyana. In the high sthala of&#xA;Oddiyana meditating on her in the midst of the mountain he attained the&#xA;siddhi of her mantra.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>In the lap of dhUmAvatI</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/shaktayaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2005-12-01_in-the-lap-of-dhumavati/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Dec 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/shaktayaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2005-12-01_in-the-lap-of-dhumavati/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2005/12/01/in-the-lap-of-dhumavati/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The harsh cawing of the solitary crow at night announces her presence.&#xA;Of large size with dishevelled hair she roams. The severed heads of&#xA;viShNu and rudra are seen beside her. The mystic bIja graaaM is&#xA;reverberating all around her. There are the senAs of the lulApamukhas&#xA;around her commanded by the dreaded kAlavAhanavadana. Beside her sits&#xA;her fair daughter rakta-jyeShThA or upa-dhUmrA. Her pArshadhas are&#xA;yelling hideous statements like without shivA, shiva is but a shava.&#xA;Others yell it is not in this jagat. In her hand she holds a large&#xA;terrible shUla.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>gupta vidyA</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/shaktayaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2005-11-29_gupta-vidya/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Nov 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/shaktayaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2005-11-29_gupta-vidya/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2005/11/29/gupta-vidya/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;shrI pratya~NgirA atharvaNa bhadrakAlI paramabhattarikA devI&lt;a href=&#34;http://picasa.google.com/blogger/&#34;&gt;&lt;figure class=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &lt;a href=&#34;https://i1.wp.com/photos1.blogger.com/pbp.gif&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;img src=&#34;https://i1.wp.com/photos1.blogger.com/pbp.gif&#34; alt=&#34;Posted by&#xA;Picasa&#34; title=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &#xA;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://photos1.blogger.com/hello/133/1300/640/pratyangira.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;figure class=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &lt;a href=&#34;https://i1.wp.com/photos1.blogger.com/hello/133/1300/400/pratyangira.jpg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;img src=&#34;https://i1.wp.com/photos1.blogger.com/hello/133/1300/400/pratyangira.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &#xA;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We stood before that great idol of pratya~NgirA before the most holy shrine of Tiruchengode. That is the idol filled with the power of atharvaNa hR^idyA. When stands one before the deity one attains the most high mantra of the devI.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;khaDUre .adhicha~NkamAM&lt;br&gt;&#xA;kharvikAM kharvavAsinIM |&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ya udArA antarhitA&lt;br&gt;&#xA;gandharvApasarasashcha ye |&lt;br&gt;&#xA;sarpA itarajanA rakShAMsi ||&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The most fierce one manifests with the appropriate bIjas added.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>vArAhI dvAdashaM</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/shaktayaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2005-04-27_varahi-dvadasham/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/shaktayaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2005-04-27_varahi-dvadasham/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2005/04/27/varahi-dvadasham/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;vArahI dvAdashaM iti mantrasya shrI ashvAnanaH R^iShiH | anuShTup&#xA;ChandaH | vArAhI devatA | shrI vArahi devI prasAda siddhi dvAra sarva&#xA;sa~NkaTa haraNaM jape viniyogaH ||&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;pa~nchamI danDanAthA cha sa~Nketa samayeshvarI /&lt;br&gt;&#xA;tathA samaya-sa~NketA vArAhI potriNI shivA //&lt;br&gt;&#xA;vArtAlI cha mahAsenA .apyAGYAchakreshvarI tatha /&lt;br&gt;&#xA;arighnI cheti samproktaM nAma dvAdashakaM mune //&lt;br&gt;&#xA;nAma-dvAdashadhAbhikhya vajra-pa~njara-madhyagaH /&lt;br&gt;&#xA;sa~NkaTe duHkham-Apnoti na kadAchana mAnavaH //&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ChinnamastA</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/shaktayaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2005-04-17_chinnamasta/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Apr 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/shaktayaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2005-04-17_chinnamasta/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2005/04/17/chinnamasta/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The below has some errors and is superseded by this&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.files.wordpress.com/2005/04/chinnamasta-1.pdf&#34;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;OM ChinnamastA mahAvidyA mahAbhImA mahodarI /&lt;br&gt;&#xA;chaNDeshvarI chaNDa-mAtA chaNDa-muNDa-prabha~njinI // 4 //&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;OM one with a severed head, the great vidyA, the terrible one, one with&#xA;a great belly;&lt;br&gt;&#xA;the terrible goddess, the frightful mother, the smasher of the demons&#xA;chaNDa and muNDa.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;mahAchaNDA chaNDa-rUpA chaNDikA chaNDa-khaNDinI /&lt;br&gt;&#xA;krodhinI krodha-jananI krodha-rUpA kuhU kalA // 5 //&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Most terrifying, of terrible form, the terrifying one, the slaughterer&#xA;of chaNDa;&lt;br&gt;&#xA;the wrathful one, the generator of wrath, of form of wrath, of form of&#xA;the new-moon phase&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>mahAkAli</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/shaktayaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2003-09-30_mahakali/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2003 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/shaktayaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2003-09-30_mahakali/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2003/09/30/mahakali/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The bhArgava sage mArkaNdeya narrated the 3 tales of the fierce goddess and the battles they fought.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The first tale was that of mahAkAli. On account of her mAya, the great god viShNu lay in slumber when the plane was submerged in the waters at the end of the kalpa. There arose from the wax in his ears two terrible daityas, madhu and kaiTabha. They rapidly advanced to slay brahmA when mahAkAli in order to awaken viShNu arose from his forehead and departed. viShNu having awoken fought the daityas in a relentless battle for 5000 years. At the end of it, under mahAkAli’s delusion the daityas sought a boon from vishNu. As the whole plane lay submerged in the waters, the daityas asked the boon that viShNu could only kill them in the spot where there was no water. viShNu granted it to them. He immediately raised the daityas to his thighs and beheaded them with the chakra.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>8 9 kAtyAyanIs</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/shaktayaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/8-9-kAtyAyanIs/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/shaktayaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/8-9-kAtyAyanIs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://x.com/blog_supplement/status/1828650914103656741?t=meMb0UNEU-urrBDjv-n4vw&amp;amp;s=19&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The incantations of the 9 kAtyAyanI-s are preserved in a Mongol variant of the bhUtadAmara text. With a minimal patina, these seem to have been absorbed from a shaiva text. The Skt text mentions 8 kAtyAyanI-s, but the text gives 9: &amp;ldquo;aShTau bhUta-rAj~nI-kAtyAyanI-vidyAH paThita-mAtreNa sidhyanti ||&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The sumbhakAtyAyanI is probably a bauddha insert into the original set of the remaining 8. The rite is prescribed thus:&#xA;The sAdhaka goes to a cemetery and repeats one of the kAtyAyanI mantra 1008 times for three days. He offers them blood arghya in a calvaria when they manifest.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>chAmuNDA etymology</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/shaktayaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/chAmuNA-etymology/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/shaktayaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/chAmuNA-etymology/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The etymology of the goddess chAmuNDA has mystified old &amp;amp;modern scholars alike. The great mantravAdin bhAskararAya correctly realized that it might stem from  some local (non-Aryan) tongue.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Within the Sanskrit tradition the paurANika-s have attempted to give it various functional explanations within the context of the battles fought by the goddess. While the most prevalent one is in mahAsaravatI cycle relating to the killing of chaNDa and muNDa -&amp;gt; chAmuNDA there are alternative versions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ekAnamshA and kAlI</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/shaktayaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/ekAnaMshA_kAlI/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/shaktayaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/ekAnaMshA_kAlI/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/blog_supplement/status/1511908631150743553&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(Continuing from &lt;a href=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/MT_lekhAH/hayagrIva-bhairava/&#34;&gt;hayagrIva bhairava note&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Finally, in the eastern locus, such a form is hinted in the kAlikA-purANa which assumes a vaiShNava hayagrIva center in kAmAkhya before the shAkta dominance. The worship of this hayagrIva is still recommended in the kAlikA &amp;amp; suggests a worship of hayagrIva conjoint with the bhairava, vAsudeva, viShNu and varAha.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Was kAmaakhya in the remote past likely a shrine to the vaiShNavI ekAnaMshA? The kalikapurANa hints at the widespread worship as per pañcarātra  before the curse to ugratArA.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>navAtmikA</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/shaktayaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/navAtmikA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/shaktayaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/navAtmikA/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://threadreaderapp.com/thread/1727938131704320456.html&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A rendering of the manifestation of supreme shakti navAtmikA of the pashchimAMnAya. The Agama explains the emergence of the navAtmikA form thus in the teaching of umA to shiva:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;शशाङ्कार्ध-कला ज्ञेया&lt;br&gt;&#xA;अम्बिका मध्यचन्द्रिका ।&#xA;एका एव पराशक्तिस्&lt;br&gt;&#xA;त्रिधा सा च प्रजायते ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The goddess ambikA manifest in the midst of the half-moon triplicated herself (technically the central triangle of the yantra). This triad of goddess are the shakti-s vAmA, jyeShThA and raudrI, corresponding to the first 3 deities of the vAmadeva-brahma-mantra&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>parA</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/shaktayaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/parA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/shaktayaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/parA/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The trika-kula&amp;rsquo;s parA devI seated on her supine consort bhairava-sadbhAva. The deity was to eventually have a deep influence on 2 of the other kula lineages, the dakShiNAMnAya (shrIkula) &amp;amp; pashchimAMnAya (kubjikA), the saiddhAntika-s (as the sarasvatI of the system), pA~ncharAtra vaiShNava (in ahirbudhnya saMhitA) and sAmAnya-smArta where her 5-headed form became the iconography &amp;amp;deity of the sAvitrI displacing the original deity of the veda savitR^i. Posting an alternative tricephalic version of her as ekavIrA encompassing the bhairavI&amp;rsquo;s aparA &amp;amp; parAparA&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tikla-cave triad</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/shaktayaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/Tikla-cave_sankarShaNa-vAsudeva-ekAnaMshA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/shaktayaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/Tikla-cave_sankarShaNa-vAsudeva-ekAnaMshA/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure class=&#34;thumbnail&#34;&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &lt;a href=&#34;../../../images/Tikla-cave_sankarShaNa-vAsudeva-ekAnaMshA.jpg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;img src=&#34;../../../images/Tikla-cave_sankarShaNa-vAsudeva-ekAnaMshA.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &#xA;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Archaeologist Wakankar discovered this sketch of the saMkarShaNa-vAsudeva-ekAnaMshA triad in a cave at Tikla on the mathurA-ujjayini route. He thought it was a king &amp;amp; queen with an attendant holding an umbrella. Neumayer&amp;rsquo;s sketch of figures &amp;amp; inscription below. However, the halAyudha, gadA, chakra indicate the deities. The inscription above looks like: 𑀤𑀩𑀼𑀓𑁂𑀦𑀁 𑀓𑀭𑀺𑀢𑀁 𑀑𑀟𑀸𑀦𑀓𑀺𑀢𑀁 : dabukenaM karitaM oDAnakitaM from a zoomed in image. May be it means &amp;ldquo;drawing made by dabuka&amp;rdquo; The proper instrumental would be dabukena but the dot&amp;rsquo;s there&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>tvaritA</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/shaktayaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/tvaritA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/shaktayaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/tvaritA/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://x.com/blog_supplement/status/1878183319051088255&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the 1000s, the chera mantravAdin IshAnashiva composed a mantra manual wherein he described tvaritA as being the form assumed by umA when she accompanied rudra to give arjuna the pAshupata missile.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;tvaritA was present in the ancestral kaula tradition and has a place in most of the successor kulAmnAya-s. In the pashchimAmnAya she is an emanation of kubjikA in the middle of a maNDala known as the khecharI chakra with the eponymous yoginI-s.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>urvashI</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/shaktayaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/urvashI/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/shaktayaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/urvashI/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/blog_supplement/status/1522978498897453056&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Almost 20 years ago on a defunct internet forum I&amp;rsquo;d written about the H cognate of Brigid. I agree with you that bhR^ihatI per se is not a theonym specific to the uShas-es. It is also applied to a distinct goddess sarasvatI. However, the cognate of Brigid does exist in our midst as the great goddess, mother bR^ihaddivA also known as the celestial urvashI &amp;ndash; we make an oblation to her in the patnIsaMyAja of the new/full-moons. It is possible an element of her theonym is laterally applied to both the uShas-es &amp;amp; sarasvatI in their celestial aspect. Her connection to the national goddess aspect is illustrated by the manifestation as urvaShI the mother of the bhArata dynasty. I&amp;rsquo;ve been intending to revisit this issue and write if the gods are favorable.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>vArAhI in kAmeshvarI system</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/shaktayaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/vArAhI_in_kAmeshvarI-system/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/shaktayaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/vArAhI_in_kAmeshvarI-system/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;(Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://threader.app/thread/1453218332967063558&#34;&gt;https://threader.app/thread/1453218332967063558&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The tirumantiram represents a syncretic tradition combining the siddhAnta &amp;amp; the traipura systems. The drAviDa-stotra to vArAhI you cited from it is indeed clear on this matter. It inheres specifically from the kameshvarI lineage of the traipura system that was particularly strong in the drAviDa country as presented in the lalitopAkhyAna. In that vArAhI &amp;amp; her 1000 pArShadI-s are incorporated independently of the other mAtR^i-s as daNDanAthA or the commander of the armies of kAmeshvarI.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>yoginI iconography</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/shaktayaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/yoginI-iconography/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/shaktayaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/yoginI-iconography/</guid>
      <description>&lt;table&gt;&#xA;  &lt;thead&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;th&gt;#&lt;/th&gt;&#xA;          &lt;th&gt;YoginI&lt;/th&gt;&#xA;          &lt;th&gt;Color&lt;/th&gt;&#xA;          &lt;th&gt;Head&lt;/th&gt;&#xA;          &lt;th&gt;Attribute&lt;/th&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;  &lt;/thead&gt;&#xA;  &lt;tbody&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;Ankusa&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;white&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;horse-headed&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;skull&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;Pasa&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;yellow&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;sow-headed&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;noose;&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;Sphota&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;red&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;lion-headed&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;iron&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;Ghanta&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;green&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;snake-headed&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;bell&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;Manuräksasi&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;brownish-white&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;yak-headed&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;skull&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;Brahmäni&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;yellowish-white&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;snake-headed&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;lotus&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;Raudri&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;greenish-white&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;leopard-headed&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;trident&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;Vaisnävi&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;bluish-white&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;marten-headed&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;cakra&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;Kaumäri&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;reddish-white&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;brown-bear-headed&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;spear&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;IndränI&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;white&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;black-bear-headed&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;noose&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;11&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;Pingala&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;yellow&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;bat-headed&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;cleaver&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;12&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;Santi&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;reddish-yellow&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;crocodile-headed&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;pitcher&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;13&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;Amrta&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;reddish-yellow&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;scorpion-headed&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;lotus&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;14&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;Saumi&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;whitish-yellow&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;hawk-headed&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;vajra&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;15&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;Dandi&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;greenish-yellow&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;fox-headed&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;rod&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;16&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;Raksasi&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;blackish-yellow&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;tiger-headed&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;blood-filled&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;17&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;BhaksasI&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;greenish-red&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;vulture-headed&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;club&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;18&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;RatI&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;red&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;horse-headed&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;corpse-torso&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;19&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;Rudhiramadi&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;pale-red&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;eagle-headed&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;rod&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;20&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;Ekacärini&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;red&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;dog-headed&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;vajra-cleaver&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;21&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;Manohärikã&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;red&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;hoopoe-headed&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;arrow&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;22&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;Siddhikari/Kauberi&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;greenish-red&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;deer-headed&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;pitcher&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;23&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;Vayudevi&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;bluish-green&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;snake-headed&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;flag&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;24&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;Agnayi&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;reddish-green&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;ibex-headed&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;fire-brand&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;25&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;Varähi&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;blackish-green&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;sow-headed&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;spiked-noose&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;26&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;Camundi&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;reddish-green&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;crow-headed&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;infant&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;27&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;Bhujanã&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;blackish-green&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;elephant-headed&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;club&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;28&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;Varunãoni&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;bluish-green&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;snake-headed&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;snake-lasso&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;29&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;Mahäkali&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;white&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;cuckoo-headed&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;Ankusa&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;30&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;Mahachagala&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;yellow&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;goat-headed&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;noose&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;31&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;Mahakumbhakarni&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;red&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;lion-headed&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;iron&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;32&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;Lambodarã&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;black-green&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;snake-headed&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;bell&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;  &lt;/tbody&gt;&#xA;&lt;/table&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Yoginis</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/shaktayaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/yoginis/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/shaktayaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/yoginis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;yogapitha-kramodaya&#34;&gt;yogapITha-kramodaya&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The yogapITha-kramodaya, one of the earliest surviving yoginI-kaula tantra-s, has an abhichArikA rite, performed in the cemetery, which is related to the terrific essence-sucking yoginI rites of the bhairava-srotas. The center of this yAga of 7 yoginI-s one named kusumamAlinI (= hAkinI based on her mantra). She is surrounded by the six yAkinI, shAkinI, kAkinI, lAkinI, rAkinI and DAkinI (some names corrupted in the Nepalian manuscript). These are none other than the dhAtunAthA-s or the “tissue-yoginI-s” of the dakShiNAmnAya associated with chakra-s of the spinal kula-patha (ekavR^ikSha: suShumNa) and the 7 dhatu-s. These, according to the YPK, corresponding to each of the 7 in the above order, are: semen, bone, connective tissue (sinew), muscle, marrow, blood, and skin. In the rite, they are called upon to afflict the respective tissues of the enemies.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>कौशिकी</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/shaktayaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/kaushikI/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/shaktayaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/kaushikI/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the archaic skandapurANa the goddess kaushikI daughter of umA and rudra places her various emanations across greater India thus:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;bahuputrikA (a kaumAra goddess) &amp;amp; pralambA  lankA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;lambauShTI, kiMnarI &amp;amp; vR^iShadaMshA in siMhala;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;revatI (a kaumAra goddess) in gokarNa;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;mukhamaNDikA (kaumAra goddess) in pANDya; shivA in AbhIra;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;shAnti in varaNAtaTa;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;prabhA in vatsagulma&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;lakShmI in kollagiri;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;upakA in pArashIka (Iranic land),&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;vAyasI in yavanadesha (Greek land);&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;prachaNDA at tukhArasthAna (Tocharia);&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;lambikA in kausala,&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;jayA+vijayA at svapura (?)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;prabhAvatI in kali~Nga;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;jayantI in hastinApura;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;ShaShThI in kashmIra;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;saramA in malaya;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;pUtanA in suvIra;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;mR^ityu in piShTapura;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;bahumAMsA in koTIvarsha;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;kaTapUtanA in paundravardhana;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;aspR^iShTA in madhyadesha;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;kiMnarI-2 in barbara;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;nirAyAsyA &amp;amp; chitragaNTA in vArANasI;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;mahAkAlI in ujjayinI;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;vAnarI in shabara-desha.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This list of 32 goddesses include kaushikI herself in the vindhya-s is likely the old list of shaktI-pITha-s that later expanded in number. Some of them survive as is to date. Most famous is lakshmI of kollagiri in modern Maharashtra.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
