<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;1 The Mahāvidyās as a Group on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/tantric-divine-feminine/1_The_mahAvidyAs_as_a_Group/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;1 The Mahāvidyās as a Group on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/tantric-divine-feminine/1_The_mahAvidyAs_as_a_Group/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 The Ten Mahāvidyās</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/tantric-divine-feminine/1_The_mahAvidyAs_as_a_Group/01_The_Ten_mahAvidyAs/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/tantric-divine-feminine/1_The_mahAvidyAs_as_a_Group/01_The_Ten_mahAvidyAs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The order in which the Mahavidyas are given varies somewhat, as do the goddesses included in the group. In contemporary sources, however, the following goddesses in the following order are most common: (1) Kali, (2) Tārā, (3) Tripura-sundari (Sodasi), (4) Bhuvanesvari, (5) Chinnamasta, (6) Bhairavi, (7) Dhumavati, (8) Bagalāmukhī, (9) Matangi, and (10) Kamala. The ten are described in most sources as follows:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Kali is black, which in fact is what her name means. She has a fierce countenance, stands on the supine body of the god Siva, and has four arms. Her upper left hand holds a bloodied cleaver and her lower left hand a severed head. Her right upper hand makes the sign &amp;ldquo;fear not,&amp;rdquo; and her lower right hand makes the gesture of bestowing boons. She is naked, apart from a garland of severed heads and a girdle of severed arms; her hair is unbound and disheveled; and she is often standing in a cremation ground or on a battlefield. She is almost always mentioned as the first of the Mahavidyas and occupies a preeminent place in the group. In some texts and in some settings, the other Mahavidyas are understood to arise from her and to be her different forms.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02 Typical Literary and Iconographic Contexts</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/tantric-divine-feminine/1_The_mahAvidyAs_as_a_Group/02_Typical_Literary_and_Iconographic_Contexts/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/tantric-divine-feminine/1_The_mahAvidyAs_as_a_Group/02_Typical_Literary_and_Iconographic_Contexts/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Mahavidyas are prominent primarily in tantric literature and in a few late *sakta **purdnas *and *upa **purdnas *(minor, later, or subsidiary *purdnas). *The *tantras *contain little narrative material about the Mahavidyas. They are primarily interested in providing the details of how to worship the Mahavidyas and do not dwell on the meaning of their symbolism or stories that feature them. A typical tantric treatment of a Mahavidya includes, first, her mantra, which is believed to represent her essence; a devotee seeking the goddess&amp;rsquo;s blessing or power must repeat it continually. Next, the goddess&amp;rsquo;s *dhydna *(meditation) mantra describes her physical appearance in some detail; again, the devotee is to fill his or her mind with this description of the goddess while ritually approaching her. The text also gives the goddess&amp;rsquo;s *rahasya *(essence or secret), which is usually similar to her *dhydna *mantra. It also lists her *kvaca *(armor), usually in the form of a prayer to protect her devotee on all sides. A *tantra *usually includes the goddess&amp;rsquo;s *name **stotra, *a list of her names or epithets. Sometimes it describes her yantra (a schematic drawing generally composed of circles, triangles, and stylized lotuses), along with directions for constructing and meditating upon it. In addition to this, the text sometimes gives directions for routine *piijd *(worship), in which various items are offered to the goddess.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03 The Mahāvidyās as Forms of the Mahādevī</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/tantric-divine-feminine/1_The_mahAvidyAs_as_a_Group/03_The_mahAvidyAs_as_Forms_of_the_mahAdevI/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/tantric-divine-feminine/1_The_mahAvidyAs_as_a_Group/03_The_mahAvidyAs_as_Forms_of_the_mahAdevI/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Both literary and iconographic materials give the general impression that the ten Mahavidyas are different forms of an overarching, transcendent female reality, who is usually referred to simply as the Mahadevi (great goddess). An underlying assumption of many *sakta *texts is that the highest reality is the Great Goddess, and this infinitely great being manifests herself in a wide variety of forms. Indeed, this is perhaps the central feature of Hindu *sdkta *theology in those texts.16 Many myths in *sakta *literature describe a goddess, or the goddess, as producing other goddesses from her own body. In such cases she often announces that she assumes different forms at different times to maintain cosmic stability,17 to bless a particular devotee, or out of a sense of sport or playfulness. The theological idea is that ultimate reality, which is female in essence and form, displays herself in a great variety of ways for different purposes. Some texts even say that wherever a female being exists, there the goddess reveals herself, being present in every female form.18 This theme is strong and obvious in the case of the Mahavidyas. Their presence in *devi *temples seems to state: &amp;ldquo;The goddess enshrined in this place assumes many forms.&amp;rdquo; The Mahavidyas are the concrete expression of the idea of &amp;ldquo;many forms.&amp;rdquo; In the case of goddesses who are identified with a particular place, and who are not well known outside their local areas, association with the Mahavidyas lends them a cosmic, universal, transcendent dimension. The presence of the Mahavidyas in a goddess temple identifies a local or regional goddess with an all-India mythology or symbolic structure, lending her a certain prestige.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04 Mahāvidyā Origin Myths</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/tantric-divine-feminine/1_The_mahAvidyAs_as_a_Group/04_mahAvidyA_Origin_Myths/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/tantric-divine-feminine/1_The_mahAvidyAs_as_a_Group/04_mahAvidyA_Origin_Myths/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have come across five versions of the origin of the Mahavidyas as a group. In one of these versions, the Mahavidyas are different forms of the goddess Sati; in a second version they are forms of the goddess Parvati; in a third they arise from the goddess Kali, herself one of the Mahavidyas; in a fourth they are forms of the goddess Durga; and in a fifth they are said to arise from the goddess Sataksi, who is also identified with Sakambhari and Durga.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05 Interrelationships among the Mahāvidyās</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/tantric-divine-feminine/1_The_mahAvidyAs_as_a_Group/05_Interrelationships_among_the_mahAvidyAs/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/tantric-divine-feminine/1_The_mahAvidyAs_as_a_Group/05_Interrelationships_among_the_mahAvidyAs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As a group, the Mahāvidyās present a curious collection of goddesses. If there is an internal coherence to the group that explains how its members are related to each other, it is not readily apparent. Neither in textual sources nor in the contemporary oral tradition have I been able to discover an obvious pattern or logic to the inclusion of these ten goddesses in the same group. There are hints in some texts, and some of my informants have speculated about the question. These hints and speculations cover a wide range of possibilities.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>06 Worship of the Mahāvidyās</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/tantric-divine-feminine/1_The_mahAvidyAs_as_a_Group/06_Worship_of_the_mahAvidyAs/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/tantric-divine-feminine/1_The_mahAvidyAs_as_a_Group/06_Worship_of_the_mahAvidyAs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Mahāvidyās are approached in a variety of ritual contexts, and the worship of one Mahavidya may differ from that of others. Some of the Mahāvidyās, for example, have ancient and widespread cults that existed, and still exist, quite apart from the Mahāvidyās as a group. This is the case with Kali, Tara, Tripura-sundari, and Kamala, for example. In general, though, we can think of their worship as taking place primarily in two contexts: in temples, where they are served by priests and where people come to take part in public worship, and in temporary places marked off by individual aspirants, where worship is undertaken in tantric fashion, either right-handed or left-handed. Although temple and tantric styles of worship have some similarities, they are quite different in mood and style.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>07 The Mahāvidyās and Magical Powers</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/tantric-divine-feminine/1_The_mahAvidyAs_as_a_Group/07_The_mahAvidyAs_and_Magical_Powers/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/tantric-divine-feminine/1_The_mahAvidyAs_as_a_Group/07_The_mahAvidyAs_and_Magical_Powers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We have already touched on the association of the Mahavidyas with magical powers, but it is so persistent that we should discuss it in more detail before turning to a treatment of the individual goddesses. Hindu literature is full of stories in which individuals, often demons, undertake ascetic and meditative practices in order to acquire special abilities with which they hope to achieve power, wealth, sex, or some other worldly pleasure or reward. In these stories, it is clear that they employ meditative and ascetic practices to attain selfish, worldly goals rather than what we might think of as spiritual ones. Texts on yoga say that one can acquire special powers *(siddhis) *by practicing yoga, but warn against indulging in them and thereby perverting the spiritual quest.89&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>08 The Significance of the Term *Mahāvidyā *</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/tantric-divine-feminine/1_The_mahAvidyAs_as_a_Group/08_The_Significance_of_the_Term_mahAvidyA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/tantric-divine-feminine/1_The_mahAvidyAs_as_a_Group/08_The_Significance_of_the_Term_mahAvidyA/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A literal translation of the term *mahavidya *is &amp;ldquo;great knowledge,&amp;rdquo; while a somewhat less literal translation might be &amp;ldquo;supreme (or superior or complete) knowledge (or wisdom).&amp;rdquo; There are several possibilities for what the name tells us about the nature and function of the Mahāvidyās. It is not obvious why these ten goddesses should have been so designated, but several explanations are possible.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I have been told by two scholars of Tantrism in Varanasi105 that the term *dasamahavidya *as it applies to the ten goddesses is technical and means the &amp;ldquo;ten great mantras,&amp;rdquo; *vidya *generally being used in this technical sense in tantric contexts. In his commentary on the *Lalitd-sahasrandma, *Bhaskararaya says: &amp;ldquo;The difference between *Mantra *and *Vidya *is that the former has reference to male deities and the latter to female ones.&amp;ldquo;106 Indeed, the first order of business in many tantric texts that discuss or describe the Mahāvidyās is to give their mantras, which consist of a few syllables. The mantra, it is often said, is highly secret and extremely powerful. It is a given in the tantric context, in fact, that the mantra is identical with the goddess. It is not that the mantra *belongs **to *the goddess, which is the way one is often tempted to understand the relationship between the deity and the mantra; the situation, rather, is that the mantra *is *the goddess. Jan Gonda says: &amp;ldquo;The essence of a *mantra *&amp;hellip; is the presence of the deity: only that *mantra *in which the *devata *has revealed his or her aspects can reveal that aspect. The deity is believed to appear from the *mantra *when it is correctly pronounced.&amp;ldquo;107&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>09 Concluding Observations</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/tantric-divine-feminine/1_The_mahAvidyAs_as_a_Group/09_Concluding_Observations/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/tantric-divine-feminine/1_The_mahAvidyAs_as_a_Group/09_Concluding_Observations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The ten Mahāvidyās form a distinctive group of deities. Although it includes some well-known goddesses, such as Kali and Laksmi, most of them are little known apart from this group, and several of the goddesses are strikingly unusual (Chinnamasta, Dhumavatl, and Bagalamukhi in particular). The group does not particularly manifest characteristics and functions that typify *sakta *Hinduism, yet they are often said to represent the Mahadevi in her diverse forms. Several texts and secondary sources imply that they sum up, or circumscribe in some fashion, the main features of the Mahadevl. Nonetheless, the group lacks many features considered central to *sakta *theology and religion.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
