<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;MT on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/kuberaH/meta/MT/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;MT on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 09 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/kuberaH/meta/MT/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Matters of religion the</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/kuberaH/meta/MT/2019-07-09_matters-of-religion-the-vayaviyaM-kaubera-vratam/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/kuberaH/meta/MT/2019-07-09_matters-of-religion-the-vayaviyaM-kaubera-vratam/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2019/07/09/matters-of-religion-the-vayaviya%e1%b9%83-kaubera-vratam/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Matters of religion: the Vāyavīyaṃ Kaubera-vratam&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;setting&#34;&gt;Setting&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The bus came to halt at the underground stop. Vrishchika of pretty tresses got off the bus and walked up the stairs to reach the over-bridge. She reached the middle of the bridge and stood there looking out expectantly at the road. It was a remarkably clear day and she could see the yonder horizon where the azure heights of father Dyaus met his lover mother Pṛthivī clad in the verdant vesture of the distant woods. Vrishchika passed into a reverie at that sight and remained oblivious to the throng of people who criss-crossed the bridge in either direction. Suddenly, an ugly man sidled up beside her and before she could react to his presence he said: “Ma’am do you visit the Hindu temple at Śukramārga?” Vrishchika: “On rare occasions.” The man responded: “We need wealthy patrons like you to visit the temple more often and make donations. Please do so devī”. So saying he handed a pamphlet to her. Vrishchika wondered: “A soothsayer at the temple of the Vāyu-born vānara had once told my family that I would be the wealthiest of all my sisters. But I’m hardly in that state now. Yet, why does he even think I’m wealthy?” She snapped out of that train of thought and waved the ugly man away saying “śubham astu! It is far way from my place but I’ll try.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
