<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>History on संस्कारे विश्वासटिप्पणयः</title>
    <link>file:///storage/emulated/0/notesData/saMskAra/kalpaH/general/history/</link>
    <description>Recent content in History on संस्कारे विश्वासटिप्पणयः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    
	<atom:link href="file:///storage/emulated/0/notesData/saMskAra/kalpaH/general/history/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Icon worship</title>
      <link>file:///storage/emulated/0/notesData/saMskAra/kalpaH/general/history/mUrti-pUjA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>file:///storage/emulated/0/notesData/saMskAra/kalpaH/general/history/mUrti-pUjA/</guid>
      <description>References (MT).
Early provenance and convergence  &amp;ldquo;Many branches of the Indo-European tree show signs for veneration of icons: Greeks, the syncretic Neoplatonic religion, Romans, Germanics, Balts and Slavs, Iranians and Indians. But not all Indo-European groups show evidence for large-scale temple construction right from inception: we find little evidence (as we saw above) amongst early Indians, early Balts or even Iranians. So it is not impossible that iconic worship of some kind was always there amongst Indo-Europeans from the ancestral period, but construction of public temples was potentially a convergent trait.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>श्रौतसम्प्रदायाः</title>
      <link>file:///storage/emulated/0/notesData/saMskAra/kalpaH/general/history/shrautam/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>file:///storage/emulated/0/notesData/saMskAra/kalpaH/general/history/shrautam/</guid>
      <description>&amp;ldquo;The AV practitioners are associated with the role of the Brahman but in reality have their own parallel śrauta tradition.&amp;rdquo; - (MT) &amp;ldquo;While the YV and SV texts as we have them today clearly postdate and presuppose the core RV, we know from the internal evidence of the RV that there were already YV and SV practitioners alongside the composers of the RV. E.g.: udgāteva śakune sāma gāyasi : You O bird sing a sāman like the udgātṛ.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>