<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>नासदीयसूक्तम् on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/tags/%E0%A4%A8%E0%A4%BE%E0%A4%B8%E0%A4%A6%E0%A5%80%E0%A4%AF%E0%A4%B8%E0%A5%82%E0%A4%95%E0%A5%8D%E0%A4%A4%E0%A4%AE%E0%A5%8D/</link>
    <description>Recent content in नासदीयसूक्तम् on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/tags/%E0%A4%A8%E0%A4%BE%E0%A4%B8%E0%A4%A6%E0%A5%80%E0%A4%AF%E0%A4%B8%E0%A5%82%E0%A4%95%E0%A5%8D%E0%A4%A4%E0%A4%AE%E0%A5%8D/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>नासदासीत्</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/brahma/Rk/nAsadIyam/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/brahma/Rk/nAsadIyam/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; includetitle=&#34;false&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;5&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sArasvata-vibhAgaH/brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/2/8_kAmya-pashavaH/9_08-16_nAsadIyam&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h5&gt;९ ०८-१६ नासदीयम् ...{Loading}...&lt;/h5&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; includetitle=&#34;false&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; unfilled=&#34;&#34; url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/10/129_nAsadIyam/&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h7&gt;१२९ ...{Loading}...&lt;/h7&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled=&#34;&#34; url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/10/129/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h9&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h9&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;एकादशेऽनुवाके त्रयोविंशतिसंख्याकानि सूक्तानि। तत्र ‘नासदासीत्’ इति सप्तर्चं प्रथम सूक्तं त्रैष्टुभम्। परमेष्ठी नाम प्रजापतिर्ऋषिः। वियदादिभावानां सृष्टिस्थितिप्रलयादीनामत्र प्रतिपाद्यत्वात् तेषां कर्ता परमात्मा देवता। तथा चानुक्रान्तं- ‘नासत्सप्त प्रजापतिः, परमेष्ठी भाववृत्तं तु’ इति। गतो विनियोगः॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;129 (955)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Creation&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Prajāpati Parameṣṭhin&lt;br&gt;&#xA;7 verses: triṣṭubh&lt;br&gt;&#xA;This is one of the most famous hymns of the R̥gveda, and one of the most signifi cant for later Indian cosmogonies. Because it is elusive and suggestive rather than  directly narrative, it has given rise to a wide variety of interpretations. The interpre tation we offer here follows the more extensive discussion in Brereton (1999), which  also refers to earlier literature and alternate interpretations.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;If this is a cosmogonic hymn, it is certainly a strange one, because the last verse  does not come to a conclusion but ends with a question. This incompleteness is  formally marked by both metrical and syntactic irregularities. The meter of verse  7b is two syllables short, leaving the its hearers to anticipate two beats that are not  there, and the syntax of 7d is incomplete since the poem ends with a relative clause  without a main clause. A close look at the rest of the hymn explains the reason for  these poetic strategies.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;In verse 1 there is a progression from negations—what existed was neither exist ing nor nonexisting and neither space nor heaven existed—to questions (1c) to  possibilities (1d). Verse 2 also begins with negation, here the negation of death,  deathlessness, and the signs of night and day. The only narrative progress is the  greater specificity in verse 2 about what is negated: there are no mortals or immor tals, there is no moon or sun. But whereas 1cd continued with questions and pos sibilities, 2cd provides an answer to the question of what existed: there existed “that  One,” which “breathed without wind.” In 1c the poet asked what “stirred,” or more  literally what “moved back and forth,” and in 2c the implicit answer is that the  “breathing” of the One moves back and forth. If 2c answers the question of 1c and  indeed if verse 2 defines what verse 1 suggests, then “that One” in verse 2 is the pre viously undefined thing that was neither existent nor nonexistent in verse 1.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Verse 3 sharpens the sense that nothing is happening, nothing material at least. It  apparently starts over once again: 3a ends “in the beginning” (ágre) just as 1a ends&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
