<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;03 PĀRVATĪ on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/03_pArvatI/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;03 PĀRVATĪ on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/03_pArvatI/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 EARLY REFERENCES TO PĀRVATĪ</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/03_pArvatI/01_EARLY_REFERENCES_TO_pArvatI/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/03_pArvatI/01_EARLY_REFERENCES_TO_pArvatI/</guid>
      <description>The goddess Satī-Pārvatī does not appear in Vedic literature. Several references to Śiva’s sister or wife do occur in Vedic texts, but the names for these deities only connect them tenuously, if at all, to the later Satī-Pārvatī. A being named Ambikā (a common epithet for several goddesses in the later tradition, especially Durgā) is called Śiva’s sister in one passage,1 while in another text she is said to be his consort.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>02 THE MYTHOLOGY OF SATĪ</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/03_pArvatI/02_THE_MYTHOLOGY_OF_satI/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/03_pArvatI/02_THE_MYTHOLOGY_OF_satI/</guid>
      <description>Not until the plays of Kālidāsa (fifth to sixth century A.D.) and the Purānas (A.D. 350 through the thirteenth century) do we find the central myths of Satī and Pārvatī told in detail. Two distinct goddesses emerge in this fully developed mythology: Satī, the daughter of Dakṣa, who becomes Śiva’s first wife, and Pārvatī, daughter of Himavat and his wife Menā, who is a reincarnation of Sati and becomes Śiva’s second wife.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>03 THE MYTHOLOGY OF PĀRVATĪ</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/03_pArvatI/03_THE_MYTHOLOGY_OF_pArvatI/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/03_pArvatI/03_THE_MYTHOLOGY_OF_pArvatI/</guid>
      <description>Pārvatī’s name, which means “she who dwells in the mountains” or “she who is of the mountain,” and her many epithets, such as śailasutā (daughter of the mountain peaks), Giriputrī (daughter of the mountains), Girīśājaputrī (daughter of the king of the mountains), Girīśā (mistress of the mountains), identify her with mountainous regions. It is quite possible that Pārvatī’s early history and origin may lie with a goddess who dwelled in the mountains and was associated with non-Āryan tribal peoples.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>04 TENSION AND RESOLUTION</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/03_pArvatI/04_TENSION_AND_RESOLUTION/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/03_pArvatI/04_TENSION_AND_RESOLUTION/</guid>
      <description>The main theme of the Pārvatī cycle of myths is clear. The association between Pārvatī and Śiva represents the perennial tension in Hinduism between the ascetic ideal and the householder ideal. Pārvatī, for the most part, represents the householder. Her mission in almost all renditions of the myth is to lure Śiva into the world of marriage, sex, and children, to tempt him away from asceticism, yoga, and otherworldly preoccupations. In this role Pārvatī is cast as a figure who upholds the order of dharma, who enhances life in the world, who represents the beauty and attraction of worldly, sexual life, who cherishes the house and society rather than the forest, the mountains, or the ascetic life.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>05 DEVOTION AND GRACE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/03_pArvatI/05_DEVOTION_AND_GRACE/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/03_pArvatI/05_DEVOTION_AND_GRACE/</guid>
      <description>Another important facet of Pārvatī is her role as a model of devotion to Śiva, as the devotee of the Lord par excellence. At several points in her mythology Pārvatī is described as devoted to Śiva, as unswerving in her attachment to him, and as incapable of being dissuaded from doting on him despite the most outrageous reports concerning his uncivilized, bizarre habits.76 Her remarkably steadfast, indeed, stubborn, devotion to him is most obvious during her long period of asceticism when she undertakes heroic bodily mortifications in order either to be granted the boon of having Śiva for her husband or to attract the attention of Śiva himself.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
