<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/AdityAH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/AdityAH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Bhaga</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/AdityAH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/bhaga/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/AdityAH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/bhaga/</guid>
      <description>Source: TW
The gods bhaga and savitR^i have overlapping functions. However, the action of their functions is in different domains.
As an analogy, one may point to the tripartition of indra, parjanya and dyaus.
The true apprehender of the shruti, after careful meditation on these gods, starts to see why, despite their overlapping functions, they are distinct in their domains.
Then there is some overlap of function with tvaShTR^i (and his ectype dhAtR^i).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>dhAtR</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/AdityAH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/dhAtR/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/AdityAH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/dhAtR/</guid>
      <description>(Source: https://threader.app/thread/1447434449222881285)
Who is the deity dhAtR? The later itihAsa-purANa place him in the Aditya class. In the RV it may be an epithet for multiple deities, but explicitly it mentioned as an epithet for visvakarman, who in turn is an epithet of the ancient tvaShTR. tvaShTR accompanies the the wives of the gods &amp;amp; other goddesses at the ritual. He appears in a similar role accompanying the sarasvatI and sinIvAlI in the sArasvata rite.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Iranic mitra</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/AdityAH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/iranic-mitra/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/AdityAH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/iranic-mitra/</guid>
      <description>Source: TW
A kuShANa coin showing mithra with a mace: the mace was called a gadha in the Iranic tradition but explicitly equated with the vajra in the case of mithra in the famous manthra with a counter-religious overlay (see below) from long incantation to him in the Zoroastrian branch of the Iranic tradition:
hishtaite aom vâshahe mithrahe vouru-gaoyaoitôish
On a side of the vehicle of mithra, the lord of wide cow-fields,</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>तपती</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/AdityAH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/tabiti/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/classes/AdityAH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/tabiti/</guid>
      <description>The non-Zoroastrian Iranic goddess Tabiti likely cognate of Indian tapatI.+++(5)+++ She is the solar goddess daughter of the sun. It is possible that the shaka rulers traced descent from her, such as the shaka ruler shown with the drinking horn in front of her. This legend was likely transmitted to Japan as she was syncretized with Amaterasu &amp;amp; the same legend adopted as the found myth of the Japanese emperors.+++(5)+++</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
