<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;1 Preface on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/0/1_Preface/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;1 Preface on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/0/1_Preface/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 Development</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/0/1_Preface/01_Development/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/0/1_Preface/01_Development/</guid>
      <description>THE WRITING OF THIS VOLUME TOOK ME BY SURPRISE. I never envisaged it as part of my “research program” until it began to form a life of its own. Eventually, it grew from childhood to adolescence and, typical of adolescence, began to exact unreasonable demands on my resources, including time, place, and modes of thought. Having now achieved maturity, it demands to be set free. On the whole, I would have preferred to be in India translating Sanskrit and examining manuscripts, rather than working on a project like this that imposed on me a new and very different set of intellectual, psychic, and even physical demands.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>02 Meditation on personhood</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/0/1_Preface/02_Meditation_on_personhood/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/0/1_Preface/02_Meditation_on_personhood/</guid>
      <description>After several years, at first intermittently, of data gathering and absorbing stories of possession, then reading and reflecting on theories of possession, and finally engaging it actively, I have arrived, with this book, at a meditation, a perilously intimate one, on personhood, which is sometimes, though not always, contiguous with selfhood. As the title of the book suggests, I find myself attempting to reconcile in this project the self, possessed, with a presentable veneer of self-possession.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>03 Incompleteness</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/0/1_Preface/03_Incompleteness/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/0/1_Preface/03_Incompleteness/</guid>
      <description>If my selection of material appears planned but extravagant, the reason is that the planning came to life as a learning process, like perfecting a rāga: I found a few unique scales and constantly improvised on them. Thus, the extravagance could never be exhaustive. The material turned out to be much more extensive than I initially expected. In many key places, in dealing with the Mahābhārata, Tantra, and bhakti texts, for example, I was forced to be illustrative and selective.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>04 Study of possession</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/0/1_Preface/04_Study_of_possession/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/0/1_Preface/04_Study_of_possession/</guid>
      <description>I should say a few words here about the study of possession. In India and elsewhere, the field has been dominated by compartmentalized ethnographies and, less often, by histories of possession in specific lineages or local cultures. No syncretic history or synoptic account of possession in India has been attempted.1 While my intention here is to locate and capture such a history, I have tried to keep in mind the problems associated with “master narratives” and endeavored to avoid them.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>05 Films</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/0/1_Preface/05_Films/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/0/1_Preface/05_Films/</guid>
      <description>After this volume went into production, two films dealing with spirit possession were released that deserve comment here because they illustrate the point of the title of this book. One was an American film, The Exorcism of Emily Rose; the other was an Indian film, Paheli (The Riddle).1 What is striking about these films is their representation of the self possessed. Emily Rose was founded on the assumption of a naturalized, identifiable, and unitary self that was breached by demonic possession.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
