<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/rudraH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 09 Nov 2008 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/rudraH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>The chants of the rudra-s: a commentary based on our discussions</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/rudraH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2008-11-09_the-chants-of-the-rudra-s-a-commentary-based-on-our-discussions/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Nov 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/rudraH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2008-11-09_the-chants-of-the-rudra-s-a-commentary-based-on-our-discussions/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
bhuvanasya pitaraM gIrbhir AbhI rudraM divA vardhayA rudram aktau |
bR^ihantaM R^iShvam ajaraM suShumnaM R^idhag-ghuvema kavineShitAsaH ||
With these chants we exalt rudra, the universe’s father, by day and by night;
We specially invoke him, bright, lofty, un-aging, and well-disposed, inspired by the wise one.
[kavi= the wise one, i.e. rudra. In modern tantrika parlance the suShumna mentioned in this R^ik is taken to mean the suShumna nerve path, but it is clear that in the vaidika context in simply meant well-disposed.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>paschimAmnAyeshvarI and shiva of the shikhA</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/rudraH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-12-05_paschimamnayeshvari-and-shiva-of-the-shikha/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Dec 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/rudraH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-12-05_paschimamnayeshvari-and-shiva-of-the-shikha/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
We first salute the master of the school, matsyendra and ku~nkumAMbA who was his kulA~NganA without whom none of these mysteries would be known to us mortals.
“siddhamAtA vibhuH shabdarAshIti yonyArNavI vAgvishuddhAsi vAgeshvarI”
That provides the inspiration of the rudra-shaktI – mahAsenasambhoginI. The one with pretty curves, who is the queen under the chinchini tree, manifests simultaneously in all her glory in the great oDDiyAna, jAlandhara, pUrNagiri and kAmarUpa.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Killing of andhaka</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/rudraH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-11-17_killing-of-andhaka/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Nov 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/rudraH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-11-17_killing-of-andhaka/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
Having bowed to the one whose odd eye roasts the universe at the end of the kalpa we narrate his awful exploits.
When rudra and umA were sporting on the eastern ridges of the mandhara, umA closed the eyes of one who simply known as the god because even his name can terrify the uninitiated. When his eyes were closed by umA’s hand which had the complexion of coral and a golden lotus the universe turned exceedingly dark, for after all he is soma-sUryAgni-lochana.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The meditation and emanation of the pa~nchAkSharI vidyA</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/rudraH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-10-01_the-meditation-and-emanation-of-the-panchakshari-vidya/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Oct 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/rudraH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-10-01_the-meditation-and-emanation-of-the-panchakshari-vidya/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
We described earlier how one installs the yantra of mahAdeva pertaining to the pa~nchAkSharI vidyA and performs worship of it. Now we shall describe that meditation of and the mantra emanation from it.
-As one starts the meditation of the pa~nchAkSharI one sees the maNDala of eight kalA goddesses appearing in the eight directions:
vAmA- brilliant white complexion, (E); jyeShThA -blood red, (SE); raudri- white again, (S); kAlI- bright yellow, (SW) ; kalavikariNI- purple, (W); balavikariNI- shining gold, (NW); balapramathanI-black, (N) sarvabhUtadamanI-light red, (NE).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The circle of mAtR^i-s</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/rudraH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-08-07_the-circle-of-matri-s/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Aug 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/rudraH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-08-07_the-circle-of-matri-s/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
The mighty bhairava stands in the midst of the circle of eight mothers (He is invoked by the formula: skhAM skhIM skhauM mahAbhairavAya namaH||). On either side of the mothers are positioned the roaring vIrabhadra who emerged from the hair of The god and the frightful vinAyaka with a single tusk, both striking terror in the heart of the beholders. vIrabhadra is surrounded by several awful pramathas brandishing all manner of terrible weapons.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The saMkShipta-bhairava mantra</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/rudraH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-07-23_the-samkshipta-bhairava-mantra/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Jul 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/rudraH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-07-23_the-samkshipta-bhairava-mantra/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
The formulae of the fierce saMkShipta bhairava can be used to counter a range of mAraNa attacks. It is different from the amR^iteshvara vidya, like that described in the netra tantra tradition. The latter is shAntaM, while the saMkShipta bhairava formulae are ghoraM. It can also be used for mAraNa strikes when conjoined with mahAmArI, the mate of the fierce bhairava, and the mantra of yama. The bhArgava mArkaNDeya is the R^iShi of the mantra of the terrifying saMkShipta bhairava.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Arimaspas, dinosaurs, griffins and sharabha.</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/rudraH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-05-20_the-arimaspas-dinosaurs-griffins-and-sharabha/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 May 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/rudraH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-05-20_the-arimaspas-dinosaurs-griffins-and-sharabha/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
A persistant Indo-Iranian motif is that of the griffin, occuring in India as the sharabha. The sharabha may be described as an imaginary animal or as an incarnation of rudra in that form. The famous sharbhAstra weapon and the sharabhAstra mantra invoke this form of rudra. The form of viShNu known as the gaNDabherunda nR^isiMha is also inspired by the same beast. The greek chroniclers recorded the griffins as being associated with an Iranian tribe on the steppe known as the Arimaspas.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>rudra namaskaraM</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/rudraH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-04-19_rudra-namaskaram/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Apr 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/rudraH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-04-19_rudra-namaskaram/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
Some of the kaTha-s record a praise of rudra when ever they see evidence for rudra in nature:
daMShTrA-karAlaM divi nR^ityamAnaM hutAsha-vaktraM jvalanArka-rUpaM |
sahasra-pAdAkShi-shirobhi yuktaM bhavantam-ekaM praNamAmi rudraM ||
namo.astu somAya su-madhyamAya namo.astu devAya hiraNyabAho |
namo.agni-chandrArka-vilochanAya namo.ambikAyAH pataye mR^iDAya ||</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The wall of bagalAmukhi</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/rudraH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-03-18_the-wall-of-bagalamukhi/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Mar 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/rudraH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-03-18_the-wall-of-bagalamukhi/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
R told me that her amongst her chosen devatAs whose mantras are perfect with her is bagalAmukhI. Fourier of maNgalagrAma, was initiated into bagalAmukhI vidyAs by the powerful chera magician. bagalAmukhi deployments can be terrifying for the victim and there are many of them that are generally kept secret. Some bagalAmukhi deployment that I have come across include: 1) the dhattUra haritAla lepana prayogaM- the yellow orpinient made from a mixture of dhattUra bIja and turmeric which can used for stambhana and vashikaraNa.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>trishiro-bhairava</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/rudraH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-03-04_trishiro-bhairava/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Mar 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/rudraH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-03-04_trishiro-bhairava/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
Images of the hallowed trishirobhairava from kAshmIr, whose avatAra puruSha is dattAtreya. These idols were originally from temples of trishiro bhairava near parihAsapura. They show the left side ugramukha which is (rudra murti) and may have a kapAla, kamaNDalu and akShamAla in the hands. The same iconography is retained for dattAtreya but, the kApAla of the trishirobhairava form is not seen. The temples were destroyed and the idols damaged by the Moslems and their current status is unclear.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The praise of rudra</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/rudraH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-02-22_the-praise-of-rudra/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Feb 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/rudraH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-02-22_the-praise-of-rudra/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
001 namas te deva-devesha devAri-balasUdana |
002 devendra-bala-viShTambha deva-dAnava-pUjita ||
Salutations to one who is lord of all the gods to the destroyer of the enemies of devas. One who is the inciter of the strength of the celestial chief. One who is adored by both gods and demons.
003 sahasrAkSha virUpAkSha tryakSha yakShAdhipa-priya |
004 sarvataH-pANi-pAdAnta sarvatokShishiromukha ||
One who is thousand-eyed, one who is many-eyed, and one who is three-eyed.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ugra</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/rudraH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-12-29_ugra/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Dec 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/rudraH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-12-29_ugra/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
When the altar is piled, it is termed ugra. It is filled with the fury of rudra mahAdeva. The agni in the midst becomes rudra and the sacrificer readies to pacify him. He recites thus:
rudró vA eShá yád agnís tásya tisráH sharavyAH pratIcI tiráshcy anUcI
This fire is rudra, three are his missiles, one that strikes straight, one transversely, and one that strikes from below (These are the 3 stars of Orion, the invakas, which are the 3 arrows fired by rudra slaying prajapati).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>aghora bhairava prayoga</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/rudraH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-12-16_aghora-bhairava-prayoga/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Dec 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/rudraH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-12-16_aghora-bhairava-prayoga/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
When the bhairava mantras are appropriately discharged they are like arrows whizzing from the pinAka. The shatru senA is as though rushing forward when it is suddenly attacked from the flanks by flaming missile shot by the agents of rudra. Each bhairava mantra is like a shower of fatal arrows raining on them with unstoppable fury.
Meditate upon the Adi-guru, the kShatriya woman, lakShmI~nkarA, who is the founder of the lineage of teachers of the lore of the bhairava in the kali yuga, the great princess, the sister of the noble rAjan indrabhUtI.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The tale of the li~Nga</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/rudraH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-11-22_the-tale-of-the-linga/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Nov 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/rudraH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-11-22_the-tale-of-the-linga/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
The tale of the li~Nga as the phallus of shiva is found in several purANas and is hence not a late concotion. It can be traced back to the bhArgava redaction of the sauta literature. The following purANas state the story:
brahmANDa 1.2.27
kUrma 2.37
skanda 1.1.6, 7.1.187 and other references
vAmana 22.6.65
devIbhAgavata 4.20
shiva 4.12
The critical version of the core tale as can be reconstructed from the above sources goes thus:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ashvina stuti</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/rudraH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-05-30_ashvina-stuti/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 May 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/rudraH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-05-30_ashvina-stuti/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
The adi parvan of the mahAbhArata provides a remarkable “fossilized” sUktaM to the ashvins. It comes in the 3rd chapter of the adi parvan known as the pauShya section (1.3.60 in the critical Poona edition of the mahAbhArata). This section is a particularly interesting in terms of retaining some of the archaic structures of the epic, probably coming unadulterated from the original form of the jaya epic. Its frame narrates the tale of how janamejaya, the kuru emperor, and conqueror of takShashIla came to perform his infamous sarpa yaGYa to avenge the killing of his father parIkShit by the nAga chief.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>shUlinI</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/rudraH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-04-19_shulini/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Apr 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/rudraH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-04-19_shulini/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
The wings of sharabha are pratya~NgirA and shUlinI. shUlinI may be invoked to complement the invocation of pratya~NgirA. Her iconography is thus:
adhyArUDhAM mR^igendraM sajala-jaladhara-shyAmalAM hastapadmaiH shUlaM bANaM kR^ipANaM-ari-jalaja-gadA-chApa-pAshAn-vahantIM /
chandrottamsAM trinetrAM chatasR^ibhir-abhitaH kheTakAn bibhratIbhiH kanyAbhiH sevyamAnAM pratibhaTa-bhayadAM shUlinIM bhAvayAmi.
Her mantra may be combined with those of pratya~NgirA to rout the enemy. The mantra is provided as being:
jvala-jvala-padasyAnte shUlinIti padaM vadet /
duShTagrahaM humastrAnte vahnijAyAvadhirmanuH //</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Night of The god</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/rudraH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-03-09_night-of-the-god/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Mar 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/rudraH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-03-09_night-of-the-god/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
oM atitIkShNa mahAkAya kalpAntadahanopama jha~NkAra-bhairavAya namastubhyaM //
We invoke the fierce jha~NkAra-bhairava. We had worshipped the terrible god with the great litany, the mahAnyAsa on the great night that he may be pacified.
Having worshipped the great god we were reminded of the intriguing words of the illustrious Kashmirian Tantric abhinavagupta of shrinagara in his great work the tantrAloka (TA 15.264b-15.266):
na khalveSha shivaH shAnto nAma kashcidvibhedavAn // 264</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Forms of the pratya~NgirA R^ik</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/rudraH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-03-05_forms-of-the-pratyangira-rik/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Mar 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/rudraH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-03-05_forms-of-the-pratyangira-rik/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
yAm kalpayanti no arayaH krUrAm kR^ityAm vadhUm iva /
tAm brahmaNA pari nijmaH pratyak kartAram R^icchatu //
This version is seen in the R^igveda khila 4.5.1. It may be used for countering kR^ityAs via the procedure recommended by the vidhAna of shaunaka.
yAM kalpayanti no .arayaH krurAM kR^ityAM vadhumiva /
tAM brahmaNA .apanirnudmaH pratyak kartAramR^ichChatu //
This version is seen in the paippalAda saMhitA of the atharvaveda and is used in the kR^ityA destroying atharvanic rites and the tantric pratya~NgirA paddhatis.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The drinking of poison</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/rudraH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2004-12-23_the-drinking-of-poison/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Dec 2004 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/rudraH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2004-12-23_the-drinking-of-poison/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
While the bhAgavataM is considered a vaiShNava text, it contains an highly magnified stotra to rudra. The stotra contains yet another example of the classical macrantropic motif that is so pervasive in Hindu thought since the puruSha sUktaM and the ashvamedha brAhmaNaM. It is full-fledged development was in India and not in Mesopotamia or Egypt. I provide a translation of the stotra given that the available ones are unsatisfactory.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>tripurAntaka brAhmaNa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/rudraH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2004-12-11_tripurantaka-brahmana/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Dec 2004 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/rudraH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2004-12-11_tripurantaka-brahmana/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
o3M teShAmsurANAM tisraH pura AsannayasmayyavamA.atha rajathA.atha hariNI tA devA jetuM nAshaknuvan tA upsadaivAjigIShan tasmAdAhuryashcaivaM veda yascha nopasadA vai mahApuraM jayanIti ta iShugaM samaskurvatAgnimanIkagaM somagaM shalyaM viShNum tejanaM te bruvan ka imAmasiShyatIti rudra ityabruvan rudro vai kruraH so.asyatviti so.abravIdvaraM vR^iNA ahameva pashUnAmadipatirasAnIti tasmAdrudraaH pashUnAmadipatistAgaM rudrovAsR^ijat sa tisraH puro bhittvaibhyo lokebhyo.asuran prANudate ||
The Asuras had three citadels; the lowest was of iron, then there was one of silver, then one of gold.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>rudra- his agents</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/rudraH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2004-05-19_rudra-his-agents/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 May 2004 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/rudraH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2004-05-19_rudra-his-agents/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
vIrabhadra: He emerged from a fragment of the matted locks of rudra for the killing of prajApati dakSha. He wrought havoc in the midsts of the deva armies and destroyed the demons created by bhR^igu before going on to behead dakSha. He then revived dakSha with a goat’s head.
kAla bhairava: Created by rudra for the beheading of the 5th head of brahma which was mocking rudra. For this he acquired the pApa of brahmahatyA and had to perform the kApAlika vrata.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>agni Ishvara rudra</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/rudraH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/agni-Ishvara-rudra/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/rudraH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/agni-Ishvara-rudra/</guid>
      <description>Source: TW
The yajurveda is where the identification of the term Ishvara with rudra gets established. rudra the Ishvara can destroy the ritualists progeny &amp;amp; animals. Hence, he must pacify rudra.
TS:
सोऽनु॑ ध्यायति॒
स ई᳚श्व॒रो रु॒द्रो भू॒त्वा
प्र॒जां प॒शून् यज॑मानस्य॒ शम॑यितोः ।
Hence, down the line when in the ritual where agni is carried in the ass cart he is said to become the destructive Ishvara, TS:
स ई᳚श्व॒रः प्र॒जाः शु॒चा प्र॒दहः॑</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Boar</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/rudraH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/boar/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/rudraH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/boar/</guid>
      <description>WRT the boar; In Iranic tradition:
verethraghnO ahuradhAtO hu kehrpa varAzahe
paiti-erenO tizhi-dãstrahe arshnO tizhi-asUrahe
hakeret-janO varAzahe anu-pOithwahe grañtahe ||
verethraghna is invoked as a mighty boar.
In yasna 6.14:
ukhrem taxmem dAmOish upamanem yazatem yazAmaide |
This dAmOish upamana is mighty boar that accompanies mithra on his march. The Germanic occurrence of a boar is hence interesting.
&amp;hellip; I&amp;rsquo;ve convergently suspect that the north- Germanic Hild swine as Odr was an ectype of Odin giving a direct link to the rudrian divo varAha of the Arya-s.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>dakSha-yAga</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/rudraH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/daksha-yAga/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/rudraH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/daksha-yAga/</guid>
      <description>Source: TW
interesting to note that the Vayu Purana account of the episode also has this feature of Devi not being there as Sati, but instead with Shiva the whole time and similar sentiments to the above
GhorAngirasa analysis The Mbh version is indeed similar to Vāyupurāṇa version. The fact that the story occurs with both Sati &amp;amp; Pārvati kind of lends support to the notion that the story is not about FIL-SIL dynamics but really goes back to the archaic Vedic meme of the Devas ostracising Rudra.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>tryambaka</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/rudraH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/tryambaka/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/rudraH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/tryambaka/</guid>
      <description>What does the term tryambaka mean? We hold that it means mother -&amp;gt; goddess. This is supported by the fact the ritual devoted to this form of rudra also invokes the goddess ambA. The ritual sUtra-s mention the 3 rudrian goddess rudrANI, bhavAnI &amp;amp; sharvANI &amp;ndash; pAraskara of SYV tradition. Thus, the form tryambaka is one with the 3 goddesses. The association of rudra with a group of goddesses is also alluded to in the shatarudrIya and the AV texts.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Unravellings</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/rudraH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/unravellings/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/rudraH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/unravellings/</guid>
      <description>Source: TW
Take Rudra. There is every good reason to believe that there were at least a few Ṛṣis or their peers &amp;amp; contemporaries who may have genuinely seen him as little more than a wrathful deity who punished wrongdoers by going after their cattle or families. There is no need to be delusional about this. There were also Ṛṣis who started getting “hints” as to Rudra’s transcendental nature even in the Ṛgveda.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>अमृतेश्वरः</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/rudraH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/amRteshvaraH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/rudraH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/amRteshvaraH/</guid>
      <description>This is the correct answer with two further Kashmirian exemplars of the same deity. The one I posted is to my knowledge the 3rd surviving exemplar. The deity is amR^iteshvara-bhairava whose vidyA is taught in the netra-tantra which has a masterly commentary by the Kashmirian mantravAdin kShemarAja, a cousin and student of abhinavagupta.
The consort of the deity is amR^italakShmI or amR^iteshvarI. At one point in time the deity was widely worshipped throughout the Indosphere.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>व्रात्यः वायुः</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/rudraH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/vrAryaH_vAyuH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/rudraH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/vrAryaH_vAyuH/</guid>
      <description>vrAtya-kANDa of atharvaveda The opening of the vrAtya-kANDa of the atharvaveda has elements that have continued to find expression through the history of the shaiva tradition. Here the prAjapatya &amp;amp; aindra flavors of the religion are incorporated within the early shaiva framework of the vrata.
व्रात्य आसीद् ईयमान एव स प्रजापति सम् ऐरयत् ॥
स प्रजापतिः सुवर्णम् आत्मन्न् अपश्यत् तत् प्राजनयत् ॥
तद् एकम् अभवत् तल् ललामम् अभवत् तन् महद् अभवत् तज् ज्येष्ठम् अभवत् तद् ब्रह्माभवत् तत् तपोऽभवत् तत् सत्यम् अभवत् तेन प्राजायत ॥</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
