<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;10 THE MĀTṚKĀS on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/10_THE_mAtRkAs/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;10 THE MĀTṚKĀS on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/10_THE_mAtRkAs/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 THE EARLY HISTORY OF THE MĀTṚKĀS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/10_THE_mAtRkAs/01_THE_EARLY_HISTORY_OF_THE_mAtRkAs/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/10_THE_mAtRkAs/01_THE_EARLY_HISTORY_OF_THE_mAtRkAs/</guid>
      <description>Certain groups of goddesses occupy an important place in the Hindu perception of the divine feminine. A band of divinities known simply as the Mātṛkās, “mothers,” is among the most significant groups of goddesses. Early references to the Mātṛkās date to around the first century A.D., but they rarely specify their number; the implication in some passages is that they are innumerable. The goddesses are only mentioned as a group, and it is as a group that they function and are characterized in almost all references throughout the tradition.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>02 THE MĀTṚKĀS IN THE LATER TRADITION</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/10_THE_mAtRkAs/02_THE_mAtRkAs_IN_THE_LATER_TRADITION/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/10_THE_mAtRkAs/02_THE_mAtRkAs_IN_THE_LATER_TRADITION/</guid>
      <description>The popularity of the Mātṛkās in the postepic period (after A.D. 400) is attested by the many casual references to them in literary works. The Natya-śāstra recommends that the Mātṛkās be worshiped prior to setting up the theater and stage for dance performances (13.66),13 Both the Cārudatta of Bhāsa and the Mṛcchakaṭika of śūdraka refer to offerings made to the Mātṛkās at crossroads.14 The Harṣacarita of Bāṇabhaṭṭa mentions an ascetic who dwells at an old matṛ-gṛha, a “house (or temple) of the Mothers,” where young nobles perform rites on behalf of the king’s health.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
