<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;GA on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/articles/GA/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;GA on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/articles/GA/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Evolution and revelation</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/articles/GA/evolution_and_revelation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/articles/GA/evolution_and_revelation/</guid>
      <description>Source: TW
If a God transcends time &amp;amp; is omniscient, He or She will contain within themselves all possible forms, syncretisms, lores, liturgies &amp;amp; rites, which &amp;ldquo;manifest&amp;rdquo; in human history over time in a gradual way that we call &amp;ldquo;evolution of ideas&amp;rdquo;.
Each and every &amp;ldquo;infinitesimal&amp;rdquo; snapshot of a God&amp;rsquo;s meme as it would have originated in a priest&amp;rsquo;s or seer&amp;rsquo;s head throughout history, be it &amp;ldquo;imagination&amp;rdquo; or intuition, be it the deity&amp;rsquo;s lore/ mythos, iconography, etc, has &amp;amp; always will exist in the God.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Identifying alien forms</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/articles/GA/identifying-alien-forms/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/articles/GA/identifying-alien-forms/</guid>
      <description>Source: TW
Identifying with non-Arya deities What I stated above, mutatis mutandis, applies to who we see as “Non-Sanskritic” Village deities as well. This deity was likely never known to the Ṛṣis or the Āryas of that time &amp;amp; perhaps was conceived much much later. But that deity of “Non-Ārya” provenance was all along a “husk” concealing a transcendental deity with whom we are much more familiar, who was waiting for us to discover this chain/layers of deities leading up to him.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Irresistable Polytheism</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/articles/GA/irresistable-polytheism/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/articles/GA/irresistable-polytheism/</guid>
      <description>Source: TW
While I&amp;rsquo;m no expert, the essence of &amp;lsquo;polytheism&amp;rsquo; for me is that we see multiplicity intrinsic to the very concept of &amp;ldquo;god&amp;rdquo;. And against this simple criterion, the way the Hindu mind has seen plurality in the divine can only be described as insanely complex &amp;amp; beautiful. Others may point out some other &amp;ldquo;underlying unity&amp;rdquo; (nirguNabrahman, puruSa-prakRti as in sAMkhyA, etc). Yet, none of this metaphysical speculations have prevented the natural inclination of the Hindu mind to conceptualize &amp;amp; celebrate the diversity in the divine.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Philosophical-grounding</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/articles/GA/philosophical-grounding/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/articles/GA/philosophical-grounding/</guid>
      <description>Source: TW
Religion needs common worship &amp;amp; ritual but a competing concern is that young gens across the world increasingly have a “standardised” sense of what they want from a religion &amp;amp; find it important to obtain a “profound/sophisticated” basis for popular rituals, lore/myths, etc.. (granirau )
Daoist trouble A case in point is the situation of folkish Daoism in Sim̐hapurī (Daoism has a remarkably sophisticated cosmology, metaphysics &amp;amp; ritual but the way it is articulated &amp;amp; experienced in SG is what matters) vs that of Buddhism.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Transcendentalization</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/articles/GA/transcendentalization/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/articles/GA/transcendentalization/</guid>
      <description>Source: TW
As part of a response, one sees the following:
Village gods like Munīśvara have now been incorporated into mainstream pantheon as an extension of Śiva &amp;amp; there are four Āgamika temples devoted to him now. Karuppaṇasvāmī (already underwent semi-“transcendentalization” in India when Śaiva Brāhmaṇa priests in TN came up with Āgamika installation rites for him a few centuries ago) keeps undergoing further such transcendentalization in TN &amp;amp; that’s slowly catching on in SG.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
