<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;Articles on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/articles/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;Articles on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 26 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/articles/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Form - Islamic objection</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/articles/form_islamic-objection/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/articles/form_islamic-objection/</guid>
      <description>Source: TW
Anyway, this argument that his deity cannot assume a form “because it is a logical impossibility” is bs. Ahadith mention Adam being created in his deity’s image. This not only shows that his deity is not only not formless, but is also finite.
If the response is that “this form is not comparable to anything in this world” it still doesn’t mean there is formlessness. In that case, H will respond (from scripture) that Bhagavān’s forms are not some imitation of creation, but is fashioned of Māyā which is His own Śakti.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Form multiplicity</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/articles/form-multiplicity/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/articles/form-multiplicity/</guid>
      <description>Source: TW
Thread by @RangaTheDude
This is an interesting question. I&amp;rsquo;ll generalize the problem and attempt to provide a coherent answer from H insider POV.
Problem: If you accept the proposition that a deity you worship is a later day addition to H pantheon, and perhaps even inspired by a contact with foreign tribe, how can you continue to worship without slipping into cognitive dissonance? @halleyji please let me know if I captured the problem reasonably accurately.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Physics &amp; powers</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/articles/physics_powers/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/articles/physics_powers/</guid>
      <description>Source: TW
Ontologically speaking, whether you realize it or not, you&amp;rsquo;ve been exposed to a higher truth level than your forefathers. You&amp;rsquo;ve learned science. You know now that Amadioha does not command thunder. You simply cannot have the same relationship with it as your forbears who sincerely thought he did. So if you worship Amadioha unironically in 2024, I&amp;rsquo;ll tell you for free that the Amadioha you think you&amp;rsquo;re worshiping is not the same one your fathers did.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
