<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 26 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Notes on the Vaiṣṇava</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2023-12-26_notes-on-the-vaiShNava-retinue-deities-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2023-12-26_notes-on-the-vaiShNava-retinue-deities-1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2023/12/26/notes-on-the-vai%e1%b9%a3%e1%b9%87ava-retinue-deities-1/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Notes on the Vaiṣṇava retinue deities-1&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;nature-of-viṣvaksena&#34;&gt;Nature of viṣvaksena&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The śaiva pattern of worship,&lt;br&gt;&#xA;which is especially emphasized in the Iśāna-srotas (siddhānta),&lt;br&gt;&#xA;features the Nirmālya-devatā, Caṇḍeśvara&lt;br&gt;&#xA;with roots in the older Pāśupata atimārga.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;This deity receives offerings, such as leaves and flowers, that have been initially offered to Rudra-sadāśiva.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;In the śaiva-saura system,&lt;br&gt;&#xA;he appears as Tejaścaṇḍa,&lt;br&gt;&#xA;the Nirmālya-devatā of Sūrya.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Vaikhānasa and Pāñcarātrika systems of the Vaiṣṇava tradition also have an equivalent deity in the form of Viṣvaksena.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;However, we posit in this note that he also encompasses to a degree features of the ape-faced śaiva deity Nandin (sometimes bull-faced, especially in the later reflexes of the tradition),&lt;br&gt;&#xA;who is one of the great gaṇeśvara-s of Rudra’s hordes,&lt;br&gt;&#xA;and the sons of Rudra, the gods Skanda and Vināyaka.+++(5)+++&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The roots of Vaiṣṇavam a</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2020-01-02_the-roots-of-vaiShNavam-a-view-from-the-numerology/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2020-01-02_the-roots-of-vaiShNavam-a-view-from-the-numerology/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2020/01/02/the-roots-of-vai%e1%b9%a3%e1%b9%87avam-a-view-from-the-numerology-of-vedic-texts/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The roots of Vaiṣṇavam: a view from the numerology of Vedic texts&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;viṣṇu&#34;&gt;Viṣṇu&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;While glorified with a 1000 names in the famous stotra of the early Sātvata tradition of the Mahābharata, in the texts of an even earlier period the god primarily went under that name &lt;strong&gt;Viṣṇu&lt;/strong&gt;. Indeed, even the litany of the 1000 names begins with viśvaṃ viśṇur vaśatkāraḥ signaling the connection to that ancient layer of tradition, with viśvam i.e, “everything” being an etymological elaboration of his name Viṣṇu, “the all-pervader”. Further, vaṣaṭkāra indicates his link to the Vedic ritual (the vaṣaṭ offering to Viṣṇu is already specifically mentioned twice in the Ṛgveda) wherein we can trace the meteoric rise of this god as the head-deity of one of the great sectarian streams of the āstika-s.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Some speculation on the Indo-Aryan cult of the vasu-s</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2009-11-10_some-speculation-on-the-indo-aryan-cult-of-the-vasu-s/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Nov 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2009-11-10_some-speculation-on-the-indo-aryan-cult-of-the-vasu-s/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2009/11/10/some-speculation-on-the-indo-aryan-cult-of-the-vasu-s/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Parts of the below material were inspired by extended collaborative&#xA;discussions with shrI KR.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/24766652@N05/4096942791/&#34; title=&#34;shraviShTha by somasushma, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;figure class=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &lt;a href=&#34;https://i1.wp.com/farm3.static.flickr.com/2558/4096942791_83e4de895d.jpg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;img src=&#34;https://i1.wp.com/farm3.static.flickr.com/2558/4096942791_83e4de895d.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;shraviShTha&#34; title=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &#xA;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The winter solstice/year beginning in the last part of shraviShTha (1300&#xA;BCE)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The three great categories of gods in the veda and beyond&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Though absent in the extant Iranian texts, the oldest Indo-Aryan texts&#xA;recognize the presence of three major categories of deva-s — the vasu-s,&#xA;rudra-s and Aditya-s. This triad is mentioned on a number of occasions&#xA;in the R^igveda. However, the R^igveda does not explicitly enumerate the&#xA;members of any of these three categories deva-s and only mentions some&#xA;of the members of each category by name. In the origin mythology&#xA;presented in RV 10.72 there is an allusion to 8 Aditya-s, but there is&#xA;hardly any evidence that this number was uniformly intended throughout&#xA;the RV. In the shatarudrIya of the yajur veda there is an allusion to&#xA;thousands of rudra-s (a concept preserved in the shaiva tantra-s,&#xA;especially of the Urdhva-srotas belonging to a much later era). The vasu&#xA;who is explicitly named in the RV is agni. Three Aditya-s, mitra, varuNa&#xA;and aryaman are frequently mentioned, but the other candidates of this&#xA;category are hazy (beyond aMsha and dakSha who are named but rarely if&#xA;ever made any offerings). In the brAhmaNa texts the number, if not the&#xA;identity, of the constituent deities in each category appears to have&#xA;been standardized. The gAyatrI is associated with the vasu-s as they are&#xA;8 in number and so is the number of syllables in a foot of this meter.&#xA;The triShTubh is associated with the rudra-s as they are 11 in number&#xA;and so is the number of syllables in a foot of this meter. The jagati is&#xA;associated with the Aditya-s as they are 12 in number and so is the&#xA;number of syllables in a foot of this meter. Since then, the number of&#xA;deities in each category has remained conserved in Hindu tradition. The&#xA;constituents of the vasu category were explicitly laid out first in the&#xA;shatapatha brAhmaNa as being the deities who composed the world namely&#xA;agni, vAyu, pR^ithivi, sUrya, antarikSha, dyaus, soma and nakShatra-s&#xA;(SB 11.6.3.6). Subsequent texts provided conceptually similar lists,&#xA;while trying to systematize to world-forming deities to a greater extant&#xA;by adjusting the names to include entities such light and water, and the&#xA;Pole star as a representative of the nakShatra category.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The sarvAtman hymn to viShNu</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-12-31_the-sarvatman-hymn-to-vishnu/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 Dec 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-12-31_the-sarvatman-hymn-to-vishnu/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2006/12/31/the-sarvatman-hymn-to-vishnu/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The sarvAtmAn hymn to viShNu shows some variations between recensions&#xA;and traditions but form accepted amongst smArtas has 40 core shlokas&#xA;corresponding to Mbh 12.47.23-63. This an extremely important hymn of&#xA;viShNu, comparable to the hymn to rudra by the goat-faced dakSha. The&#xA;R^iShi of sarvAtmaka mahAvaiShNava stotra is given as bhagavAn vyAsa,&#xA;the Chandas is anuShTubh, the devAtA is sarvAtmaka mahA-viShNu.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Its importance lies in the fact that it might represent one of the&#xA;earliest post-vedic compositions to viShNu, within an early vaiShNava&#xA;lineage that was strongly affiliated with vedic ritualism. An important&#xA;point to note is that the critical version of the hymn shared by all&#xA;recensions and practiced by smArtas does not have any mention of the&#xA;avatAra-s or the vAsudeva-centric elements of sAttvata that contributed&#xA;to pA~nchAratra. So its original composition was possibly outside of&#xA;these streams and was latter swallowed into the sAttvata context (as&#xA;much of the vaiShNava material in the mahAbhArata belongs to the early&#xA;sAttvata tradition). We suspect that there were 3 streams of early&#xA;vaiShNavism: 2 associated with the kR^iShNa yajurvedins: 1) The&#xA;taittirIyas, of which the vaikhAnasa branch gave rise to an early&#xA;vaiShNava system. 2) the kaTHas who possibly incorporated an early&#xA;avatAra model centered on yaGYa-varaha (viShNu smR^iti, viShNu-dharma&#xA;and viShNu-dharmottara eventually emerged from this school). 3) The&#xA;sAttvata-s who promulagated the chatur-vyUha system and developed other&#xA;aspects of the avatAra concept centered on kR^iShNa. This was the&#xA;precursor of the later pA~ncharAtra. It is possible, but not certain,&#xA;that this school might have had association with a shukla-yajurvedic&#xA;shAkha called ekAyana. This school was strong in Mathura and interacted&#xA;with the early shaivas and kaumAra-s, who also have a presence in the&#xA;mahAbhArata. In later history all these three schools extensively&#xA;exchanged concepts, espcially in terms of the avatAra concept.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>astras of viShNu</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-12-17_astras-of-vishnu/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Dec 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-12-17_astras-of-vishnu/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2006/12/17/astras-of-vishnu/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The powers of the great god, who envelops the universe with his 3&#xA;strides, dwelling in the ocean of existence sleeping on the snake of&#xA;time, watched upon by the epitome of the female kind, are put forth as&#xA;deadly 105 astras.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The head of them is the chakra known as sudarshana:&lt;br&gt;&#xA;dhyAtaM sakR^id bhagavAneka koTyaghaugham haratyaraM |&lt;br&gt;&#xA;sudarshanasya taddivyaM bhargo devasya dhImahi ||&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The pravartaka astras of viShNu:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>memories arising from the padmAvatI stones</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-09-24_memories-arising-from-the-padmavati-stones/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Sep 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-09-24_memories-arising-from-the-padmavati-stones/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2006/09/24/memories-arising-from-the-padmavati-stones/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://photos1.blogger.com/blogger/2010/410/1600/padmavati2.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;figure class=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &lt;a href=&#34;https://i0.wp.com/photos1.blogger.com/blogger/2010/410/320/padmavati2.jpg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;img src=&#34;https://i0.wp.com/photos1.blogger.com/blogger/2010/410/320/padmavati2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &#xA;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As mentioned earlier in my explorations of the maharaTTa country with&#xA;shUdra-shreShTha, S and Mis-creant I came across several aniconic&#xA;padmAvatI stones painted orange with a lead paint. However, in the&#xA;exploration of Satmala we did see a couple of iconic padmavatI images.&#xA;One of them was still in worship and another was largely in neglect in a&#xA;dung-ridden area. This image was strange in having a nAstIka arihant&#xA;inscribed on her. A drAviDa nastIka savant brought to my attention that&#xA;they worshiped padmAvatI as a shasana devI, that is an agent of a&#xA;nAstIka tirthankara. He gave me a print of the jaina version of the&#xA;deity that resembled the weathered image in part. This suggests that&#xA;padmAvatI was worshiped by nAstIka-s as well as astIka-s and tribes in&#xA;that region. I wonder if the padmAvatI at Venkatadri is also a&#xA;syncretized version of the old padmAvatI widely worshiped throughout the&#xA;Deccan in the early medieaval period.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>daNDin’s pUrvapIThikA of dasha-kumAra-charitra</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-04-22_dandins-purvapithika-of-dasha-kumara-charitra/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Apr 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-04-22_dandins-purvapithika-of-dasha-kumara-charitra/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2006/04/22/dandins-purvapithika-of-dasha-kumara-charitra/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The 3rd stride of viShNu as well as his snake is the enduring Hindus&#xA;symbol of the axis that precesses with the passage of kAla or time.&#xA;Right from the R^igveda this axial role of viShNu is at the fore in all&#xA;conceptions of him. We have alluded to this a few times before, see:&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2004/12/06/the-snake-of-vishnu/&#34;&gt;snake of&#xA;viShNu&lt;/a&gt;,&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2005/09/05/the-finnish-epic/&#34;&gt;the Finnish&#xA;epic&lt;/a&gt;,&#xA;and more obliquely in &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2005/08/07/the-fall-of-prahlada/&#34;&gt;fall of&#xA;praHlAda&lt;/a&gt;.&#xA;The element of the axis and its precession is very much a part of the&#xA;“core mythology” of viShNu: 1) the horn of matsya- the new axis being&#xA;provided for the world after its shift due to precession. 2) The mandAra&#xA;mountain as the staff for the churning of the world ocean being borne by&#xA;viShNu on his back in the form of kUrma. 3) varAha raising the “world&#xA;plane” with his tusks- the world plane being the equatorial circle&#xA;intersecting the ecliptic. It had sunk because the precession had pushed&#xA;the old intersection with the ecliptic below the plane. 4) nR^isimha&#xA;emerging by shattering the pillar- the old axis is broken by the flow of&#xA;time by precession. 5) trivikrama with his three steps stabilizes the&#xA;new world plane (equatorial circle), the ecliptic’s high point (step 2)&#xA;and the precessing axis (step 3). It is in this context that the great&#xA;R^ikSha jAmbavant is described as circumambulating trivikrama as he took&#xA;his great strides. This represents the new axis being established and&#xA;the constellation of the Great Bear (represented as the bear jAmbavant)&#xA;making a circle of the north celestial pole. Indeed viShNu himself is&#xA;identified with the constellation of the shishumAra or Draco associated&#xA;with the old north pole from earlier period of Aryan memory. As the&#xA;knowledge of precession is very subtle (even alluded in the opening of&#xA;the maitrayaNi brAhmaNa fragment by shAkAyanya who was well aware of&#xA;these matters) the third step of viShNu is secret and was only know to&#xA;the great kavi-s.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The peculiar mythology behind the mAyAvAmana mantras</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-04-16_the-peculiar-mythology-behind-the-mayavamana-mantras/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Apr 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-04-16_the-peculiar-mythology-behind-the-mayavamana-mantras/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2006/04/16/the-peculiar-mythology-behind-the-mayavamana-mantras/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The hAdi mata votaries from the North also preserved a range of kramas,&#xA;now largely reduced to auxilliary rites associated as AvarNa invocations&#xA;of their primary rite of tripurasundarI. This follows the basic pattern&#xA;seen in the shrIvidyArNava’s procedures. Many of these are strikingly&#xA;interesting such as the invocation of the terrific graveyard-ranging&#xA;bahurUpa bhairava and his wife, a special mantra of the supreme&#xA;Anandabhairava, the 8-handed amR^itasUrya invocation and the formulae&#xA;derived from the kaTha yajurveda. Here, however I briefly allude to a&#xA;remarkable “left-handed” form of viShNu and his mythology.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The left-handed aShTha-mukha gaNDabheruNDa nR^ikeshari mantra</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-03-11_the-left-handed-ashtha-mukha-gandabherunda-nrikeshari-mantra/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Mar 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-03-11_the-left-handed-ashtha-mukha-gandabherunda-nrikeshari-mantra/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2006/03/11/the-left-handed-ashtha-mukha-gandabherunda-nrikeshari-mantra/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It is said that there are two emanations of the mantra of the most&#xA;terrible aShTha-mukha gaNDabheruNDa nR^isimha (AMGN)- a dakShiNa and&#xA;vAma form. The right-handed form is said to lie in the text termed the&#xA;bhIma-tantra which is a upa-tantra of the ananta-vijaya saMhitA of the&#xA;viShNu-yAmala tradition. The left-handed form is said to like in the&#xA;text termed vAmA-tantra which is also an upa-tantra of the ananta-vijaya&#xA;saMhitA. Not much is know of the full extant of these texts ( if they&#xA;survive in an degree at all they are obviously kept a close secret) but&#xA;fragments relevant to ritual performance have been transmitted to those&#xA;in the know. It is however clear that the left-handed vidya has&#xA;propagated considerably in various guises. AMGN is said to have 8 heads&#xA;of the leonine form with saber teeth, whereas two heads of the&#xA;dinosaurian form (which are apparently concealed as per the vAma&#xA;mantra). He has 16 hands with a garland of skulls and holds a chakra,&#xA;trident, gadA, sword, bow and arrow, in addition to various other&#xA;weapons. The mantra was narrated thus by mahAdeva to ishAnI when she&#xA;embraced him and kissed him:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The chakras of viShNu</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-02-14_the-chakras-of-vishnu/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Feb 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-02-14_the-chakras-of-vishnu/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2006/02/14/the-chakras-of-vishnu/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://photos1.blogger.com/blogger/2010/410/1600/sudarshana.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;figure class=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &lt;a href=&#34;https://i0.wp.com/photos1.blogger.com/blogger/2010/410/320/sudarshana.jpg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;img src=&#34;https://i0.wp.com/photos1.blogger.com/blogger/2010/410/320/sudarshana.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &#xA;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;From viShNu emanate several chakra missiles, all of which may follow the&#xA;deadly sudarshana and discs when used in battle against the dAnavas and&#xA;rAkShasas. They represent the sum of the deadly destructive fury of&#xA;viShNu. Likewise, the sampUrNa chakra prayoga rite invokes these weapons&#xA;to power the countering or attacking mantra missiles.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The following are the chakras:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;mahArAtridhara chakra: This powered by mahAmAyA and is dark hued and&#xA;terrifying with a single spoke.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;uShash-chakra: This is powered by vAyu and agni and is of the color&#xA;of dawn and with two spokes&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;udaya chakra: This is powered by the fury of the world-destroying&#xA;venom of saMkarShaNa. It is the 3 spoked wheel&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;aishvarya chakra: This is powered by the all-prosperous pradyumna and&#xA;has 4 spokes.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;shaktimahAchakra: This is powered by the blazing aniruddha and has 5&#xA;spokes&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;ShaDara-chakra: This is powered by keshava and has 6-spokes. It comes&#xA;out from the sudarshana disc.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;mahAsudarshana chakra: This is powered by padmanAbha and has 12&#xA;spokes. It is the destroyer of the asuras and the fiery atri durvAsa.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;sahasrAra chakra: This is the wheel powered viShNu manifesting in the&#xA;parame vyoman. It blazes with a 1000 spokes with all chakras, terrible&#xA;shUlas, musalas, halAyudhas, gadAs, prAsa and other weapons surrounding&#xA;it.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ekAnamshA: a deity of tantric vaiShNavism</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-02-04_ekanamsha-a-deity-of-tantric-vaishnavism/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Feb 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-02-04_ekanamsha-a-deity-of-tantric-vaishnavism/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2006/02/04/ekanamsha-a-deity-of-tantric-vaishnavism/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://photos1.blogger.com/blogger/2010/410/1600/ekAnamshA.0.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;figure class=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &lt;a href=&#34;https://i1.wp.com/photos1.blogger.com/blogger/2010/410/320/ekAnamshA.0.jpg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;img src=&#34;https://i1.wp.com/photos1.blogger.com/blogger/2010/410/320/ekAnamshA.0.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &#xA;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The core pantheon of the pA~ncharAtra texts is the chaturvyuha or the&#xA;serial emanations of nArAyaNa. The primary manifestation of nArAyaNa is&#xA;vAsudeva, from whom emerge saMkarShaNa and pradyumna. From pradyumna&#xA;emerges aniruddha. This pantheon appears to be a unique feature of the&#xA;yadu tribes that subsequently seems to have spawned the classical&#xA;pA~ncharAtra. However, the early texts suggest that there was another&#xA;parallel system that appears to have largely passed out of subsequent&#xA;vaiShNavism. That was the cult of the goddess ekAnamshA. Who is she ?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>viShNu mahApanjara stotraM</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-11-25_vishnu-mahapanjara-stotram/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Nov 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-11-25_vishnu-mahapanjara-stotram/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2005/11/25/vishnu-mahapanjara-stotram/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;namo-namaste govindaM chakraM gR^ihya sudarshanaM |&lt;br&gt;&#xA;prAchyAM rakShasva mAM viShNo tvAm-ahaM sharaNaM gataH ||&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Salutations to govinda, who holds the sudarshaNa discus;&lt;br&gt;&#xA;I seek refuge in you, O viShNu protect me from the east.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;gadAM kaumodakIM gR^ihNa padmanAbha namo.astu te |&lt;br&gt;&#xA;yAmyAM rakShasva mAM viShNo tvAm-ahaM sharaNaM gataH ||&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Salutations to padmanAbha, holding the kaumodaki mace;&lt;br&gt;&#xA;I seek refuge in you, O viShNu protect me from the direction of yama&#xA;(south).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The vaiShNava mahAmantra</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-10-16_the-vaishnava-mahamantra/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Oct 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-10-16_the-vaishnava-mahamantra/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2005/10/16/the-vaishnava-mahamantra/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;oM oM oM hrIM hrIM hrIM shrIM shrIM shrIM 0M aM aM aM hauM hauM hauM&#xA;haMsaH haMsaH haMsaH oM hrIM shrIM namo viShNave //&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The mantra rahasyas:&lt;br&gt;&#xA;That great mantra encompasses a series of 3 praNavas. The 3 praNavas are&#xA;the AdhAra that is known as the brahman. This is followed by the 3&#xA;tArikAs and the 3 anutArikAs which are two wives of viShNu. They are the&#xA;supremre states with all things existing in these two shaktis of viShNu.&#xA;This sequence represents the primary reality which is the absolute&#xA;puruSha, the shAnta and the nAda that manisfest there after. shrI is an&#xA;intrinsic part of each stage in the form of time manifesting as nimeSha&#xA;and unmesSha.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The shrIdhara krama</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-10-15_the-shridhara_krama/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Oct 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-10-15_the-shridhara_krama/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2005/10/15/the-shridhara_krama/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The fragment of the totala tantra preserved by tradition has an important rite the shrIdhara karma to viShNu that is thus performed (we provide a edited version from a reasonably well made transcription):&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;-The upAsaka shall have a bath, then perform saMdhyA and then enter the sacrificial room.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;-He shall then wash his hands and feet and perform Achamana. He shall place his right palm on the left palm in the saMkalpa posture and utter the mUla mantra:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The dark hero of the yadus</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-08-27_the-dark-hero-of-the-yadus/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Aug 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-08-27_the-dark-hero-of-the-yadus/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2005/08/27/the-dark-hero-of-the-yadus/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The birth anniversary of the dark hero of the yadus dawned. We decided to&lt;br&gt;&#xA;recall his awful deeds in course of his momentous life that overlapped with the tumult taking place in the bhArata realms.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The yadu was born to vasudeva and devakI, who were imprisoned by kaMsa, devakI’s brother.The tyrant kaMsa had been told that devakI’s 8th son will kill him one day.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;devakI’s eighth son was born on a rohiNI aShtTami, and was spirited away by vasudeva to his cowherd friend nanda’s abode. Instead he brought back nanda’s daughter to replace his son.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;kR^iShNa devakIputra’s possible escape still worried kaMsa so he sent a demoness putanA to slay devakIputra. But kR^iShNa slew pUtana instead.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;kR^iShNa then still a child slew effortlessly demons such as triNavarta, aghAsura and dhenuka.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;kR^iShNa then subdued the nAga chief kaliya on the banks of the yamuna.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;kR^iShNa’s brother balabhadra, son of rohiNi and vasudeva slew the demon pralamba.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;devakIputra then killed the agents of kaMsa like shankachuda, ariSTa, keshi and vyoma.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;then kR^iShNa and balarAma proceeded to the court of kaMsa, at akrUra’s invitation.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;then the brother advanced to the capital of kaMsa, mathura, and were pitted against the wrestlers chANUra and muShTika, whom they promptly slew.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;then kR^iShna killed kaMsa by suddenly attacking him and restored ugrasena on the throne In course of his varied career the mighty bowman vAsudeva killed a number of powerful adversaries of the yadus. He successively destroyed, after killing kaMsa, kAlayavana, naraka the king of pragjyotiSha and his general mura, paundraka the false vAsudeva, jarAsandha via pANDava bhima, shishupAla during the rAjasUya of yuddhiShThira, shalva the great invader, dantavakra and vidhuratha.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>sudarshaNa rahasya</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-07-18_sudarshana-rahasya/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Jul 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-07-18_sudarshana-rahasya/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2005/07/18/sudarshana-rahasya/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Having bowed to the one sleeping atop the coils of the snake of time we&#xA;salute the greatest of his weapons.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;oM urugAyAya hum phaT //&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;That supreme emanation of the shakti of nArAyaNa manifested with a&#xA;predominance of her tejas, is as bright as many millions of suns, moons&#xA;and fires in profusion. It pervades the tryambaka vidya of the 7th&#xA;maNDala of the R^igveda. It is described as the supreme udyama, foremost&#xA;prANa and all weapons and shaktis of the hordes of viShNu and&#xA;vishvaksena arise from it. Of nArAyaNa modes of activity based on his&#xA;five functions this is the most effective. No single act conducted by&#xA;the supreme viShNu can performed with its aid. This is the sudarshaNa&#xA;disc. The emanation of sudarshaNa starts functioning at the moment of&#xA;the origin of the universe and lakShmi adheres to her chakra-rUpa even&#xA;as nArAyaNa sustains and absorbs creation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The praise of varAha mUrtI</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-03-12_the-praise-of-varaha-murti/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Mar 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-03-12_the-praise-of-varaha-murti/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2005/03/12/the-praise-of-varaha-murti/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;daMShTrAyAM vasudhA sashaila-nagarAraNyApagA huMkR^itau vAgIshI&#xA;shasite.anilo ravi vidhU bAhvoshcha dakShAnyayoH /&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The earth with its mountains, cities, forests and waterbodies are in his&#xA;tusks, his grunts are sarasvatI (vAgIshI). The air is his breath and the&#xA;sun and moon are his right and left hands.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;kukShau syurvasavo dishaH shrutipathe dasrau dR^ishoH pAdayoH padmottho&#xA;hR^idaye hariH pR^ithagamI pujyA mukhe sha~NkaraH //&lt;br&gt;&#xA;His belly is [made of] the vasus, in his ear are the directions, the&#xA;ashvins are his eyes, in his feet is the lotus born [brahma], in his&#xA;heart is viShNu and in his mouth is shiva.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>vibhavas of viShNu</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-03-10_vibhavas-of-vishnu/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Mar 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-03-10_vibhavas-of-vishnu/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2005/03/10/vibhavas-of-vishnu/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The vibhavas:&lt;br&gt;&#xA;padmanAbha&lt;br&gt;&#xA;dhruva&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ananta&lt;br&gt;&#xA;shaktIsha&lt;br&gt;&#xA;madhusudhana&lt;br&gt;&#xA;vidyAdhideva&lt;br&gt;&#xA;kapila&lt;br&gt;&#xA;vishvarUpa&lt;br&gt;&#xA;haMsa&lt;br&gt;&#xA;krodAtman&lt;br&gt;&#xA;vaDavaktra&lt;br&gt;&#xA;dharma&lt;br&gt;&#xA;vAgIshvara&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ekArNavashaya&lt;br&gt;&#xA;kUrma&lt;br&gt;&#xA;varAha&lt;br&gt;&#xA;nR^isimha&lt;br&gt;&#xA;amR^itAharaNA&lt;br&gt;&#xA;shripati&lt;br&gt;&#xA;kAntAtman&lt;br&gt;&#xA;rAhujit&lt;br&gt;&#xA;kAlanemighna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;pArijAtahara&lt;br&gt;&#xA;lokanAtha&lt;br&gt;&#xA;dattAtreya&lt;br&gt;&#xA;nygrodashAyin&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ekashR^i~Ngatanu&lt;br&gt;&#xA;vAmana&lt;br&gt;&#xA;trivikrama&lt;br&gt;&#xA;nara&lt;br&gt;&#xA;nArAyaNa&lt;br&gt;&#xA;hari&lt;br&gt;&#xA;kR^iShNa&lt;br&gt;&#xA;rAmo bhArgava&lt;br&gt;&#xA;rAmachandra&lt;br&gt;&#xA;vyAsa&lt;br&gt;&#xA;kalkI&lt;br&gt;&#xA;pAtAlashAyin&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>kShemendra on kalki</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-03-03_kshemendra-on-kalki/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Mar 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-03-03_kshemendra-on-kalki/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2005/03/03/kshemendra-on-kalki/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The great Kashmirian author in his text the dashAvatAracharitra which&#xA;was written in 1066 AD describes the conditions that would prevail on&#xA;the earth just before the coming of kalki.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;“The Turushkas, Pathans, Daradas and dwellers of Shakastan will cause&#xA;the earth to decay as do the leper his open oozing sores. Every&#xA;direction overrun by the dreadful mlechChas, the earth will resound with&#xA;the clash of swords drawn in combat and her soil will be soaked with&#xA;blood.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Buddhist kalki</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-03-01_the-buddhist-kalki/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-03-01_the-buddhist-kalki/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2005/03/01/the-buddhist-kalki/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The bauddhas have internalized the last incarnation of viShNu, the&#xA;all-destroying kalki or pramati who is said to annihilate the mlecchas&#xA;and dasyus and restore the world to the Aryas. The kAlachakra tantra of&#xA;the unclean upachInAchAra stream gives a highly remarkable account of&#xA;the end of the yuga. It’s parallels to the mainstream Hindu version are&#xA;unmistakable and appears to have been clearly derived from it [It is&#xA;even possible that there was a now lost Hindu version which might have&#xA;been a closer precursor of the version in the kAlachakra tantra]. But&#xA;the inspiration for the account from the dreaded Islamic violence is&#xA;very clearly seen and perceived by its author, and incorporated in&#xA;typical prophetic style seen in the purANas (verse 1.150 onwards of the&#xA;kalAchakra tantra). The nature of Islam was clearly understood by these&#xA;bauddha authors.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The snake of viShNu</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2004-12-06_the-snake-of-vishnu/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Dec 2004 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2004-12-06_the-snake-of-vishnu/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2004/12/06/the-snake-of-vishnu/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Upon the great snake shesha sleeps the great god viShNu, even as the the&#xA;kalpa wears out. He stirs only when the waters rise and threaten to sink&#xA;the world plane. This shesha is time and hence he is called ananta.&#xA;Thus, when viShNu sleeps on the coils of the great world snake he is&#xA;experiencing the cyclic passage of time.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Once the great god vAyu and the world snake ananta had a contest of&#xA;strength. shesha wound around the mount meru around which the world&#xA;revolves and vAyu was supposed to dislodge the snake from the great&#xA;mountain. The efforts of mAtarishvan to dislodge the great snake proved&#xA;futile for a long time eventhough the world shook with his terrible&#xA;gusts. Then in fury he uprooted the mount meru snake and all and hurled&#xA;the mountain with great ferocity. Under the impact of vAyu’s blow, meru&#xA;shattered and ananta lost his grip and surrendered. With meru shattered&#xA;the world shook and had no axis. The deva viShNu then stabilized the&#xA;shattered meru it with his foot.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Antiquity as major deity</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/antiquity_as_major_deity/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/antiquity_as_major_deity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Clearly there was the classic viShNu-focal system of vedic and earlier IE provenance; then there was the more local evolution in the Indo-Iranian borderlands of the vAsudeva-sAttvata tradition. The earlier harivaMsha was definitely focused on a version of the sAttvata tradition. But there was a parallel strand of vaiShNava tradition predominant among the vaikhAnasa-s &amp;amp; and an early strand of pA~ncharAtra-s that was closer to vaidika focality on viShNu.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The viShNu purANa tries bring the 2 together by giving devakIputra the focus of the &amp;ldquo;earthly&amp;rdquo; expression of the sAttvata religion a central place in the narrative. rAmachandra aikShvAkava is not given much space in this text. However, it goes on to clarify that the saMkarShaNa &amp;amp; vAsudeva are only amshAmsha, i.e 1/p*1/q fractions of the primal viShNu. So these avatAra-s are only parts or minor parts of viShNu, namely two hairs dropping off from him. Thus, it places the sAttvata heroes in more meaningful hierarchy with respect to the god himself. But like the shuklayajurveda verse there is a certain fractality. This little part of viShNu can itself have tremendous potency as exhibited by the saMkarShaNa and the vAsudeva.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>hayagrIva bhairava</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/hayagrIva-bhairava/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/hayagrIva-bhairava/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/blog_supplement/status/1511908631150743553&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A most remarkable Kashmirian 10 headed viShNu vishvarUpa from late kArkota age. The first triad of heads are the usual nR^isiMha-viShNu-varAha triad; the next triad is bhairava-maheshvara-umA; then the 3 vyUha deities; the worn-out one on the top is likely hayagrIva.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;One can find some parallels to vishvarUpa vibhava of viShNu from some pA~ncharAtrika texts. The above (haribhaktivilAsa quote) indeed seems to be a citation of hayashIrsha. It might also be seen as an expression of the general prescription given in the jayAkhya. However, the hayashrISha at the top makes think it might be related to the hayashIrsha-centric vishvarUpa.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>kAlachakraH</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/kAlachakraH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/kAlachakraH/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The kAlachakra that is also known as the god vAsudeva.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;āvartamānam ajaram vivartanam&lt;br&gt;&#xA;șan-nemikam dvādaśāram suparva |&lt;br&gt;&#xA;yasyedam āsye pariyāti viśvam&lt;br&gt;&#xA;tat kālacakram nihitam guhāyām ||&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Eternally turning forth and turning back,&lt;br&gt;&#xA;with a six-sectored felly, twelve spokes, and a good linchpin into whose mouth all existence rushes forth, that wheel of time is stationed in the [secret] cave of existence.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It goes back to the RV where viShNu is seen as setting the wheel of time of time in motion. There are several allusions to this in the bhArata.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Misc emanations</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/misc-emanations/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/misc-emanations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The nine sAttvata-s of the sAttvata-manDala of the pa~ncharAtra are: vAsudeva, balabhadra, pradyumna, sAtyakI, akrUra, aniruddha, gada, sAmba and nishaTha. An andhra mantravAdin replaced akrUra with kR^itavarman in his performance of the yAga.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;However, a distinct &amp;ldquo;vaiShNava&amp;rdquo; as opposed to &amp;ldquo;sAttvata&amp;rdquo; tradition present a concept of navavyUha, navanAyaka-s or navamUrti. There are are 1. vAsudeva; 2. saMkarShaNa; 3.pradyumna; 4. aniruddha; 5. nArAyaNa; 6. brahman; 7. viShNu; 8. varAha; 9. nR^isiMha. Some mantravAdin-s substitute hayagrIva for brahman. This 9 fold form appears to be a parallel of the shaiva navAtman-bhairava. The first 5 of these in one lineage is termed the pa&lt;del&gt;nchamUrti: saiddhAntika shaiva-s adopt this for their worship of viShNu within the maNDala of sadAshiva. In another lineage, the last 5 might be seen as the deities of the vaiShNava-pa&lt;/del&gt;nchabrahma-mantra-s.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modena deity</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/modena-deity/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/modena-deity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://threadreaderapp.com/thread/1578587848394932224.html&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A peculiar deity found in an apparently mithrAistic context at Modena. The deity has been interpreted as:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;a Roman rendering of the para-Zoroastrian deity zurvan akArana.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Orphic protogonic deity Phanes/ Protogonos;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Chronos.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Zeus who swallowed the latter.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The chronic association of the deity &amp;ndash; thus identifying him with zurvan is seen in the form of the zodiac around him &amp;amp; the snake winding around him which represents the periodicity of time &amp;ndash; an element associated the Indo-Aryan chronic deity viShNu. However, the links to the protogonic deity on the Indo-Aryan side are seen in the form of the two halves of the egg shells on which he is standing &amp;ndash; the hiraNyagarbha: e.g:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PanchopaniShat-tanuH</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/panchopaniShat-tanuH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/panchopaniShat-tanuH/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://x.com/blog_supplement/status/1923621246681399695&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The shaiva-s originally conceptualized rudra-sadAshiva as pa&lt;del&gt;nchamantra-tanu, i.e., one whose body is made up of 5 mantra-s. The pa&lt;/del&gt;ncharAtra has two variations of this theme. viShNu is said to assume this 5-fold form, pa&lt;del&gt;ncha-mUrti of viShNu, when “refracted” through his five shakti-s: parameShThinI, puruShi, vishvA, nivR^itti and sarvA. These shakti-s constitute the equivalent of the pa&lt;/del&gt;nchamantra-tanu of viShNu and are the source of prakR^iti:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;pa&lt;del&gt;ncha-shaktimayo devah paramAtmA jagat-prabhuh |&lt;br&gt;&#xA;pa&lt;/del&gt;nchendriya-samAyogah panchadhA j~nAnam ashnute ||&lt;br&gt;&#xA;(parama-saMhitA)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>vishvaxena</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/vishvaxena/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/vishvaxena/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It seems, given his name and function, viShvaksena evolved as a vaiShNava reflex of skanda. This is supported by the early kaumAra tradition where he is surrounded by the 4 vinAyaka-s like those companions of viShvaksena. Moreover, skanda played a key role in the creation of vinAyaka(-s) in one of the old traditions preserved in the voluminous skandapurANa. Notably, in a curious twist the shaiva vatulottara names skanda as viShvaksena and vishAkha as jayatsena once in the account of the AvaraNa of rudragaNa-s. An eastern tradition preserved in the merutantra records his worship along with sAtyaki &amp;ndash; probably an inheritance from an old sAttvata tradition which might have even conceived of sAtyaki as his incarnation.+++(5)+++&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>पुष्टिः सरस्वती</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/puShTi-sarasvatI/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/puShTi-sarasvatI/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://x.com/blog_supplement/status/783489936200794112&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Erotic eulogy of viShNu attributed to bhava-deva lost polymath pA~ncharAtrika tAntrika of the east who was minister&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;ॐ नमो भगवते वासुदेवाय ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;गाढोपगूढ-कमला-कुच-कुंभ-पत्र-&lt;br&gt;&#xA;मुद्राङ्कितेन वपुषा &lt;strong&gt;परिरिप्समानः&lt;/strong&gt; ।&lt;br&gt;&#xA;&lt;strong&gt;मा लुप्यताम्&lt;/strong&gt; अभिनवा वन-मालिकेति&lt;br&gt;&#xA;&lt;strong&gt;वाग्-देवतोपहसितो ऽस्तु&lt;/strong&gt; हरिः श्रिये वः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;With his body marked by the impressions of the unguent on the firm pot-like breasts of Kamalā (Laksmī) whom he had just hugged, he wished to embrace [the speech-deity].&#xA;May that Hari [then] taunted by the speech-deity thus, &amp;ldquo;Do not mess up your new forest-flower garland&amp;rdquo;, bring you wealth.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
