<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 26 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Notes on the Vaiṣṇava</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2023-12-26_notes-on-the-vaiShNava-retinue-deities-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2023-12-26_notes-on-the-vaiShNava-retinue-deities-1/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
Notes on the Vaiṣṇava retinue deities-1
Nature of viṣvaksena The śaiva pattern of worship,
which is especially emphasized in the Iśāna-srotas (siddhānta),
features the Nirmālya-devatā, Caṇḍeśvara
with roots in the older Pāśupata atimārga.
This deity receives offerings, such as leaves and flowers, that have been initially offered to Rudra-sadāśiva.
In the śaiva-saura system,
he appears as Tejaścaṇḍa,
the Nirmālya-devatā of Sūrya.
The Vaikhānasa and Pāñcarātrika systems of the Vaiṣṇava tradition also have an equivalent deity in the form of Viṣvaksena.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Some speculation on the Indo-Aryan cult of the vasu-s</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2009-11-10_some-speculation-on-the-indo-aryan-cult-of-the-vasu-s/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Nov 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2009-11-10_some-speculation-on-the-indo-aryan-cult-of-the-vasu-s/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
Parts of the below material were inspired by extended collaborative discussions with shrI KR.
The winter solstice/year beginning in the last part of shraviShTha (1300 BCE)
The three great categories of gods in the veda and beyond
Though absent in the extant Iranian texts, the oldest Indo-Aryan texts recognize the presence of three major categories of deva-s — the vasu-s, rudra-s and Aditya-s. This triad is mentioned on a number of occasions in the R^igveda.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The sarvAtman hymn to viShNu</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-12-31_the-sarvatman-hymn-to-vishnu/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 Dec 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-12-31_the-sarvatman-hymn-to-vishnu/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
The sarvAtmAn hymn to viShNu shows some variations between recensions and traditions but form accepted amongst smArtas has 40 core shlokas corresponding to Mbh 12.47.23-63. This an extremely important hymn of viShNu, comparable to the hymn to rudra by the goat-faced dakSha. The R^iShi of sarvAtmaka mahAvaiShNava stotra is given as bhagavAn vyAsa, the Chandas is anuShTubh, the devAtA is sarvAtmaka mahA-viShNu.
Its importance lies in the fact that it might represent one of the earliest post-vedic compositions to viShNu, within an early vaiShNava lineage that was strongly affiliated with vedic ritualism.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>astras of viShNu</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-12-17_astras-of-vishnu/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Dec 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-12-17_astras-of-vishnu/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
The powers of the great god, who envelops the universe with his 3 strides, dwelling in the ocean of existence sleeping on the snake of time, watched upon by the epitome of the female kind, are put forth as deadly 105 astras.
The head of them is the chakra known as sudarshana:
dhyAtaM sakR^id bhagavAneka koTyaghaugham haratyaraM |
sudarshanasya taddivyaM bhargo devasya dhImahi ||
The pravartaka astras of viShNu:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>memories arising from the padmAvatI stones</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-09-24_memories-arising-from-the-padmavati-stones/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Sep 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-09-24_memories-arising-from-the-padmavati-stones/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
As mentioned earlier in my explorations of the maharaTTa country with shUdra-shreShTha, S and Mis-creant I came across several aniconic padmAvatI stones painted orange with a lead paint. However, in the exploration of Satmala we did see a couple of iconic padmavatI images. One of them was still in worship and another was largely in neglect in a dung-ridden area. This image was strange in having a nAstIka arihant inscribed on her.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>daNDin’s pUrvapIThikA of dasha-kumAra-charitra</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-04-22_dandins-purvapithika-of-dasha-kumara-charitra/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Apr 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-04-22_dandins-purvapithika-of-dasha-kumara-charitra/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
The 3rd stride of viShNu as well as his snake is the enduring Hindus symbol of the axis that precesses with the passage of kAla or time. Right from the R^igveda this axial role of viShNu is at the fore in all conceptions of him. We have alluded to this a few times before, see: snake of viShNu, the Finnish epic, and more obliquely in fall of praHlAda. The element of the axis and its precession is very much a part of the “core mythology” of viShNu: 1) the horn of matsya- the new axis being provided for the world after its shift due to precession.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The peculiar mythology behind the mAyAvAmana mantras</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-04-16_the-peculiar-mythology-behind-the-mayavamana-mantras/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Apr 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-04-16_the-peculiar-mythology-behind-the-mayavamana-mantras/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
The hAdi mata votaries from the North also preserved a range of kramas, now largely reduced to auxilliary rites associated as AvarNa invocations of their primary rite of tripurasundarI. This follows the basic pattern seen in the shrIvidyArNava’s procedures. Many of these are strikingly interesting such as the invocation of the terrific graveyard-ranging bahurUpa bhairava and his wife, a special mantra of the supreme Anandabhairava, the 8-handed amR^itasUrya invocation and the formulae derived from the kaTha yajurveda.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The left-handed aShTha-mukha gaNDabheruNDa nR^ikeshari mantra</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-03-11_the-left-handed-ashtha-mukha-gandabherunda-nrikeshari-mantra/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Mar 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-03-11_the-left-handed-ashtha-mukha-gandabherunda-nrikeshari-mantra/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
It is said that there are two emanations of the mantra of the most terrible aShTha-mukha gaNDabheruNDa nR^isimha (AMGN)- a dakShiNa and vAma form. The right-handed form is said to lie in the text termed the bhIma-tantra which is a upa-tantra of the ananta-vijaya saMhitA of the viShNu-yAmala tradition. The left-handed form is said to like in the text termed vAmA-tantra which is also an upa-tantra of the ananta-vijaya saMhitA.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The chakras of viShNu</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-02-14_the-chakras-of-vishnu/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Feb 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-02-14_the-chakras-of-vishnu/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
From viShNu emanate several chakra missiles, all of which may follow the deadly sudarshana and discs when used in battle against the dAnavas and rAkShasas. They represent the sum of the deadly destructive fury of viShNu. Likewise, the sampUrNa chakra prayoga rite invokes these weapons to power the countering or attacking mantra missiles.
The following are the chakras:
mahArAtridhara chakra: This powered by mahAmAyA and is dark hued and terrifying with a single spoke.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ekAnamshA: a deity of tantric vaiShNavism</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-02-04_ekanamsha-a-deity-of-tantric-vaishnavism/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Feb 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-02-04_ekanamsha-a-deity-of-tantric-vaishnavism/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
The core pantheon of the pA~ncharAtra texts is the chaturvyuha or the serial emanations of nArAyaNa. The primary manifestation of nArAyaNa is vAsudeva, from whom emerge saMkarShaNa and pradyumna. From pradyumna emerges aniruddha. This pantheon appears to be a unique feature of the yadu tribes that subsequently seems to have spawned the classical pA~ncharAtra. However, the early texts suggest that there was another parallel system that appears to have largely passed out of subsequent vaiShNavism.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>viShNu mahApanjara stotraM</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-11-25_vishnu-mahapanjara-stotram/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Nov 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-11-25_vishnu-mahapanjara-stotram/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
namo-namaste govindaM chakraM gR^ihya sudarshanaM |
prAchyAM rakShasva mAM viShNo tvAm-ahaM sharaNaM gataH ||
Salutations to govinda, who holds the sudarshaNa discus;
I seek refuge in you, O viShNu protect me from the east.
gadAM kaumodakIM gR^ihNa padmanAbha namo.astu te |
yAmyAM rakShasva mAM viShNo tvAm-ahaM sharaNaM gataH ||
Salutations to padmanAbha, holding the kaumodaki mace;
I seek refuge in you, O viShNu protect me from the direction of yama (south).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The vaiShNava mahAmantra</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-10-16_the-vaishnava-mahamantra/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Oct 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-10-16_the-vaishnava-mahamantra/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
oM oM oM hrIM hrIM hrIM shrIM shrIM shrIM 0M aM aM aM hauM hauM hauM haMsaH haMsaH haMsaH oM hrIM shrIM namo viShNave //
The mantra rahasyas:
That great mantra encompasses a series of 3 praNavas. The 3 praNavas are the AdhAra that is known as the brahman. This is followed by the 3 tArikAs and the 3 anutArikAs which are two wives of viShNu. They are the supremre states with all things existing in these two shaktis of viShNu.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The shrIdhara krama</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-10-15_the-shridhara_krama/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Oct 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-10-15_the-shridhara_krama/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
The fragment of the totala tantra preserved by tradition has an important rite the shrIdhara karma to viShNu that is thus performed (we provide a edited version from a reasonably well made transcription):
-The upAsaka shall have a bath, then perform saMdhyA and then enter the sacrificial room.
-He shall then wash his hands and feet and perform Achamana. He shall place his right palm on the left palm in the saMkalpa posture and utter the mUla mantra:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The dark hero of the yadus</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-08-27_the-dark-hero-of-the-yadus/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Aug 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-08-27_the-dark-hero-of-the-yadus/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
The birth anniversary of the dark hero of the yadus dawned. We decided to
recall his awful deeds in course of his momentous life that overlapped with the tumult taking place in the bhArata realms.
The yadu was born to vasudeva and devakI, who were imprisoned by kaMsa, devakI’s brother.The tyrant kaMsa had been told that devakI’s 8th son will kill him one day. devakI’s eighth son was born on a rohiNI aShtTami, and was spirited away by vasudeva to his cowherd friend nanda’s abode.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>sudarshaNa rahasya</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-07-18_sudarshana-rahasya/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Jul 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-07-18_sudarshana-rahasya/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
Having bowed to the one sleeping atop the coils of the snake of time we salute the greatest of his weapons.
oM urugAyAya hum phaT //
That supreme emanation of the shakti of nArAyaNa manifested with a predominance of her tejas, is as bright as many millions of suns, moons and fires in profusion. It pervades the tryambaka vidya of the 7th maNDala of the R^igveda. It is described as the supreme udyama, foremost prANa and all weapons and shaktis of the hordes of viShNu and vishvaksena arise from it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The praise of varAha mUrtI</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-03-12_the-praise-of-varaha-murti/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Mar 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-03-12_the-praise-of-varaha-murti/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
daMShTrAyAM vasudhA sashaila-nagarAraNyApagA huMkR^itau vAgIshI shasite.anilo ravi vidhU bAhvoshcha dakShAnyayoH /
The earth with its mountains, cities, forests and waterbodies are in his tusks, his grunts are sarasvatI (vAgIshI). The air is his breath and the sun and moon are his right and left hands.
kukShau syurvasavo dishaH shrutipathe dasrau dR^ishoH pAdayoH padmottho hR^idaye hariH pR^ithagamI pujyA mukhe sha~NkaraH //
His belly is [made of] the vasus, in his ear are the directions, the ashvins are his eyes, in his feet is the lotus born [brahma], in his heart is viShNu and in his mouth is shiva.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>vibhavas of viShNu</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-03-10_vibhavas-of-vishnu/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Mar 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-03-10_vibhavas-of-vishnu/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
The vibhavas:
padmanAbha
dhruva
ananta
shaktIsha
madhusudhana
vidyAdhideva
kapila
vishvarUpa
haMsa
krodAtman
vaDavaktra
dharma
vAgIshvara
ekArNavashaya
kUrma
varAha
nR^isimha
amR^itAharaNA
shripati
kAntAtman
rAhujit
kAlanemighna
pArijAtahara
lokanAtha
dattAtreya
nygrodashAyin
ekashR^i~Ngatanu
vAmana
trivikrama
nara
nArAyaNa
hari
kR^iShNa
rAmo bhArgava
rAmachandra
vyAsa
kalkI
pAtAlashAyin</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>kShemendra on kalki</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-03-03_kshemendra-on-kalki/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Mar 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-03-03_kshemendra-on-kalki/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
The great Kashmirian author in his text the dashAvatAracharitra which was written in 1066 AD describes the conditions that would prevail on the earth just before the coming of kalki.
“The Turushkas, Pathans, Daradas and dwellers of Shakastan will cause the earth to decay as do the leper his open oozing sores. Every direction overrun by the dreadful mlechChas, the earth will resound with the clash of swords drawn in combat and her soil will be soaked with blood.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Buddhist kalki</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-03-01_the-buddhist-kalki/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-03-01_the-buddhist-kalki/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
The bauddhas have internalized the last incarnation of viShNu, the all-destroying kalki or pramati who is said to annihilate the mlecchas and dasyus and restore the world to the Aryas. The kAlachakra tantra of the unclean upachInAchAra stream gives a highly remarkable account of the end of the yuga. It’s parallels to the mainstream Hindu version are unmistakable and appears to have been clearly derived from it [It is even possible that there was a now lost Hindu version which might have been a closer precursor of the version in the kAlachakra tantra].</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The snake of viShNu</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2004-12-06_the-snake-of-vishnu/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Dec 2004 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2004-12-06_the-snake-of-vishnu/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
Upon the great snake shesha sleeps the great god viShNu, even as the the kalpa wears out. He stirs only when the waters rise and threaten to sink the world plane. This shesha is time and hence he is called ananta. Thus, when viShNu sleeps on the coils of the great world snake he is experiencing the cyclic passage of time.
Once the great god vAyu and the world snake ananta had a contest of strength.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Antiquity as major deity</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/antiquity_as_major_deity/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/antiquity_as_major_deity/</guid>
      <description>Clearly there was the classic viShNu-focal system of vedic and earlier IE provenance; then there was the more local evolution in the Indo-Iranian borderlands of the vAsudeva-sAttvata tradition. The earlier harivaMsha was definitely focused on a version of the sAttvata tradition. But there was a parallel strand of vaiShNava tradition predominant among the vaikhAnasa-s &amp;amp; and an early strand of pA~ncharAtra-s that was closer to vaidika focality on viShNu.
The viShNu purANa tries bring the 2 together by giving devakIputra the focus of the &amp;ldquo;earthly&amp;rdquo; expression of the sAttvata religion a central place in the narrative.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>hayagrIva bhairava</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/hayagrIva-bhairava/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/hayagrIva-bhairava/</guid>
      <description>Source: TW
A most remarkable Kashmirian 10 headed viShNu vishvarUpa from late kArkota age. The first triad of heads are the usual nR^isiMha-viShNu-varAha triad; the next triad is bhairava-maheshvara-umA; then the 3 vyUha deities; the worn-out one on the top is likely hayagrIva.
One can find some parallels to vishvarUpa vibhava of viShNu from some pA~ncharAtrika texts. The above (haribhaktivilAsa quote) indeed seems to be a citation of hayashIrsha. It might also be seen as an expression of the general prescription given in the jayAkhya.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>kAlachakraH</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/kAlachakraH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/kAlachakraH/</guid>
      <description>The kAlachakra that is also known as the god vAsudeva.
āvartamānam ajaram vivartanam
șan-nemikam dvādaśāram suparva |
yasyedam āsye pariyāti viśvam
tat kālacakram nihitam guhāyām ||
Eternally turning forth and turning back,
with a six-sectored felly, twelve spokes, and a good linchpin into whose mouth all existence rushes forth, that wheel of time is stationed in the [secret] cave of existence.
It goes back to the RV where viShNu is seen as setting the wheel of time of time in motion.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Modena deity</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/modena-deity/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/modena-deity/</guid>
      <description>Source: TW
A peculiar deity found in an apparently mithrAistic context at Modena. The deity has been interpreted as:
a Roman rendering of the para-Zoroastrian deity zurvan akArana. Orphic protogonic deity Phanes/ Protogonos; Chronos. Zeus who swallowed the latter. The chronic association of the deity &amp;ndash; thus identifying him with zurvan is seen in the form of the zodiac around him &amp;amp; the snake winding around him which represents the periodicity of time &amp;ndash; an element associated the Indo-Aryan chronic deity viShNu.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>vishvaxena</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/vishvaxena/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/vishvaxena/</guid>
      <description>It seems, given his name and function, viShvaksena evolved as a vaiShNava reflex of skanda. This is supported by the early kaumAra tradition where he is surrounded by the 4 vinAyaka-s like those companions of viShvaksena. Moreover, skanda played a key role in the creation of vinAyaka(-s) in one of the old traditions preserved in the voluminous skandapurANa. Notably, in a curious twist the shaiva vatulottara names skanda as viShvaksena and vishAkha as jayatsena once in the account of the AvaraNa of rudragaNa-s.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>पुष्टिः सरस्वती</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/puShTi-sarasvatI/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/viShNuH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/puShTi-sarasvatI/</guid>
      <description>Source: TW
Erotic eulogy of viShNu attributed to bhava-deva lost polymath pA~ncharAtrika tAntrika of the east who was minister
ॐ नमो भगवते वासुदेवाय ॥
गाढोपगूढ-कमला-कुच-कुंभ-पत्र-
मुद्राङ्कितेन वपुषा परिरिप्समानः ।
मा लुप्यताम् अभिनवा वन-मालिकेति
वाग्-देवतोपहसितो ऽस्तु हरिः श्रिये वः ॥
With his body marked by the impressions of the unguent on the firm pot-like breasts of Kamalā (Laksmī) whom he had just hugged, he wished to embrace [the speech-deity]. May that Hari [then] taunted by the speech-deity thus, &amp;ldquo;Do not mess up your new forest-flower garland&amp;rdquo;, bring you wealth.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
