<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/revantaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 24 Jun 2007 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/revantaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>A local pantheon of mallaNNa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/revantaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2007-06-24_a-local-pantheon-of-mallanna/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Jun 2007 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/revantaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2007-06-24_a-local-pantheon-of-mallanna/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2007/06/24/a-local-pantheon-of-mallanna/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A train of thought culminated in me remembering the peculiar case of the equestrian deity mallaNNa found in Ailoni. There is a smaller temple of mallaNNa in that village. Here he is depicted with his two wives with four arms hold a sword, trident, skull bowl and Damaru. His first wife is mADaladevI who is supposed to be umA incarnated amongst the lingAyata-s or gone kApu-s. She is depicted with a crown and two hands with a sword and skull bowl. She is the Andhra ortholog of mhALsA. His second wife is ketammA who is believed to be ga~NgA incarnated as a golla, and is the ortholog of bAnU. She is similarly armed as mADaladevI but has an elaborate hair-do instead of a crown. Also shown are 3 heads of Meccan demons or mlechCha-turuShka-s or yavana-kula daitya-s who where beheaded by mallaNNa.&#xA;He has a peculiar entourage of deities around him. He has a herd of sheep that he obtained from his wife ketammA. He has an army of 7 (or 7 times 100) dogs (vedic: shvabhya shvapatibhyashcha vo namaH; also compare with 7 fold troops of maruts). His brother is bayaNNa (a fierce bhairava; bhairoba in the mahArATTa country). There is a goddess poshammA who may have many arms and is like shAkambharI. There is then agni and vAyu. Then there is vAsukI or nAga-sarpaM. mallaNA is supposed to make 13 cups of sheep milk for the 7 dogs, bayaNNa, poshammA, vAsukI, agni, vAyu and himself. In the temple following this a ritual is performed where the cups of leaf are made and milk offered the deities. Here, as in some forms of the khaNDobA myth from mahArAShTra, mallaNNa is said to have incarnated to slay Meccan demons or green-robed demons who had seized the land in the age of kali and were tormenting the Hindus. maNi and malla may be called suratrANa-s who ruled from Bidar and some other place.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The deva revanta: Mythology, iconography, history and ritualism</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/revantaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-08-31_the-deva-revanta-mythology-iconography-history-and-ritualism/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Aug 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/revantaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-08-31_the-deva-revanta-mythology-iconography-history-and-ritualism/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2006/08/31/the-deva-revanta-mythology-iconography-history-and-ritualism/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://photos1.blogger.com/blogger/2010/410/1600/revanta.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;figure class=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &lt;a href=&#34;https://i0.wp.com/photos1.blogger.com/blogger/2010/410/320/revanta.jpg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;img src=&#34;https://i0.wp.com/photos1.blogger.com/blogger/2010/410/320/revanta.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &#xA;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;Like kArttikeya, revanta, a once popular deity, has faded from the Hindu mind, with decline of Indic civilization. However, in the south his successor ectype shAstR^i is still worshiped in the folk religion. We have long wanted collate a file on this deva and revive his rites as we are amongst the few still adhering to his worship. We have been made aware of some other works on him but we have not read those.   Mythology   The purANas narrate the core myth of the origin of the god revanta thus:   vivasvAn was given sanj~nA as his wife by tvasTA vishvakarman. vivasvan begot the twins yama and yamI, and manu vaivasvata through her. However, sanj~nA was unable to endure the excessive fiery lustre of vivasvAn and decided to leave him and go to the regions of the uttara kuru. She created a replica of herself in the form ChAyA and placed her with vivasvAn before retiring in the form of a mare. vivasvAn took ChAyA too be sanj~nA and begot on ChAyA, the inauspicious shanaishchara, the daughter tapatI and manu sAvarNI. One day ChAyA got into a conflict with the death-like yama vaivasvata as she mis-treated her foster son. Thus vivasvAn realized that ChAyA was not sanj~nA and through his dUradR^iShTi located her in the uttara kuru regions as a mare. So he assumed the form of a stallion and reached there. They copulated first via their nostrils, spawning the ashvins and then internally spawning revanta. He was born with a sword and bow, riding a horse and bearing a quiver full of arrows. vivasvAn said to revanta that he shall be the lord of the guhyaka tribe of yakShas and yakShiNI-s. He mentioned that at the time of forest fires and volcanic eruptions, and when dasyus and mlechChas devastate the land the mortal need to invoke revanta to obtain relief.&#xA;Versions of this tale are narrated in the viShNu (VP 3.2) and mArkaNDeya (MkP 78) purANa-s. The matsya (MP 11.2) and agni (AP 272.3; 273 in MBLD edition) purANa-s narrates a variant in which vivasvAn has a separate wife rAj~nI through whom he fathers revanta. The devi bhAgavataM mentions revanta as riding on uchChaishravas to visit viShNu, when lakShmI gets fascinated by the horse and fails to pay attention to viShNu. As a result he cursed lakShmI to became a mare and generates the haihaya dynasty in this account (DB 6.17-18).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
