<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;08 KĀLĪ on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/08_kAlI/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;08 KĀLĪ on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/08_kAlI/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 EARLY HISTORY</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/08_kAlI/01_EARLY_HISTORY/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/08_kAlI/01_EARLY_HISTORY/</guid>
      <description>The earliest references to Kālī in the Hindu tradition date to the early medieval period (around A.D. 600) and usually locate Kālī either on the battlefield or in situations on the periphery of Hindu society. In the Agni- and Garuḍa-purāṇas she is mentioned in invocations that aim at success in war and against one’s enemies. She is described as having an awful appearance: she is gaunt, has fangs, laughs loudly, dances madly, wears a garland of corpses, sits on the back of a ghost, and lives in the cremation ground.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>02 THE LATER HISTORY AND THE SIGNIFICANCE OF KĀLĪ</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/08_kAlI/02_THE_LATER_HISTORY_AND_THE_SIGNIFICANCE_OF_kAlI/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/08_kAlI/02_THE_LATER_HISTORY_AND_THE_SIGNIFICANCE_OF_kAlI/</guid>
      <description>Given Kālī’s intimidating appearance and ghastly habits, it might seem that she would never occupy a central position in Hindu piety, yet she does. She is of central importance in Tantrism, particularly left-handed Tantrism, and in Bengali Śākta devotionalism. An underlying assumption in Tantric ideology is that reality is the result and expression of the symbiotic interaction of male and female, Śiva and śakti, the quiescent and the dynamic, and other polar opposites that in interaction produce a creative tension.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
