<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;12 GODDESSES AND SACRED GEOGRAPHY on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/12_GODDESSES_AND_SACRED_GEOGRAPHY/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;12 GODDESSES AND SACRED GEOGRAPHY on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/12_GODDESSES_AND_SACRED_GEOGRAPHY/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 EARTH AS A GODDESS/INDIA AS A GODDESS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/12_GODDESSES_AND_SACRED_GEOGRAPHY/01_EARTH_AS_A_GODDESS__INDIA_AS_A_GODDESS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/12_GODDESSES_AND_SACRED_GEOGRAPHY/01_EARTH_AS_A_GODDESS__INDIA_AS_A_GODDESS/</guid>
      <description>An important aspect of the reverence for the divine feminine in the Hindu tradition is an awe for the sacrality of the land itself and for the Indian subcontinent as a whole. The most ancient expression of this in the Hindu tradition is found in the Ṛg-veda and its several hymns that praise the goddess Pṛthivī. It is clear that the hymns to Pṛthivī are grounded in reverence for the awesome stability of the earth itself and the apparently inexhaustible fecundity possessed by the earth.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>02 THE ŚĀKTA PĪṬHAS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/12_GODDESSES_AND_SACRED_GEOGRAPHY/02_THE_shAkta_pIThas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/12_GODDESSES_AND_SACRED_GEOGRAPHY/02_THE_shAkta_pIThas/</guid>
      <description>The myth and cult of the Śākta pīṭhas is another vivid expression of the Hindu intuition that the Indian subcontinent itself is a goddess. India is covered with sacred places associated with prominent geographical features of the country. Mountains, hills, rivers, caves, and other sites having some geographical or natural peculiarity are often affirmed to possess sacred power or to be places where one may make contact with the divine. These sites are usually called tīrthas, a term that means a place where one fords a river.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>03 THE GANGES AND THE SACRALITY OF RIVERS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/12_GODDESSES_AND_SACRED_GEOGRAPHY/03_THE_GANGES_AND_THE_SACRALITY_OF_RIVERS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/12_GODDESSES_AND_SACRED_GEOGRAPHY/03_THE_GANGES_AND_THE_SACRALITY_OF_RIVERS/</guid>
      <description>Geographical sacrality in the Hindu tradition is also dramatically expressed in the reverence shown to almost every river of the Indian subcontinent. This reverence extends all the way back to the Ṛg-veda, where the idea is expressed that earthly rivers have their origin in heaven. In the Ṛg-veda the Sarasvatī River is praised as a mighty goddess who blesses her devotees with health, long life, and poetic inspiration.37 The earthly Sarasvatī River is said to be only a partial manifestation of the goddess Sarasvatī, for she is said to exist in heaven as well as on earth.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
