<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;01 GODDESSES IN VEDIC LITERATURE on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/01_GODDESSES_IN_VEDIC_LITERATURE/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;01 GODDESSES IN VEDIC LITERATURE on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/01_GODDESSES_IN_VEDIC_LITERATURE/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 UṢAS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/01_GODDESSES_IN_VEDIC_LITERATURE/01_uShas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/01_GODDESSES_IN_VEDIC_LITERATURE/01_uShas/</guid>
      <description>In the Ṛg-veda the goddess Uṣas is consistently associated with and often identified with the dawn. She reveals herself in the daily coming of light to the world. A young maiden, drawn in a hundred chariots (1.48), she brings forth light and is followed by the sun (Surya), who urges her onward (3.61). She is praised for driving away, or is petitioned to drive away, the oppressive darkness (7.78; 6.64; 10.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>02 PRTHIVĪ</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/01_GODDESSES_IN_VEDIC_LITERATURE/02_prthivI/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/01_GODDESSES_IN_VEDIC_LITERATURE/02_prthivI/</guid>
      <description>The goddess Pṛthivī is nearly always associated with the earth, the terrestrial sphere where human beings live. In the Ṛg-veda, furthermore, she is almost always coupled with Dyaus, the male deity associated with the sky. So interdependent are these two deities in the Ṛg-veda that Pṛthivī is rarely addressed alone but almost always as part of the dual compound dyāvāpṛthivī, sky-earth. Together they are said to kiss the center of the world (1.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>03 ADITI</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/01_GODDESSES_IN_VEDIC_LITERATURE/03_ADITI/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/01_GODDESSES_IN_VEDIC_LITERATURE/03_ADITI/</guid>
      <description>Although the goddess Aditi is mentioned nearly eighty times in the Ṛg-veda, it is difficult to gain a clear picture of her nature. She is usually mentioned along with other gods or goddesses, there is no one hymn addressed exclusively to her, and unlike many other Vedic deities she is not obviously associated with some natural phenomenon. Compared to Uṣas and Pṛthivī, her character seems ill defined. She is virtually featureless physically.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>04 SARASVATĪ</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/01_GODDESSES_IN_VEDIC_LITERATURE/04_sarasvatI/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/01_GODDESSES_IN_VEDIC_LITERATURE/04_sarasvatI/</guid>
      <description>The close association between natural phenomena and such Vedic goddesses as Uṣas and Pṛthivī is also seen in the goddess Sarasvatī, who is associated with a particular river. Although scholars have debated precisely which river she was identified with in Vedic times (the Sarasvatī River of that period has since disappeared), in the Ṛg-veda her most important characteristics are those of a particular mighty river. Indeed, at times it is not clear whether a goddess or a river is being praised; many references hail the Sarasvatī River as a mighty goddess.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>05 VĀC</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/01_GODDESSES_IN_VEDIC_LITERATURE/05_vAch/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/01_GODDESSES_IN_VEDIC_LITERATURE/05_vAch/</guid>
      <description>Although the significance of sound and speech as the primordial stuff of creation is primarily a post-Ṛg-vedic concept, it is apparent even in the Ṛg-veda that sound, and especially ritual speech, is powerful, creative, and a mainstay of cosmic-ritual order. The goddess Vāc, whose name means “speech,” reveals herself through speech and is typically characterized by the various attributes and uses of speech. She is speech, and the mysteries and miracles of speech express her peculiar, numinous nature.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>06 NIRṚTI</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/01_GODDESSES_IN_VEDIC_LITERATURE/06_nirRti/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/01_GODDESSES_IN_VEDIC_LITERATURE/06_nirRti/</guid>
      <description>The Vedic goddesses we have looked at so far are generally benign, protective deities to whom the hymnist typically appeals for wealth, strength, and general well-being. The goddess Nirṛti has no such benign qualities. She is not mentioned very often in the Ṛg-veda, but when she is, the concern of the hymn is to seek protection from her or to ask that she be driven away. The scattered references to her seem to equate her with death, ill luck, and destruction.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>07 RĀTRĪ</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/01_GODDESSES_IN_VEDIC_LITERATURE/07_rAtrI/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/01_GODDESSES_IN_VEDIC_LITERATURE/07_rAtrI/</guid>
      <description>The goddess Rātrī is almost always associated with the night. Indeed, she is the night, and as such she is the presence or power that is petitioned by people for comfort and security in the dark hours before the triumphant return of the dawn. Her physical appearance is rarely mentioned, although she is sometimes described as a beautiful maiden along with her sister, Uṣas, the dawn. She is called glorious and immortal and is praised for providing light in the darkness, bedecked as she is with countless stars.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>08 MINOR VEDIC GODDESSES</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/01_GODDESSES_IN_VEDIC_LITERATURE/08_MINOR_VEDIC_GODDESSES/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/01_GODDESSES_IN_VEDIC_LITERATURE/08_MINOR_VEDIC_GODDESSES/</guid>
      <description>Several goddesses known to the Ṛg-veda are mentioned so infrequently that it is difficult to perceive what their distinctive natures might have been. Some of these minor goddesses seem to be synonymous with abundance. Puraṁdhi, Pārendi, Rākā, and Dhiṣaṇā, none of whom is mentioned more than about a dozen times in the Ṛg-veda, are all associated with bounty and riches. As is the case with most Vedic goddesses, their natures appear to be benign and their presences revealed through material well-being.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>09 CONCLUSION</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/01_GODDESSES_IN_VEDIC_LITERATURE/09_CONCLUSION/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/01_GODDESSES_IN_VEDIC_LITERATURE/09_CONCLUSION/</guid>
      <description>Several conclusions concerning goddesses in Vedic literature are clear. First, none of them rivals the great male gods in these texts. Indeed, Uṣas, the most popular goddess (in terms of the number of times she is mentioned and the number of hymns addressed specifically to her), is only a deity of the third rank. In short, male deities dominate the Vedic vision of the divine.
Second, there is evidence that some of the Vedic goddesses survive in the later Hindu tradition.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
