<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 13 Feb 2008 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Retrospections on the curtain-raiser to the long past Great War 1</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2008-02-13_retrospections-on-the-curtain-raiser-to-the-long-p/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Feb 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2008-02-13_retrospections-on-the-curtain-raiser-to-the-long-p/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
We began to enter the minds of our ancestors the mantra dR^iShTa-s of yore for the first time. The deva-s started unveiling themselves: the upward blaze of agni in the three stations, the power of vAyu, the all-encompassing indra, the natural conservations of mitra, the natural laws whose violations are punished by varuNa, the exhilaration of knowing the natural law in aryaman, the swift transmission of the maruts, the dissolution of natural bonds through their father, the archer rudra, the light of savitA, the warmth of puShA, distribution of energies through bhaga, the flow of time in viShNu, the Milky way and the earthly flows of sarasvatI, the chemistry of the ashvins, the clear reflection by bR^ihaspati, the revolutions and the cycles of the observable cosmos in soma and tvaShTa with the R^ibhus, the world axis and its precessions in Aja-ekapAd and ahir-budhnya, the origins in aditi and then the mysterious prajApati called ka, and national identity in the 3 goddess ilA, sarasvatI and bhAratI 2) Then the exploits of the great pinAkin-mahAdeva came to us.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>devatA chitra saMgraha</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-12-11_devata-chitra-samgraha/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Dec 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-12-11_devata-chitra-samgraha/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
The eldest son of the great king of Nepal, pR^ithivi nArAyaNa shahA (who defeated the British and founded the Nepal Kingdom until its recent destruction by Marxists), pratApa siMha, compiled a voluminous work on the mantra shAstra during his brief life. As a companion to this a collection of pictures for the dhyAna-s on various deities was prepared by the artists in Nepal. A copy of this collection with R1’s father is of considerable interest in terms of tradition Hindu dhyAna art of which not many old samples survive.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lankan pantheon</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/lankan-pantheon/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/lankan-pantheon/</guid>
      <description>The once vigorous lankan flavor of the Hindu tradition had several rituals with deshIya liturgies which were marginalized or exterminated relatively recently by the resurgent sthaviravAdin-s of the shAkyamata.
Some examples included the extensive sekra-geDi-shAntiya, an aindra ritual. One major center of his ritual was Padeniya in lankA where a temple housed his image. Now believed to have been absorbed into the saugata vihAra where the idol is still apparently there.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Odd survivals</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/odd-survivals/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/odd-survivals/</guid>
      <description> rAkA - Rakkayi Amman temple in Alagar Malai aindra praxis of the rathva tribes in lATAnarta +++(←ind in their uttarAyaNa festival)+++ varuNa worship in what is now TSP; vAyu again in lATa &amp;amp; that probably extended to the realm of the madhva-s. </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Polytheism</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/polytheism/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/polytheism/</guid>
      <description>Source: TW
A high IQ u1 intellectual told me that he was inspired by the thought that a good mathematics is one whose axiomatic foundation yields a great richness &amp;amp; diversity of results. That&amp;rsquo;s why he said he started taking H&amp;rsquo;ism &amp;amp; studying it deeply.
He said you guys were able to come with a rich diversity of pantheons not once, which would be the IE foundation, but multiple times in the purANa-s &amp;amp;tantra-s.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
