<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;02 ŚRĪ-LAKṢMĪ on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/02_shrI-laxmI/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;02 ŚRĪ-LAKṢMĪ on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/02_shrI-laxmI/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 THE EARLY HISTORY OF ŚRĪ-LAKṢMĪ</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/02_shrI-laxmI/01_THE_EARLY_HISTORY_OF_shrI-laxmI/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/02_shrI-laxmI/01_THE_EARLY_HISTORY_OF_shrI-laxmI/</guid>
      <description>The goddess Śrī-Lakṣmī does not appear in the earliest Vedic literature.1 The term śrī, however, does occur quite often, and it is clear that the meanings of the term are related to the nature of the later goddess Śrī-Lakṣmī. As used in the Vedic hymns the term śrī suggests capability, power, and advantageous skills. As an external quality śrī suggests beauty, luster, glory, and high rank. The term is especially used in later Vedic literature to refer to the ruling power, dominion, and majesty of kings.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>02 ŚRĪ-LAKṢMĪ IN LATER HINDUISM</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/02_shrI-laxmI/02_shrI-laxmI_IN_LATER_HINDUISM/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/02_shrI-laxmI/02_shrI-laxmI_IN_LATER_HINDUISM/</guid>
      <description>In the course of her history Śrī-Lakṣmī has been associated with male deities, each of whom is significant in suggesting characteristics of the goddess. Some texts associate her with the god Soma. Srī-Lakṣmī, along with several other deities, attends Soma after he performs a great royal sacrifice.17 The association of Lakṣmī with Soma is noteworthy for two reasons. First, in attending him after he has assumed the position of royal authority, she demonstrates one of her main characteristics, that of bestowing royal authority or being present where royal authority exists.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>03 ŚRĪ-LAKṢMĪ IN THE PĀÑCARĀTRA AND ŚRĪ VAIṢṆAVA SCHOOLS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/02_shrI-laxmI/03_shrI-laxmI_IN_THE_pAncharAtra_AND_shrI_vaiShNav/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/02_shrI-laxmI/03_shrI-laxmI_IN_THE_pAncharAtra_AND_shrI_vaiShNav/</guid>
      <description>Śrī-Lakṣmī’s association with Viṣṇu eventually leads to her playing important roles in the mythological and philosophic visions of the Pāñcarātra and Śrī Vaiṣṇava schools of thought and devotion. In the Pāñcarātra school Lakṣmī comes to play the central role in the creation and evolution of the universe as the śakti of Viṣṇu. In the Pāñcarātra creation scenario Viṣṇu remains almost entirely inactive, relegating the creative process to Lakṣmī. After awakening Lakṣmī at the end of the night of dissolution, Viṣṇu’s role in the creation of the universe is restricted to that of an inactive architect whose plan is put into effect by a builder.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>04 THE WORSHIP OF ŚRĪ-LAKṢMĪ</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/02_shrI-laxmI/04_THE_WORSHIP_OF_shrI-laxmI/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/02_shrI-laxmI/04_THE_WORSHIP_OF_shrI-laxmI/</guid>
      <description>Śrī-Lakṣmī is today one of the most popular and widely venerated deities of the Hindu pantheon. Her auspicious nature and her reputation for granting fertility, luck, wealth, and well-being seem to attract devotees in every Indian village. “All of India’s back country is the dominion of Lakṣmī, the goddess of the lotus. . . . She accompanies every mile traveled through central India, every visit to a temple. . . .</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
