<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;10 Possession in Tantra on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/10_Possession_in_Tantra/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;10 Possession in Tantra on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/10_Possession_in_Tantra/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 Samāveśa as Tantric Realization</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/10_Possession_in_Tantra/01_SamAvesha_as_Tantric_Realization/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/10_Possession_in_Tantra/01_SamAvesha_as_Tantric_Realization/</guid>
      <description>Caveat Tantra is a category increasingly subject to debate. It is now regarded by many of the most informed scholars as a category with vague characterization and definition, an amorphous medley of practices, rites, and doctrines that became tantric by attrition; they simply do not fit elsewhere.1 This, combined with a Western fascination for things tantric (especially a mistaken identification of Tantra with sex), enables most nonspecialists to dodge the problem of Tantra.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>02 Discipline and Enlightenment</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/10_Possession_in_Tantra/02_Discipline_and_Enlightenment/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/10_Possession_in_Tantra/02_Discipline_and_Enlightenment/</guid>
      <description>Along with the Vedas and the two Sanskrit epics, the Tantras provide the richest sources for the phenomenology of religious possession in premodern India, and, along with the Mahābhārata (MBh) the richest sources for its analysis. Indeed, it is evident that the Tantras, particularly those of the Śaiva and Sākta sects of Kashmir and northeastern India that developed around the turn of the first millennium C.E., confront the issue of possession and problematize it more concretely than anywhere else in Sanskrit literature.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>03 Divinizing the Body</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/10_Possession_in_Tantra/03_Divinizing_the_Body/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/10_Possession_in_Tantra/03_Divinizing_the_Body/</guid>
      <description>Michel Foucault noted that the body is the primary site of ritualization, where “the most minute and local social practices are linked up with the large-scale organization of power.”30 This is perhaps nowhere truer than in a ritual system in which the body is regarded as a receptive replicator of the cosmos. This is the case in much of Indian ritual, in which the macrocosm is classically held to naturalize, animate, and regulate, through ritual performance, the microcosmic power structures that engender and are defined by local social arrangements and practices.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>04 Nyāsa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/10_Possession_in_Tantra/04_nyAsa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/10_Possession_in_Tantra/04_nyAsa/</guid>
      <description>Two phenomena that share conceptual territory with āveśa are nyāsa and (prāṇa-) pratiṣṭhā. There is an important distinction between them: The latter two are intentional, textualized, and enjoined bodily constructions, transformations of intellectual and social practices (arguably these are the same thing) into sacred physical terrain. Nyasa (literally “setting upon, placing down, imposition”)38 is a common, and often standard, part of brahmanical worship that finds its greatest advocacy in the Tantras and Purāṇas.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>05 Pratiṣṭhā</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/10_Possession_in_Tantra/05_PratiShThA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/10_Possession_in_Tantra/05_PratiShThA/</guid>
      <description>Related to nyāsa are pratiṣṭhā (establishment of a deity in a material object), attested as early as the vedic Brāhmaṇa literature and, more specifically and recently, praṇa-pratiṣṭhā (installation of vital breath [prāṇa] into an image of a deity).66 The relatively recent Tantrarāja Tantra (2.39–40) notes the possible loci of pratiṣṭhā in the case of the goddess: She can be established in a cakra (viz. a yantra), a disciple, or a fashioned image of herself.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>06 Possession in Buddhist Tantras</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/10_Possession_in_Tantra/06_Possession_in_Buddhist_Tantras/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/10_Possession_in_Tantra/06_Possession_in_Buddhist_Tantras/</guid>
      <description>Tantric or Vajrayāna Buddhism spread from North India, Kashmir, and Nepal into Tibet between 500 and 1000 C.E., as many scholars have shown. It was then enhanced in Tibet by the indigenous Bön and other local cults and cosmologies and by the spectacular environment that is Tibet, all of which have conferred on it a unique position among the various versions of Asian Buddhism. Among the unique features of Vajrayāna Buddhism is the importance of initiations, a legacy of the Śaiva traditions of Kashmir and northern India.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>07 Tantric Possession and Images of a Multiple Self</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/10_Possession_in_Tantra/07_Tantric_Possession_and_Images_of_a_Multiple_Self/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/10_Possession_in_Tantra/07_Tantric_Possession_and_Images_of_a_Multiple_Self/</guid>
      <description>What is revealed here is a continuum of practice from brahmanical to Buddhist, always with the underlying themes of physical divinization and multiplicity within an apparent singularity of personality. First, we briefly explicated the important term samāveśa, which occurs frequently in the Śaiva Tantras to indicate both the practice of immersion into a deity and the state of liberation that results from this practice. The unvarying requirement for these, the contingency that confers eligibility (adhikāra) for samāveśa, is tantric initiation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>08 NOTES</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/10_Possession_in_Tantra/08_NOTES/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/4_Worldly_and_Otherworldly_Ruptures/10_Possession_in_Tantra/08_NOTES/</guid>
      <description>Cited in Kaw 1967:233, 1975:175; Sanderson 1986:176; Torella 1994:203. Śiva’s projection into the individual is fourfold: as a sensationless void (sūnyam), as internal sensation (āntaraḥ sparśaḥ), as the intellect (buddhiḥ), and as the body (śarīra) (cf. Sanderson 1986.).
asmad rūpasamāviṣṭaḥ svātmanātmanivāraṇe | śivaḥ karotu nijayā namaḥ śāktyā tatātmane ||
Cf. Utpaladeva’s Vṛtti on Śivadṛṣṭi 1.1, that samāveśa is to be practiced assiduously, after which it grants fruit commensurate with the vision it generates.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
