<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 26 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Theology and AI</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2023-11-26_theology-and-ai/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2023-11-26_theology-and-ai/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2023/11/26/theology-and-ai/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Theology and AI&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;visualization-and-drift&#34;&gt;Visualization and drift&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A key feature of most polytheistic religions, typically natural religions, is the importance of a multiplicity of visualizations of deities. This visualization might be solely mental/textual or expressed in different ways in the graphic and plastic arts.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The mode of representation can change dramatically over time in the same religious tradition. For instance, we can infer that the early Indo-Europeans, going back to their Indo-Hittite past, had a fairly elaborate visualization of deities, but it was minimally expressed as physical iconography. However, different branches of Indo-Europeans convergently acquired physical artistic expressions of their pantheon in their loci of post-conquest settlement. Sometimes, these interacted with each other, resulting in fusions of styles. Thus, in the borderlands of the Panjab, there developed a vigorous iconographic tradition that brought together three distinct branches of Indo-European expression—the Hindus, the Iranics (Zoroastrian and Non-Zoroastrian), and the Greeks.+++(5)+++ The triumph of the Romans brought together the Greek and Roman traditions into a common iconographic expression that additionally swept in various non-IE articulations from West Asia and North Africa.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Categories of Hindus</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2004-09-23_categories-of-hindus/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Sep 2004 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2004-09-23_categories-of-hindus/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2004/09/23/categories-of-hindus/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;bhakti&#34;&gt;bhakti&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;She said would only marry ranganAtha. In a dream the triple-strider appeared to her father and asked him to send her decked in wedding attire to his shrine. Even as she neared the shrirangaM her father was filled with that inexplicable mixture of joy and sorrow, but she was experiencing unrestrained excitement. As the party reached the temple she jumped out of her palanquin and rushed to the garbhAgR^iha and merged with the 4-handed one in a flash of light.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>शास्त्र-सम्बन्धः</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/shAstra-sambandhaH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/shAstra-sambandhaH/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/blog_supplement/status/1379952671268995073&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Humans were not around from the inception in this universe. In fact they are very recent phenomenon given the age of the universe. The shAstra-s (in the broad sense) have been around for just a subset of that period of human existence. At some point the humans &amp;amp; their shAstra-s will become extinct. Thus, if the devatA-s were dependent on the shAstra-s then their existence will be finite &amp;amp; conterminal with the emergence &amp;amp; extinction of species like humans. This is contradictory with the very account of most devatA-s in a shAstra, be it naigamika or Agamika.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
