<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/MT_lekhAH/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2004 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/MT_lekhAH/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Limbya Shinde</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/MT_lekhAH/2004-03-16_limbya-shinde/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2004 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/MT_lekhAH/2004-03-16_limbya-shinde/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2004/03/16/limbya-shinde/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Limbya narrates: When I was a young I was seized by a by a bhoot. It was a huge ghost of the &lt;strong&gt;Khais&lt;/strong&gt; variety that may assume the form of a Meccan demon or a Mohammedan. When I was sleeping one night near my sheep the Khais came and pulled my leg. I was afraid and said f**k you, who is pulling at me. I woke up but could not see anything. Next morning I went to take bath at the river. I took off my clothes and went into the water. When I sprinkled myself with water the Khais pushed me into water. I said to myself f**k you, who is pushing me. Somehow I finished my bath and came out. Then I milked the sheep, washed my hands and ate some &lt;strong&gt;bhAkrI&lt;/strong&gt;. Then I took my staff and drove he sheep to the pasture. Then my body began to ache. I had hired a couple of herders to graze my 200-300 sheep. I called my herders and asked them to look after the sheep saying that I could not go on as I needed to sleep. I went to a raised platform where rice had been laid out to dry. I laid down my dhoti and went to sleep under the platform. I slept from 12 noon to 4 in the afternoon. Then I got up and slowly headed to our tent. When I got there darkness was closing.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
