<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;1 Academic and Brahmanical Orthodoxies on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/1_Orthodoxies_Madness_and_Method/1_Academic_and_Brahmanical_Orthodoxies/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;1 Academic and Brahmanical Orthodoxies on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/1_Orthodoxies_Madness_and_Method/1_Academic_and_Brahmanical_Orthodoxies/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 Sanskritic Culture and the Culture of Possession</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/1_Orthodoxies_Madness_and_Method/1_Academic_and_Brahmanical_Orthodoxies/01_Sanskritic_Culture_and_the_Culture_of_Possession/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/1_Orthodoxies_Madness_and_Method/1_Academic_and_Brahmanical_Orthodoxies/01_Sanskritic_Culture_and_the_Culture_of_Possession/</guid>
      <description>Ethnographic work at the beginning of the twentieth century, which has been supplemented and revitalized during the past forty years, shows that spirit or deity possession is a widespread epstēmē—a historically situated discourse, phenomenon, and practice—in Indian thought, culture, religion, and medicine.1 However, if our knowledge of the subject were limited to the accounts of classical Indologists and others who have privileged the “high” intellectual and religious traditions while eschewing the history of actual religious practice, we would scarcely know of the existence of this phenomenon, much less its pervasiveness.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>02 The Sanskritic Vocabulary of Possession</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/1_Orthodoxies_Madness_and_Method/1_Academic_and_Brahmanical_Orthodoxies/02_The_Sanskritic_Vocabulary_of_Possession/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/1_Orthodoxies_Madness_and_Method/1_Academic_and_Brahmanical_Orthodoxies/02_The_Sanskritic_Vocabulary_of_Possession/</guid>
      <description>It is difficult to recommend a single definition of possession, or indeed a single word for it, in the Indian context, primarily because this context—even as described in Sanskrit texts—is more accurately a shifting series of contexts that betray a broad life experience. Kathleen Erndl states, “The word possession can … provide only a rough and partial semantic equivalent for what is a fluid, multifaceted set of concepts.”39 The fact that I am able to locate only one attempt to define possession in Sanskrit literature, by the great tenth-century Kashmiri paṇḍita Abhinavagupta (discussed below), and that this definition does not easily suit most of the Sanskritic contexts of possession, demonstrates that possession as apprehended from these literary contexts constitutes a category in need of clarification.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>03 Problematics of Interpretation</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/1_Orthodoxies_Madness_and_Method/1_Academic_and_Brahmanical_Orthodoxies/03_Problematics_of_Interpretation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/1_Orthodoxies_Madness_and_Method/1_Academic_and_Brahmanical_Orthodoxies/03_Problematics_of_Interpretation/</guid>
      <description>Until the 1970s it was acceptable literary practice to employ terms such as “person,” “self,” and “experience” unquestioningly in academic discourse. Since then, however, these and other related terms have come under close critical scrutiny. The word “consciousness,” for example, is used in contemporary Anglophone culture in ways never imagined, for instance, in classical India; indeed, I have identified more than thirty different words and terms in one Sanskrit text alone, the Bhāgavata Purāṇa, that have been variously translated with this juggernaut significator of contemporary culture.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>04 The Concept of Experience</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/1_Orthodoxies_Madness_and_Method/1_Academic_and_Brahmanical_Orthodoxies/04_The_Concept_of_Experience/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/1_Orthodoxies_Madness_and_Method/1_Academic_and_Brahmanical_Orthodoxies/04_The_Concept_of_Experience/</guid>
      <description>When I speak of an experience of soma (Chapter 5), a cultural or religious experience, a personal experience, a dissociative experience, and especially an experience of possession, I am employing with apparent ease terminology that hovers on a precipitous edge of ancient and classical Indian discourse maps. No one can doubt that people as well as cultures and civilizations experience in some sense, and that they experience all the time. Several scholars, however, including Wilhelm Halbfass, Wayne Proudfoot, and Robert Sharf, have noted, or even reinforced, certain relatively recent doubts cast on the “notion” of experience, particularly religious experience, positing that its validity can be situated only within highly specified cultural contexts.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>05 The Person and the Self</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/1_Orthodoxies_Madness_and_Method/1_Academic_and_Brahmanical_Orthodoxies/05_The_Person_and_the_Self/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/1_Orthodoxies_Madness_and_Method/1_Academic_and_Brahmanical_Orthodoxies/05_The_Person_and_the_Self/</guid>
      <description>The notion of a “person” distinguished from a “self” was initially, if vaguely, proposed by Marcel Mauss in his final but seminal essay, “Une catégorie de l’esprit humain: la notion de personne, celle de ‘moi,’” written in 1938.55 Since then, philosophers and anthropologists have inquired further into these categories. This distinction is important in problematizing possession, especially in India, where the oppositions person/self share conceptual territory with the indigenous categories puruṣa/puruṣottama and ātman/brahman, and in early Buddhism with the terms attabhāva (Pali &amp;lt; Skt.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>06 NOTES</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/1_Orthodoxies_Madness_and_Method/1_Academic_and_Brahmanical_Orthodoxies/06_NOTES/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/1_Orthodoxies_Madness_and_Method/1_Academic_and_Brahmanical_Orthodoxies/06_NOTES/</guid>
      <description>Erndl 1996:178. See Daniel 1984:227 on the impossibility of studying a culture in its own terms, but for its own terms. We must keep Daniel’s caveat in mind throughout this study. Eliade 1969:339, also 320; cf. Eliade 1964:411ff. Eliade 1969:339; Lewis 1989. In a different context, Benz (1972) distinguishes between emotion (Ergriffenheit) and frenzy or spirit possession (Besessenheit). Ergriffenheit indicates blessing, healing, renewal, while Besessenheit indicates malevolent and destructive possession); cited by Schoembucher 1993:241–42.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
