<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;MT on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/tengrism/articles/MT/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;MT on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 03 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/tengrism/articles/MT/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Some further notes on</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/tengrism/articles/MT/2024-03-03_some-further-notes-on-the-mongol-religion-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/tengrism/articles/MT/2024-03-03_some-further-notes-on-the-mongol-religion-3/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
Some further notes on the Mongol religion-3
The core of the material discussed in this note is based on the publications of the Hungarian-Mongolian Joint Expedition studying folk traditions in Mongolia and the masterly work of Igor de Rachewiltz on religion in the Secret History of the Mongols (SHM). We take a look at this material from a comparative religions and historical perspective. A primer.
In the Ṛgveda, the deities Dyaus and Pṛthivī (alternatively known as Bhūmī or Kṣāmā) generally occur as dyad — a devatā-dvandva of the form Dyāvāpṛthivī or Dyāvābhūmī or Dyāvākṣāmā — that may be rendered as Heaven and Earth.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Some further notes on the old Mongol religion-2</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/tengrism/articles/MT/2021-07-01_some-further-notes-on-the-old-mongol-religion-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/tengrism/articles/MT/2021-07-01_some-further-notes-on-the-old-mongol-religion-2/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
O fire mother,
whose father is flint,
whose mother is pebble,
whose meal is yellow feather grass,
whose life is an elm tree.
An incantation to the Fire Goddess Ghalun-eke; translation from the Mongolian by Yönsiyebü Rinchen
This note revisits some themes relating to the Mongol religion gathered in the 1950s and 1960s by the Mongol scholar Yönsiyebü Rinchen from the Mongolian Academy of Science, Ulaanbaatar. He says that he descends on his father’s side from an ancient Hunnic clan founded by a certain Yöngsiyebü, who was the lord of a tümen.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Some further notes on the Mongol religion</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/tengrism/articles/MT/2013-04-03_some-further-notes-on-the-mongol-religion/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Apr 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/tengrism/articles/MT/2013-04-03_some-further-notes-on-the-mongol-religion/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
The young Mongol scholar Dorje Banzar, published a book in 1846 in Russian at the university of Kazan that brought to light for the first time the old religion of the Mongols to the scholarly world. In the 1960s, M. Jaadamba, a descendent of Chingiz Kha’Khan, along with a group of Mongolian workers brought to light several texts and incantations of the ancient Mongol ritual that had never been seen before.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The fire hymns of the Mongols</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/tengrism/articles/MT/2005-10-23_the-fire-hymns-of-the-mongols/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Oct 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/tengrism/articles/MT/2005-10-23_the-fire-hymns-of-the-mongols/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
The fire worship of the Hindus is an ancient Indo-European trait that was clearly amplified in the Indo-Iranian branch. The primary fire priests of the Indo-Aryans are the bhR^igus and and a~Ngirasas who are remembered in the old vedic texts. The bhR^igus also known as atharvans are also remembered as the founders of the fire worship amongst the Iranians. The Iranian word for fire being Atar. One of the interesting trends noticed in the Hindu fire worship is personal association of each major Aryan clan with the invocation of fire, recaptitulating the way their founders did it via the AprI hymns.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fire-ritual</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/tengrism/articles/MT/fire-ritual/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/tengrism/articles/MT/fire-ritual/</guid>
      <description>Source: TW
From 2 Mongol manuscripts copied on Russian paper 1 can reconstruct a fairly archaic form of the Mongol fire ritual minus the bauddham. Below are those core element of the &amp;ldquo;pradhAna-homa&amp;rdquo; &amp;amp; agny upasthAnam. Even here the overlay of Old Iranic, H &amp;amp; core Mongolic elements is seen.
We summon good fortune from the land and direction of Esrün Qormusta and all gods. Qurui qurui qurui. We summon good fortune from the direction of the land of the mighty nāga kings and all nāgas.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
