<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;MT on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/tengrism/articles/MT/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;MT on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 03 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/tengrism/articles/MT/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Some further notes on</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/tengrism/articles/MT/2024-03-03_some-further-notes-on-the-mongol-religion-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/tengrism/articles/MT/2024-03-03_some-further-notes-on-the-mongol-religion-3/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2024/03/03/some-further-notes-on-the-mongol-religion-3/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Some further notes on the Mongol religion-3&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The core of the material discussed in this note is based on the publications of the Hungarian-Mongolian Joint Expedition studying folk traditions in Mongolia and the masterly work of Igor de Rachewiltz on religion in the Secret History of the Mongols (SHM). We take a look at this material from a comparative religions and historical perspective. &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2021/07/01/some-further-notes-on-the-old-mongol-religion-2/&#34;&gt;A primer.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the Ṛgveda, the deities Dyaus and Pṛthivī (alternatively known as Bhūmī or Kṣāmā) generally occur as dyad — a devatā-dvandva of the form Dyāvāpṛthivī or Dyāvābhūmī or Dyāvākṣāmā — that may be rendered as Heaven and Earth. These devatā-dvandva-s are mentioned a total of 122 times in the RV. They are understood both as the parents of the gods and the universe (e.g., ya ime dyāvāpṛthivī janitrī rūpair apiṃśad bhuvanāni viśvā ।), and the stage for their acts. Imagine a religious system where these other gods recede into that backdrop or reside in a hidden realm that can only be seen by special individuals. What we would end up with is something like the overt religious system of the SHM. In that primal history (epic) of the Chingizid Mongols the chief religious protagonists are a precise cognate of the Indo-Aryan devatā-dvandva Dyāvāpṛthivī. In the Mongolian, it occurs in the form Tenggeri[Tengri]-Qajar, with Tengri being the cognate of Dyaus and Qajar being the cognate of Pṛthivī. Together, Tengri-Qajar are said to shape human events (Mo: jayaghan ~ destiny), provide the foundation for the existence of animals, and give “increase”, power, strength and protection. As per the SHM, together they conferred on Temüjin the lordship of the ulus and, in the same text, they are elsewhere mentioned as protecting Chingiz Khan and his army. They are explicitly mentioned to have aided Temüjin in the campaign again the Merkits along with Toghrul Wang Khan and Jamuqa to recover his wife, Börte. Thus, generally, the role of the Mongolian devatā-dvandva matches quite well with the Indo-Aryan Dyāvāpṛthivī. For instance, Atri invokes the dyad thusly:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Some further notes on the old Mongol religion-2</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/tengrism/articles/MT/2021-07-01_some-further-notes-on-the-old-mongol-religion-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/tengrism/articles/MT/2021-07-01_some-further-notes-on-the-old-mongol-religion-2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2021/07/01/some-further-notes-on-the-old-mongol-religion-2/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;O fire mother,&lt;br&gt;&#xA;whose father is flint,&lt;br&gt;&#xA;whose mother is pebble,&lt;br&gt;&#xA;whose meal is yellow feather grass,&lt;br&gt;&#xA;whose life is an elm tree.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;An incantation to the Fire Goddess Ghalun-eke; translation from the Mongolian by Yönsiyebü Rinchen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This note revisits some themes relating to the Mongol religion gathered in the 1950s and 1960s by the Mongol scholar Yönsiyebü Rinchen from the Mongolian Academy of Science, Ulaanbaatar. He says that he descends on his father’s side from an ancient Hunnic clan founded by a certain Yöngsiyebü, who was the lord of a tümen. He records an oral chant preserved by the clan on this ancient ancestor of theirs. On his mother’s side he claims descent from Chingiz Khan via Tsoktu Taiji (1581-1637 CE), the chief of Kokonor, who aided the practitioners of the ancient Bon religion of Tibet before they fell to the bauddha-s backed by the Oirat Mongols.+++(5)+++ Rinchen, with his connections to the old Mongol religion prior to its fall to the bauddha-s, records several notable features of its practice. As we have noted before on these pages, the fall of the old religion to the bauddha-s was neither smooth nor complete. In addition to the material collected by Heissig, we have deprecations such as this one from the old shamans against the religion and followers of the tathāgata invoking at the black (qara) “ghosts” or “spirits”:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Some further notes on the Mongol religion</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/tengrism/articles/MT/2013-04-03_some-further-notes-on-the-mongol-religion/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Apr 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/tengrism/articles/MT/2013-04-03_some-further-notes-on-the-mongol-religion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2013/04/03/some-further-notes-on-the-mongol-religion/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The young Mongol scholar Dorje Banzar, published a book in 1846 in Russian at the university of Kazan that brought to light for the first time the old religion of the Mongols to the scholarly world. In the 1960s, M. Jaadamba, a descendent of Chingiz Kha’Khan, along with a group of Mongolian workers brought to light several texts and incantations of the ancient Mongol ritual that had never been seen before. We have alluded to some of these incantations on these pages before. This old religion of the Mongols has been considerably diluted by the missionary activity of the tAthAgata-s but remains in certain pockets of steppe eking out a precarious existence. Along with the hoary Shinto tradition of the eastern islanders it remains one of the important documents of old Eurasian ritual expression. We had early pointed out parallels between to &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2005/10/23/the-fire-hymns-of-the-mongols/&#34;&gt;Mongol fire ritual&lt;/a&gt; and the ancient Hindu one in the veda. We had also pointed to the interactions of the Mongol tradition with the Indo-Aryan and Iranian traditions, with elements such as the the &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2010/05/10/the-mahamayuri-vidya-rajni/&#34;&gt;nakShatra mantra-s&lt;/a&gt;, the equation of &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2007/12/06/the-confluence-of-four-paths/&#34;&gt;Köke Möngke Tengri with Ahura Mazda&lt;/a&gt; and the invocation of Darqan Guejir Tengri.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The fire hymns of the Mongols</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/tengrism/articles/MT/2005-10-23_the-fire-hymns-of-the-mongols/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Oct 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/tengrism/articles/MT/2005-10-23_the-fire-hymns-of-the-mongols/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2005/10/23/the-fire-hymns-of-the-mongols/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The fire worship of the Hindus is an ancient Indo-European trait that&#xA;was clearly amplified in the Indo-Iranian branch. The primary fire&#xA;priests of the Indo-Aryans are the bhR^igus and and a~Ngirasas who are&#xA;remembered in the old vedic texts. The bhR^igus also known as atharvans&#xA;are also remembered as the founders of the fire worship amongst the&#xA;Iranians. The Iranian word for fire being Atar. One of the interesting&#xA;trends noticed in the Hindu fire worship is personal association of each&#xA;major Aryan clan with the invocation of fire, recaptitulating the way&#xA;their founders did it via the AprI hymns. Beyond the AprIs there are the&#xA;original kindlers of the fire who are remembered as part of the begining&#xA;of the fire rites. This illustrated in the famous formula remembering&#xA;the first of the bhArgavas who kindled the fire. In any regular fire&#xA;sacrifice termed the iShTi, after the rectitation of the 15-fold&#xA;sAmidhenI hymns (pra vo vAja …) the pravara of the yajamAna and his&#xA;founding fathers are recited. Then even as the adhvaryu pours a libation&#xA;of ghee in the fire even as the hotar chants:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fire-ritual</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/tengrism/articles/MT/fire-ritual/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/tengrism/articles/MT/fire-ritual/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/blog_supplement/status/1689508464945491969&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;From 2 Mongol manuscripts copied on Russian paper  1 can reconstruct a fairly archaic form of the Mongol fire ritual minus the bauddham. Below are those core element of the &amp;ldquo;pradhAna-homa&amp;rdquo; &amp;amp; agny upasthAnam. Even here the overlay of Old Iranic, H &amp;amp; core Mongolic elements is seen.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We summon good fortune from the land and direction of Esrün Qormusta and all gods. Qurui qurui qurui. &lt;br&gt;&#xA;We summon good fortune from the direction of the land of the mighty nāga kings and all nāgas. Qurui qurui qurui. &lt;br&gt;&#xA;We invite favors from the land of the King of Jewels, the god Vaiśravana and other immensely powerful yakṣas. Qurui qurui qurui. &lt;br&gt;&#xA;We invite (B: summon) good fortune of the supreme ninety-nine gods and the Möngke Tengri, the Father. Qurui qurui qurui. &lt;br&gt;&#xA;We summon good fortune from the Lower Seventy-Seven Etügen mothers and lords of the land. Qurui qurui qurui. &lt;br&gt;&#xA;We invite favors of the Seven Old Men who gave birth to everyone belonging to people and animals and of tens of thousands of stars. Qurui qurui qurui. &lt;br&gt;&#xA;We invite good fortune of the Sun, Moon, Luminous sons and daughters (Var: 28 asterisms), the immensely powerful protective genius [of the standard] and all the splendor. Qurui qurui qurui. &lt;br&gt;&#xA;We invite good fortune of the undying long life and the never-diminishing goods and domestic animals. Qurui qurui qurui. &lt;br&gt;&#xA;We invite good fortune of the large kinship family, noble origin, and unequaled reputation. Qurui qurui qurui. &lt;br&gt;&#xA;We summon the beneficial fortune of offspring proliferating virtue and merit and multiplying [descendants]. Qurui qurui qurui &lt;br&gt;&#xA;We invite the good fortune of fruits and grains and various fruits. Qurui qurui qurui.&#xA;Wealth and livestock incantations. &lt;br&gt;&#xA;May the calamity of contagious air and epidemics disappear! May my well-being be established. Qurui qurui qurui. &lt;br&gt;&#xA;In the Indian language: kuy-e kuy-e kuy-e. In the Tibetan language: gyang du len. In the Mongolian language: qurui qurui qurui. &lt;br&gt;&#xA;May the good fortune summoned in three languages arrive in its entirety and stay here securely. Qurui qurui qurui. &lt;br&gt;&#xA;Any little misdeeds that I have done due to the ignorance of my mind, our savior and refuge (the Fire God), be pleased to forgive them all. &lt;br&gt;&#xA;My Fire God, bringing benefit to yourself and others in leaving, please establish the auspiciousness, and now and whenever I summon, be pleased to come [again] with mercy and grace. &lt;br&gt;&#xA;As the fire god in the form of the body of supreme wisdom leaves for his place, the protector deity gains the form of the blazing fire. &lt;br&gt;&#xA;The blessings of Esrün and respectable guardian gods and the auspiciousness of help-providing gods having been established, may the affairs intending good peace be fulfilled as desired, may the life be long and [may] the felicity and happiness free of disease become absolute.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
