<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;05 SĪTĀ on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/05_sItA/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;05 SĪTĀ on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/05_sItA/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 THE EARLY HISTORY OF SĪTĀ</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/05_sItA/01_THE_EARLY_HISTORY_OF_sItA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/05_sItA/01_THE_EARLY_HISTORY_OF_sItA/</guid>
      <description>The word sītā means “furrow,” “the line made by the plow,” and is the name of a goddess associated with plowed fields in Vedic literature. In a hymn addressed to the lord of the fields, Kṣetrapati, Sītā is invoked as follows:
Auspicious Sītā, come thou near:
we venerate and worship thee
That thou mayst bless and prosper us
and bring us fruits abundantly.
May Indra press the furrow down,
may Pūshan guide its course aright.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>02 KINGS AND THE FERTILITY OF THE EARTH</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/05_sItA/02_KINGS_AND_THE_FERTILITY_OF_THE_EARTH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/05_sItA/02_KINGS_AND_THE_FERTILITY_OF_THE_EARTH/</guid>
      <description>Identification of Rāma’s wife with a goddess of the plowed fields, with a goddess of fertility, seems to be related to the central role that kings in ancient India were assumed to play in promoting the fertility of the land.8 The interrelation between fertility and the manly vigor and power of the ruler or king finds its prototype in the Ṛg-veda, where the mighty god Indra combats the demon Vṛtra, who withholds the creative, nourishing waters of creation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>03 THE IDEAL WIFE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/05_sItA/03_THE_IDEAL_WIFE/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/05_sItA/03_THE_IDEAL_WIFE/</guid>
      <description>Sītā is defined in the Rāmāyaṇa and in the subsequent cult of Rāma almost entirely in relation to her husband. She is portrayed as the ideal Hindu wife, whose every thought revolves around her husband. For Sītā Rāma is the center of her life. She is always steadfast in her loyalty to him. His welfare, reputation, and wishes are uppermost in her mind. The Manu-dharma-śāstra describes the ideal wife as a woman who always remains faithful to her husband, no matter what his character might be: “Though destitute of virtue, or seeking pleasure elsewhere, or devoid of good qualities, a husband must be constantly worshiped as a god by a faithful wife” (5.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>04 IDEAL DEVOTEE AND INTERMEDIARY</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/05_sItA/04_IDEAL_DEVOTEE_AND_INTERMEDIARY/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/05_sItA/04_IDEAL_DEVOTEE_AND_INTERMEDIARY/</guid>
      <description>After Vālmikī’s Rāmāyaṇa, Rāma increasingly ascended to a position of supreme deity for many Hindus. Today in India he is one of the most popular deities and is the recipient of fervent devotion from millions of devotees. The shift in Rāma’s status from that of a human hero or incarnation of Viṣṇu in Vālmikī’s Rāmāyaṇa to that of the lord of the worlds is evident in the sixteenth-century Hindi work of Tulsī Dās, the Rāmcarit-mānas, an extremely popular devotional work in North India.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
