<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;06 RĀDHĀ on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/06_rAdhA/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;06 RĀDHĀ on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/06_rAdhA/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 THE EARLY HISTORY OF RĀDHĀ</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/06_rAdhA/01_THE_EARLY_HISTORY_OF_rAdhA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/06_rAdhA/01_THE_EARLY_HISTORY_OF_rAdhA/</guid>
      <description>Rādhā does not appear as a fully developed figure until quite late in the Hindu tradition. Prior to Jayadeva’s Gītagovinda (twelfth century) she is mentioned in only a few brief references.2 The Padma-, Brahmavaivarta-, and Devī-bhāgavata-purāṇas, which describe her affair with Kṛṣṇa in detail, are all considered late. Although the early references are few and although they never supply lengthy descriptions of Rādhā, her character is nevertheless clearly suggested.
In these passages Rādhā is a lovesick girl or woman who is overcome by her emotions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>02 THE GOPĪ TRADITION</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/06_rAdhA/02_THE_gopI_TRADITION/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/06_rAdhA/02_THE_gopI_TRADITION/</guid>
      <description>Another historical thread is important in understanding Rādhā’s central role in Jayadeva’s writing and in the later devotional movements of North India. This is the mythological tradition surrounding Kṛṣṇa’s sojourn in Vraja and his dalliance there with the gopīs, the cowherd women of the village. This tradition dates back to the Harivaṁśa (ca. A.D. 500) and is a central part of most later Vaiṣṇava Purānas. The most popular and detailed rendering of the tradition prior to Jayadeva is found in the Bhāgavata-purāṇa, written in South India sometime during the tenth century.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>03 RĀDHĀ AS BELONGING TO ANOTHER \(PARAKĪYĀ\)</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/06_rAdhA/03_rAdhA_AS_BELONGING_TO_ANOTHER_parakIyA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/06_rAdhA/03_rAdhA_AS_BELONGING_TO_ANOTHER_parakIyA/</guid>
      <description>Not until Jayadeva’s Gītagovinda in the twelfth century do we find a sustained rendition of Rādhā as the central figure in the love drama between Kṛṣṇa and the cowherd women of Vraja. In this poem the tradition of Rādhā as Kṛṣṇa’s favorite and the tradition of the gopīs came together to form the central heroine of the text. The poem is dominated by the lovesick Rādhā, who ventures out at night to search the woods for her lover, Kṛṣṇa.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>04 RĀDHĀ AS BELONGING TO KṚṢṆA \(SVAKĪYĀ\)</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/06_rAdhA/04_rAdhA_AS_BELONGING_TO_kRShNa_svakIyA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/06_rAdhA/04_rAdhA_AS_BELONGING_TO_kRShNa_svakIyA/</guid>
      <description>Although Rādhā’s position as Kṛṣṇa’s legal, divine consort never became very popular in Kṛṣṇa devotional movements, there is a sustained rendition of Kṛṣṇa mythology in which Rādhā is cast in this role. The Brahma-vaivarta-purāṇa assumes Rādhā’s status as a goddess.25 She is inextricably associated with Kṛṣṇa philosophically as his śakti, as his underlying power or that dimension of himself that empowers him, indeed, enables him, to create the world and display himself in his various forms.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
