<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;8 Vampires, Prostitutes, and Poets on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/3_Classical_Literature/8_Vampires_Prostitutes_and_Poets/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;8 Vampires, Prostitutes, and Poets on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/3_Classical_Literature/8_Vampires_Prostitutes_and_Poets/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 Culture, Fiction, and Possession</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/3_Classical_Literature/8_Vampires_Prostitutes_and_Poets/01_Culture_Fiction_and_Possession/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/3_Classical_Literature/8_Vampires_Prostitutes_and_Poets/01_Culture_Fiction_and_Possession/</guid>
      <description>In the present study we examine possession as a descriptor for a kind or class of mood, as a mechanism of divine creation, as a possible consequence of the consumption of soma, as a factor in disease production, as part of the job description of the gandharva and other semidivine beings, as ordnance in the arsenal of accomplished yogins, and as a mode of devotion. What sets these portrayals apart from representations of possession in texts we examine here is that they were assumed by the authors of the various genres we have examined so far (Vedas, Purāṇas, Sanskrit epics, Yoga texts, Tantras, medical literature, and so on) to abide in a kind of facticity based on the interplay of myth, historical event, discourse mode, and didactic intent.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>02 Possession in Sanskrit Fiction</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/3_Classical_Literature/8_Vampires_Prostitutes_and_Poets/02_Possession_in_Sanskrit_Fiction/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/3_Classical_Literature/8_Vampires_Prostitutes_and_Poets/02_Possession_in_Sanskrit_Fiction/</guid>
      <description>Possession, especially of the dead, was a particularly lively motif in Sanskrit and other Indic fiction. This was discussed at length by Maurice Bloomfield, who noted in 1917 that possessing another’s body “is an art destined to make a brilliant career in fiction.”5 Bloomfield, however, examined possession solely as a literary curiosity, not as a cultural phenomenon. In his study, Bloomfield summarized tales from the MBh, the KSS, including its lengthy cycle called Vetālapañcaviṃśati or the twenty-five tales of King Vikrama and a certain testy vampire (vetāla), and a few Jain texts, including the Pārśvanātha Caritra and Merutuṇga’s Prabandhacintāmaṇi (Wishing Stone of Narratives).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>03 The Vetālapañcaviṃśati</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/3_Classical_Literature/8_Vampires_Prostitutes_and_Poets/03_The_Vetla-pancaviMshati/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/3_Classical_Literature/8_Vampires_Prostitutes_and_Poets/03_The_Vetla-pancaviMshati/</guid>
      <description>The obvious place to begin is the Vetālapañcaviṃśati, probably the best-known example of possession in Hindu fiction (I exclude the MBh from this category). I can hardly do better than to quote Asko Parpola’s lengthy summary of the frame story of this cycle:
The hero is a brave king called Vikramāditya, the “sun of valour,” or (in Somadeva’s version) Trivikramasena. A mendicant (bhikṣu, śramaṇa) called Kṣāntiśīla donates a fruit every day to the king, who without further ado gives them to his treasurer.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>04 The Bhagavadajjukāprahasanam</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/3_Classical_Literature/8_Vampires_Prostitutes_and_Poets/04_The_Bhagavadajjukprahasanam/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/3_Classical_Literature/8_Vampires_Prostitutes_and_Poets/04_The_Bhagavadajjukprahasanam/</guid>
      <description>The most extended example of possession as a motif in Sanskrit fiction occurs in the early seventh-century drama Bhagavadajjukāprahasanam (The Farce of the Saint-Courtesan), by the Pallava king Mahendravarman (though it was more likely written by a paṇḍita in his court). One of the peculiarities of Sanskrit drama is that it is composed not just in Sanskrit but in one or more Middle Indic (Prakrit) dialects as well, based on the social ranking of the characters.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>05 Can There Be an Aesthetic of Possession?</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/3_Classical_Literature/8_Vampires_Prostitutes_and_Poets/05_Can_There_Be_an_Aesthetic_of_Possession/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/3_Classical_Literature/8_Vampires_Prostitutes_and_Poets/05_Can_There_Be_an_Aesthetic_of_Possession/</guid>
      <description>Any discussion of a possible formal aesthetic of possession based on classical theories of Indian poetics (alaṃkāraśāstra), the central element of which is cognate, in spirit at least, with what is known in Western scholarly discourse as audience response theory, must be addressed more fully after an evaluation of possession in devotional religious practice and an appraisal of Indian demonologies (bhūtavidyā). These are discussed in Chapters 9 and 12. However, it is important to begin this discussion here, because more than anywhere else, except perhaps in the more technical and inaccessible literature of Āyurveda and Tantra, possession is revealed in fiction and drama to be a conspicuous feature of popular culture, if not always well regarded among the literati.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>06 NOTES</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/3_Classical_Literature/8_Vampires_Prostitutes_and_Poets/06_NOTES/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/3_Classical_Literature/8_Vampires_Prostitutes_and_Poets/06_NOTES/</guid>
      <description>See Clifford 1984:148ff. See, for example, the work of Parpola, who has often speculated on the origins of the Sanskrit epics (e.g., 2002). Parpola sees a mid-first-millennium B.C.E. migration of pale-skinned (pāṇḍu) Iranians who migrated into India, integrated with the local population, legitimated themselves by fabricating genealogies that situated them in ruling families, and finally disseminated tales of their exploits. Few Indologists will easily subscribe to this theory, but it demonstrates that consideration of the MBh as fiction remains an ongoing enterprise.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
