<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;07 DURGĀ on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/07_durgA/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;07 DURGĀ on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/07_durgA/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 THE WARRIOR GODDESS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/07_durgA/01_THE_WARRIOR_GODDESS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/07_durgA/01_THE_WARRIOR_GODDESS/</guid>
      <description>Although several Vedic deities play central roles as demon slayers and warriors, no goddesses are cast in this function in Vedic literature. The name Durgā is mentioned in Vedic literature,1 but no goddess resembling the warrior goddess of later Hinduism is to be found in these early texts.
Around the fourth century A.D. images of Durgā slaying a buffalo begin to become common throughout India.2 By the medieval period (after the sixth century) Durgā has become a well-known and popularly worshiped deity.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>02 THE WORSHIP OF DURGĀ</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/07_durgA/02_THE_WORSHIP_OF_durgA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/07_durgA/02_THE_WORSHIP_OF_durgA/</guid>
      <description>One of the most important festivals in North India is Durgā Pūjā, which is celebrated in the autumn during the month of Āśvin. The festival takes place over a period of nine days and is often called the Navarātra festival. The central image of the festival shows Durgā slaying Mahiṣa. The iconographical details of the images are usually faithful to the scene as described in the Devī-māhātmya and other scriptures. Durgā has many arms, each of which bears a weapon; she stands on her lion vehicle; and she is thrusting her trident into the chest of Mahiṣa, who is in human form, half-emerged from the carcass of a slain buffalo.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
