<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;6 Friendly Acquisitions, Hostile Takeovers on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/3_Classical_Literature/6_Friendly_Acquisitions_Hostile_Takeovers/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;6 Friendly Acquisitions, Hostile Takeovers on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/3_Classical_Literature/6_Friendly_Acquisitions_Hostile_Takeovers/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 The Mahābhārata, Where Everything Can Be Found</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/3_Classical_Literature/6_Friendly_Acquisitions_Hostile_Takeovers/01_The_MahAbhArata_Where_Everything_Can_Be_Found/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/3_Classical_Literature/6_Friendly_Acquisitions_Hostile_Takeovers/01_The_MahAbhArata_Where_Everything_Can_Be_Found/</guid>
      <description>The Vocabulary of Possession in the MBh Minoru Hara has scoured the MBh for occurrences of ā√viś, ostensibly to shed light on the term śraddhāviveśa (possessed by faith) in the Kaṭha Upaniṣad (1.2).3 Indeed, his focus is more on the MBh than on the Upaniṣads, saving the present author considerable labor. He lists sixty semantic contexts in which ā√viś is found in the MBh, in verbal, nominal, and adjectival form. It is clear from Hara’s study that āveśa was a popular and highly developed notion in the MBh.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>02 The Skandas</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/3_Classical_Literature/6_Friendly_Acquisitions_Hostile_Takeovers/02_The_Skandas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/3_Classical_Literature/6_Friendly_Acquisitions_Hostile_Takeovers/02_The_Skandas/</guid>
      <description>One of the most prominent varieties of possession in Indian literature is demonic, disease-producing possession. This topic is largely the province of the classical medical tradition (Āyurveda), where it undergoes visible development from the earliest texts of Caraka and Suśruta in the first few centuries C.E. to the later compendia in the early to mid-second millennium. These texts describe exogenous (āgantuka) diseases caused by grahas (graspers), whose numbers grow and assume more specific identities over the centuries.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>03 Notes on Possession in the Rāmāyana</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/3_Classical_Literature/6_Friendly_Acquisitions_Hostile_Takeovers/03_Notes_on_Possession_in_the_rAmAya-Na/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/3_Classical_Literature/6_Friendly_Acquisitions_Hostile_Takeovers/03_Notes_on_Possession_in_the_rAmAya-Na/</guid>
      <description>In striking contrast to the MBh, the Rāmāyaṇa does not comprehend or explicate a diversity of possession states. In the Rāmāyaṇa possession is employed entirely as a descriptor, sometimes as a metaphor of emotional engagement, not as an indicator of hostile or friendly takeover of a body by a spirit, deity, or yogin. This reflects the divergent nature of the two epics. The MBh is defined by its ambiguities of character and plot, of good and evil, and of dharma.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>04 NOTES</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/3_Classical_Literature/6_Friendly_Acquisitions_Hostile_Takeovers/04_NOTES/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/3_Classical_Literature/6_Friendly_Acquisitions_Hostile_Takeovers/04_NOTES/</guid>
      <description>Hiltebeitel (2001:18ff.) argues for a much more consolidated dating, with the entire composition between 150 B.C.E. and the beginning of the Common Era. See Fitzgerald’s critique of this (2003). It will not be possible here to deal with cases not involved directly with possession, no matter how fascinating, such as the case of the mixed-gender identity of Sikhandin, in the Vanaparvan. Cf. Olivelle 1998:375; Roebuck 2000:312. The literature on regional MBhs and Rāms attests to this; cf.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
