<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/laxmIH/meta/MT_lekhAH/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 21 Dec 2006 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/laxmIH/meta/MT_lekhAH/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>The basic invocation of padmAvatI according the padmAvatI kalpa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/laxmIH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-12-21_the-basic-invocation-of-padmavati-according-the-padmavati-kalpa/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Dec 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/laxmIH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-12-21_the-basic-invocation-of-padmavati-according-the-padmavati-kalpa/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
The jinendra explained at length how the padmAvatI prayoga-s are performed as per the padmAvatI kalpa. Described below is the vidhi for padmAvatI ArAdhana:
athaH sarvAvarNa pUjA:
OM hrIM dharaNendrAya namaH – eastern door; OM hrIM adhachChadanAya namaH – southern door; OM hrIM UrdhvachChadanAya namaH – western door; OM hrIM padmachChadanAya namaH – northern door
OM laM indrAya namaH (E) | OM raM agnaye namaH (SE) | OM sham yamAya namaH (S) | OM ShaM nairR^ityAya namaH (SW) | OM vaM varuNAya namaH (W) | OM yaM vAyave namaH (NW) | OM saM kuberAya namaH (N) | OM haM IshAnAya namaH (NE) ||</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>memories arising from the padmAvatI stones</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/laxmIH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-09-24_memories-arising-from-the-padmavati-stones/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Sep 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/laxmIH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-09-24_memories-arising-from-the-padmavati-stones/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
As mentioned earlier in my explorations of the maharaTTa country with shUdra-shreShTha, S and Mis-creant I came across several aniconic padmAvatI stones painted orange with a lead paint. However, in the exploration of Satmala we did see a couple of iconic padmavatI images. One of them was still in worship and another was largely in neglect in a dung-ridden area. This image was strange in having a nAstIka arihant inscribed on her.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>totalottara tantra mAhAlakShmI krama</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/laxmIH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2005-10-10_totalottara-tantra-mahalakshmi-krama/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Oct 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/laxmIH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2005-10-10_totalottara-tantra-mahalakshmi-krama/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
The totalottara tantra is one of the important garuDa tantras of which fragments relating to special worship of mahAlakShmI are preserved by tradition. It may be done on the night of the concluding mahAlakShmI day during the sharada navarAtrI or dIpAvalI.
Of the great mantra of shrI nArAyaNa is the R^iShi; mahAlakShmI is the devatA
oM shrAM a~NguShThAbhyAM namaH /
oM shrIM tarjanIbhyAM namaH /
oM shrUM madhyamAbhyAM namaH /</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Antiquity as major deity</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/laxmIH/meta/MT_lekhAH/antiquity_as_major_deity/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/laxmIH/meta/MT_lekhAH/antiquity_as_major_deity/</guid>
      <description>Clearly there was the classic viShNu-focal system of vedic and earlier IE provenance; then there was the more local evolution in the Indo-Iranian borderlands of the vAsudeva-sAttvata tradition. The earlier harivaMsha was definitely focused on a version of the sAttvata tradition. But there was a parallel strand of vaiShNava tradition predominant among the vaikhAnasa-s &amp;amp; and an early strand of pA~ncharAtra-s that was closer to vaidika focality on viShNu.
The viShNu purANa tries bring the 2 together by giving devakIputra the focus of the &amp;ldquo;earthly&amp;rdquo; expression of the sAttvata religion a central place in the narrative.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lakshmi Ardoksho Fortuna Matronae</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/laxmIH/meta/MT_lekhAH/laxmI_Ardoksho_fortuna_matronae/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/laxmIH/meta/MT_lekhAH/laxmI_Ardoksho_fortuna_matronae/</guid>
      <description>For comparison see earlier image of parallel iconography:
kAshmIra-laxmIH chipped-elephant-at-top lions cornucopia Now note the following:
She has a cornucopia, a distinctive feature in northern representations of shrI where she is equated in iconography with her cognates, the Roman Fortuna &amp;amp; Iranian Ardoksho who are both shown with the same. Note this syncretic Gandharan lakShmI-Ardoksho
gAndhAra-laxmI-ardoksho Note the same and iconographic parallels in this Roman Pompeiian Fortuna
pompeii-fortuna Note the same iconography of the central Celtic homolog goddess from the Lyons triad of Matronae.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
