<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;3 Concluding Reflections on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/tantric-divine-feminine/3_Concluding_Reflections/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;3 Concluding Reflections on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/tantric-divine-feminine/3_Concluding_Reflections/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 Corpses and Cremation Grounds</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/tantric-divine-feminine/3_Concluding_Reflections/01_Corpses_and_Cremation_Grounds/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/tantric-divine-feminine/3_Concluding_Reflections/01_Corpses_and_Cremation_Grounds/</guid>
      <description>Corpses are remarkably often associated with the Mahavidyas, and cremation grounds seem to be highly favored as places in which to worship them. Kali, Tārā, Bagalamukhi, Tripura-sundari, Matarigi, and Bhairavi are all said to stand or sit upon corpses. Kali, Tārā, Chinnamasta, and Dhumavati are often described or pictured as dwelling in cremation grounds. On several occasions the *Mantra-mahodadhih *stipulates that *sadhand *(spiritual endeavor) should be done while sitting on a corpse or on a place where a corpse has recently been buried.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>02 Skulls and Severed Heads</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/tantric-divine-feminine/3_Concluding_Reflections/02_Skulls_and_Severed_Heads/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/tantric-divine-feminine/3_Concluding_Reflections/02_Skulls_and_Severed_Heads/</guid>
      <description>Another remarkable feature of Mahavidya iconography is the prevalence of skulls and chopped-off heads. Kali, Tārā, Chinnamasta, Matarigi, and Bhairavi all wear garlands of skulls or severed heads and are often said to hold a freshly cut head or a skull in their hands. Skulls also adorn Tara&amp;rsquo;s forehead and sometimes Kali&amp;rsquo;s hair. Some texts devoted to worship of the Mahavidyas also prescribe skulls as seats upon which effective *sadhana *may be performed.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>03 Sexuality and Awakened Consciousness</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/tantric-divine-feminine/3_Concluding_Reflections/03_Sexuality_and_Awakened_Consciousness/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/tantric-divine-feminine/3_Concluding_Reflections/03_Sexuality_and_Awakened_Consciousness/</guid>
      <description>Mahavidya iconography, mythology, worship, and ritual are dominated by implicit and explicit sexual symbolism. Sexual intercourse is explicitly portrayed in the *dhydna *mantras and portraits of Kali, Chinnamasta, and Tara,24 and most of the individual Mahavidyas are described as sexually attractive and powerful. The mythology concerning the origin of certain individual Mahavidya goddesses (for example, Chinnamasta and Matarigi) stresses sexual tension. The yantras that represent the Mahavidyas contain implicitly sexual symbols, and the central metaphor of awakening *kundalini **sakti *may be interpreted as the arousal of sexual energy.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>04 The Conjunction of Death and Sexual Imagery</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/tantric-divine-feminine/3_Concluding_Reflections/04_The_Conjunction_of_Death_and_Sexual_Imagery/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/tantric-divine-feminine/3_Concluding_Reflections/04_The_Conjunction_of_Death_and_Sexual_Imagery/</guid>
      <description>It is striking that imagery of both sex and death should be so central in Mahavidya materials and that both are so often juxtaposed in the characterization of a goddess and in certain rituals of worship. Kali, Tārā, and Chinnamasta, in particular, often combine both types of imagery in their icons. In an eighteenth-century Kangra painting, Tārā stands on Kama and Rati, who are copulating on a cremation fire.31 Kali is sometimes shown copulating with Siva in a cremation ground,32 and Chinnamasta decapitates herself while standing or sitting on Rati, who is having sexual intercourse with Kama.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>05 The Roles of Women and Reverence for Women</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/tantric-divine-feminine/3_Concluding_Reflections/05_The_Roles_of_Women_and_Reverence_for_Women/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/tantric-divine-feminine/3_Concluding_Reflections/05_The_Roles_of_Women_and_Reverence_for_Women/</guid>
      <description>It is striking how central female imagery and women are in Mahavidya and related tantric materials. Theologically, the goddess, or Sakti, in one form or another is equal or superior to a male deity or principal, usually Siva. She is usually identified with the origin of the cosmos and is said to infuse it and contain it. Frequently in Mahadevi texts she empowers the male gods to create, maintain, and consume the creation, or she undertakes these functions herself.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>06 The Potentially Liberating Nature of Social Antimodels</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/tantric-divine-feminine/3_Concluding_Reflections/06_The_Potentially_Liberating_Nature_of_Social_Ant/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/tantric-divine-feminine/3_Concluding_Reflections/06_The_Potentially_Liberating_Nature_of_Social_Ant/</guid>
      <description>Finally, the question remains: Why would one wish to identify with, to actually become (in the logic of Tantra), a goddess such as Kali, Chinnamasta, Dhumavati, Bhairavl, or Matarigi, each of whom dramatically embodies marginal, polluting, or socially subversive qualities? These goddesses are frightening, dangerous, and loathsome. They often threaten social order. In their strong associations with death, violence, pollution, and despised marginal social roles, they call into question such normative social &amp;ldquo;goods&amp;rdquo; as worldly comfort, security, respect, and honor.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
