<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;7 Enlightenment and the Classical Culture of Possession on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/3_Classical_Literature/7_Enlightenment_and_the_Classical_Culture_of_Possession/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;7 Enlightenment and the Classical Culture of Possession on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/3_Classical_Literature/7_Enlightenment_and_the_Classical_Culture_of_Possession/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 Possession as Yoga Practice</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/3_Classical_Literature/7_Enlightenment_and_the_Classical_Culture_of_Possession/01_Possession_as_Yoga_Practice/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/3_Classical_Literature/7_Enlightenment_and_the_Classical_Culture_of_Possession/01_Possession_as_Yoga_Practice/</guid>
      <description>Possession is mentioned in the third adhyāya of Patañjali’s Yogasūtms (YS), the chapter dealing with extraordinary powers (vibhūti, siddhi) gained through the practice of yoga. YS 3.38 reads: “Due to loosening the cause of bondage and from full knowledge of [the mechanics of psychic] movement, entrance [āveśa] of one’s mind [citta] into another’s body [becomes possible]” (bandhakāraṇaśaithilyāt pracārasaṃvedimāc ca cinasya paraśarīrāveśaḥ).3 The primary commentator on the YS, Vyāsa, believes that the cause (kāmṇa) of bondage in the form of the repository of one’s accumulated actions (karmāśaya) is loosened by the power of samādhi.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>02 Possession and the Subtle Body in the Yogavāsiṣṭha</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/3_Classical_Literature/7_Enlightenment_and_the_Classical_Culture_of_Possession/02_Possession_and_the_Subtle_Body_in_the_Yogavsiha/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/3_Classical_Literature/7_Enlightenment_and_the_Classical_Culture_of_Possession/02_Possession_and_the_Subtle_Body_in_the_Yogavsiha/</guid>
      <description>The Yogavāsiṣṭha contains a passage (6.1.82) that is as detailed as Hemacandra’s on the process of possessing other bodies. This important ninth-century text in which yoga, Vedānta, and surreal transformation are central recounts stories told to Rāma as a child by Vasiṣṭha, his family’s guru. The passage in question is included in a lengthy tale of King Śikhidhvaja of Mālva and his devoted wife, Cūḍālā, who were supremely pious and dedicated to the pursuit of self-knowledge (ātmajñāna).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>03 Śaṇkara’s Possession of a Dead King</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/3_Classical_Literature/7_Enlightenment_and_the_Classical_Culture_of_Possession/03_shankaras_Possession_of_a_Dead_King/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/3_Classical_Literature/7_Enlightenment_and_the_Classical_Culture_of_Possession/03_shankaras_Possession_of_a_Dead_King/</guid>
      <description>It is important now to return to the story of Śaṇkara and the deceased king. This is told in varying degrees of detail in the hagiographies of Śaṇkara life. Two may be cited here: the Śaṇkaradigvijaya (ŚDV) of Mādhava-Vidyāraṇya and the Śrīśaṅkaravijaya (ŚV) of Anantānandagiri.19 The former is much more expansive on the events of his personal life, which is densely imbued with the miraculous, while the latter is both more concise and diffuse, focusing more closely on Śaṇkara’s travels and debates.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>04 Possession and the Body in the Brahmasūtras</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/3_Classical_Literature/7_Enlightenment_and_the_Classical_Culture_of_Possession/04_Possession_and_the_Body_in_the_BrahmasUtras/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/3_Classical_Literature/7_Enlightenment_and_the_Classical_Culture_of_Possession/04_Possession_and_the_Body_in_the_BrahmasUtras/</guid>
      <description>The final section of Bādarāyaṇa’s Brahmasūtras (BS) discusses the symptoms of enlightenment. One of the final sūtras in this section states that, just as the flame of a lamp “enters” (āveśaḥ) another wick, a liberated being can enter another body (pradīpavad āveśas tathā hi darśayati, BS 4.4.15). It will be of interest to examine the remarks of a few commentators on this sūtra. We first look at what is probably the oldest surviving commentary on the BS, that of Bhāskara, composed in the mid-seventh century, whose sectarian affiliation is unclear from this commentary.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>05 Possession in Indian and Tibetan Buddhism</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/3_Classical_Literature/7_Enlightenment_and_the_Classical_Culture_of_Possession/05_Possession_in_Indian_and_Tibetan_Buddhism/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/3_Classical_Literature/7_Enlightenment_and_the_Classical_Culture_of_Possession/05_Possession_in_Indian_and_Tibetan_Buddhism/</guid>
      <description>In spite of an official absence of an inherently existent self in Buddhism, personhood nonetheless persists, as discussed earlier. As Gombrich has remarked, “the anatta doctrine has no more affective immediacy with regard to the next life than with regard to this.”38 In practice, the person in Sinhala Buddhism, the topic of Gombrich’s appraisal, is as porous as any other in South Asia, as the work of Gombrich, Kapferer, and others testifies.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>06 Conclusions</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/3_Classical_Literature/7_Enlightenment_and_the_Classical_Culture_of_Possession/06_Conclusions/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/3_Classical_Literature/7_Enlightenment_and_the_Classical_Culture_of_Possession/06_Conclusions/</guid>
      <description>Despite the preceding discussions, it must be stated that possession was barely a blip on the philosophical screen in India. It was not problematized or thematized on its own merit, and when it was addressed at all it was out of necessity, because the authors of earlier texts mentioned it. When it was regarded categorically (as has always been the wont of Indian sastra), as it was in the Yogasūtras and Brahmasūtras, possession was assigned fuzzy ontological or soteriological characteristics rather than epistemological ones (perhaps Hemacandra and the Yogavāsiṣṭha aside).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>07 NOTES</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/3_Classical_Literature/7_Enlightenment_and_the_Classical_Culture_of_Possession/07_NOTES/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/3_Classical_Literature/7_Enlightenment_and_the_Classical_Culture_of_Possession/07_NOTES/</guid>
      <description>See Kelly 1998:173, and especially 188n6 on the problematic word Bewußtsein, probably better as “awareness” than “consciousness,” though Kelly himself has “reluctantly chosen the traditional term.” See my remarks in Chapter 1 on the use of the word “consciousness.” For the problems surrounding this, see Clarke 1997:112ff. Or, as Bloomfield writes, “penetration of one’s mind-stuff into the body of another” (1917:1). Cf. Caraka Saṃhitā, Śarīrasthānam 1.140, where āveśa is mentioned as one of the eight siddhis, and Bloomfield 1917:6, for other references.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
