<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;5 The Vedas and Upaniṣads on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/3_Classical_Literature/5_The_Vedas_and_Upaniads/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;5 The Vedas and Upaniṣads on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/3_Classical_Literature/5_The_Vedas_and_Upaniads/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 Embodiment and Disembodiment Among the Ṛṣis</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/3_Classical_Literature/5_The_Vedas_and_Upaniads/01_Embodiment_and_Disembodiment_Among_the_is/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/3_Classical_Literature/5_The_Vedas_and_Upaniads/01_Embodiment_and_Disembodiment_Among_the_is/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The vedic literature from the Ṛgveda (ṚV) to the classical Upaniṣads is the earliest source of information on possession in India. It is also among the most unambiguous. Because one of the principal arguments of this book is that there is a recognizable “tradition” of possession in India, it is necessary to say a few words about the early relationship between the folk and the classical as this bears greatly on any allegation of a tradition widely regarded as an experiential phenomenon with a popular discourse that largely bypasses ancient and classical literature. I say this in spite of all the evidence adduced in the following chapters, because most of these texts, or at least the passages cited in them, exist on the periphery of mainstream classical literature, by which I here mean śāstra.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02 Possession in the Early Vedic Literature</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/3_Classical_Literature/5_The_Vedas_and_Upaniads/02_Possession_in_the_Early_Vedic_Literature/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/3_Classical_Literature/5_The_Vedas_and_Upaniads/02_Possession_in_the_Early_Vedic_Literature/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The verbal root √viś, to enter, occurs 103 times in the Ṛgveda in various forms. Of these, 69 are used with the prefix . It is not necessary to examine each of these occurrences to conclude that in the ṚV forms of āviś are not used in the simple sense of entry, as a person through a door, but in a more abstract sense, beyond the normal physical contexts of entering a separate enclosed or semienclosed space.10 The root ā√viś in its many derivative forms occurs almost entirely in the sense of entities of different densities or substantialities penetrating and pervading one another.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03 Shape-Shifting and Possession</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/3_Classical_Literature/5_The_Vedas_and_Upaniads/03_Shape-Shifting_and_Possession/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/3_Classical_Literature/5_The_Vedas_and_Upaniads/03_Shape-Shifting_and_Possession/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Sāyaṇa understands the last quarter-verse of ṚV 10.136.2 differently, avoiding any suggestion of possession. He says: “[the munis] entered the deity’s own physical form” (devatāsvarūpaṃ prāviśan). This is slightly ambiguous, but he probably means here that the munis assumed or constructed a form of the deity rather than merged with a pre-existing divine body.47 The former is more likely because Sāyaṇa consistently avoids speaking of possession, while he readily acknowledges shape-shifting—which is in any case much in evidence in the vedic and post-vedic literature. This example demonstrates that shape-shifting was proximate to possession and perhaps indistinguishable from it in certain contexts, especially in the early history of Sanskrit literature when the vocabulary for the two was not fully differentiated. Although it is unwise to get too far ahead of ourselves, it may be useful to note here an example of this lexical differentiation. The much later Jain Pārśvanātha Caritra distinguishes between shape-shifting (rūpāntarakṛti) and entering another’s body (parakāyapraveśa).48 Another reason for arguing in favor of possession rather than shape-shifting in the case of the muni is that he is, unmistakably, an ascetic, and merging with or becoming possessed by a deity was more likely for such a figure than was shape-shifting, which signifies greater stakes in worldly pursuits than those that the muni appears to have.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04 In the Beginning, God Possessed Heaven and Earth</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/3_Classical_Literature/5_The_Vedas_and_Upaniads/04_In_the_Beginning_God_Possessed_Heaven_and_Earth/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/3_Classical_Literature/5_The_Vedas_and_Upaniads/04_In_the_Beginning_God_Possessed_Heaven_and_Earth/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Possession is, first and foremost, a quality of embodiment. It may be a uniquely configured embodiment or, under certain conditions, a viewpoint on embodiment. Embodiment is characterized in the Upaniṣads as primordial, archetypal: It happened in the beginning. In that beginning, bráhman, the eternal, absolute, unlimited power, was anthropomorphized, even humanized, by manifesting recognizable qualities such as desire and fear, as púruṣa, the first and supreme person. This neuter bráhman, with or without its masculine cloak as púruṣa, desired multiplicity, thus entered, embodied, and animated an equally primordial, if initially inert, materiality. The bráhman then divided its newly adopted body into male and female, then into all different types of sexually differentiated beings. This primordial embodiment and subsequent mixing and recombinant identities is at the basis of the Indian notions of multiple and polyvalent selves. This is a self that cannot be expressed except through its multiformity—and which is therefore not reducible except by recapturing its archetypal nature through philosophical understanding or spiritual exercise. Embodiment or animation, however, in its multiform complexity, is irreducible in and to its essences without a termination in the form of death, which returns the materiality of an embodied individual to its primordial quiescence and latency. Archetypal embodiment, then, is also archetypal possession, serving as a model for the flow and exchange of substances, substance codes, and essences, which affect other psychophysical organisms for the duration of their shared locus. However, even on the eventual (and inevitable) separation of substances, this flow and exchange to a great extent produces the unique identity of every embodied individual.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05 Transfer of Essence</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/3_Classical_Literature/5_The_Vedas_and_Upaniads/05_Transfer_of_Essence/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/3_Classical_Literature/5_The_Vedas_and_Upaniads/05_Transfer_of_Essence/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Related to possession and sometimes nearly indistinguishable from it, as we have seen in reviewing vedic passages on speech (vc) and sustenance (rjam), is a notion developed with considerable sophistication in the middle vedic texts and Upaniṣads. This notion may be labeled “transfer of essence.” This topic is vast and fraught with pitfalls, including proximity to early notions of karma (the pervading influence of the moral quality of one’s action on the individual as a whole),83 its overlap with the often-discussed epistemological strategy called bandhu or bandhuta, linkage of one phenomenon, entity, being, notion, or concept with another, based on phonological similarities, numerological equivalences, or other formal principles,84 and the subsequent invitation into the minefield of transactional models for human (and nonhuman) action. We can barely pause to deal with the first and second of these, but will gradually unfold the third, for which McKim Marriott and Stephanie Jamison have worked out effective models, albeit separately: Jamison did not consult Marriott’s work in constructing her transactional model of vedic sacrificial ritual in her book Sacrificed Wife/Sacrificer’s Wife.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>06 The Gandharva, the Apsaras, and the Vedic Body</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/3_Classical_Literature/5_The_Vedas_and_Upaniads/06_The_Gandharva_the_Apsaras_and_the_Vedic_Body/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/3_Classical_Literature/5_The_Vedas_and_Upaniads/06_The_Gandharva_the_Apsaras_and_the_Vedic_Body/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If a single “being” or “entity” may be specified in the Vedas as more deeply implicated in possession than any other, it is, with the exception of the human being, the gandharava. A great deal has been written about this mysterious being since A. Kuhn first addressed the subject in 1852.139 Although it is not my job here either to recount the history of scholarship on the subject or to offer my own definitive account, it may be mentioned that most of the research during the first century after Kuhn’s article appeared was dedicated to speculations on the etymology of the word and its cognates in Greek, particularly kentauros (centaur). Early generations of Indologists labored to identify the gandharva as a cloud spirit, the rising sun, Soma, the genius of the moon, the rainbow, a wind-spirit, a horse or ass, or a giant.140 These identifications were set aside, at least as unilateral interpretations, by A. B. Keith and O. H. de A. Wijesekera, who questioned the linguistic connection with Greek and noted both the incomplete vedic and other Indic evidence brought by previous scholars and uncertainty regarding the deep history of the kentauros.141 The most sensible writing on gandharva to date remains that of Wijesekera,142 who sees connections of the gandharva with all the suggested “meanings” at different points, but none, he demonstrates, are valid as exclusive interpretations. As with most important terms, its meaning appears to have shifted slightly from the ṚV to the Upaniṣads and the Pali canon.143&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
