<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;4 Notes on Regional Languages and Models of Possession on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/2_Modernity_and_the_Languages_of_Possession/4_Notes_on_Regional_Languages_and_Models_of_Possession/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;4 Notes on Regional Languages and Models of Possession on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/2_Modernity_and_the_Languages_of_Possession/4_Notes_on_Regional_Languages_and_Models_of_Possession/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 Hindi</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/2_Modernity_and_the_Languages_of_Possession/4_Notes_on_Regional_Languages_and_Models_of_Possession/01_Hindi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/2_Modernity_and_the_Languages_of_Possession/4_Notes_on_Regional_Languages_and_Models_of_Possession/01_Hindi/</guid>
      <description>Variants of the Sanskrit āveśa and grahaṇa appear widely distributed in regional Indian languages. The unexpectedly late semantic conflation of √gṛh with ā√viś in Sanskrit is seen in several Middle Indo-Aryan languages contemporaneous with such usages in Sanskrit texts from the last few centuries of the first millennium C.E., which in turn set the stage for the all but interchangeable use of these verbs in New Indo-Aryan. In Hindi, āveś in the early Sanskritic senses of pervasion, absorption, and entry has been completely superseded.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>02 Urdu: Hanumān’s Court at Bālājī</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/2_Modernity_and_the_Languages_of_Possession/4_Notes_on_Regional_Languages_and_Models_of_Possession/02_Urdu_hanumAns_Court_at_BAlAjI/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/2_Modernity_and_the_Languages_of_Possession/4_Notes_on_Regional_Languages_and_Models_of_Possession/02_Urdu_hanumAns_Court_at_BAlAjI/</guid>
      <description>One of the most striking models of possession and exorcism, in which bhūt-prets play a significant role, occurs in the environs of the Bālājī temple in Mehndipur, Rajasthan, as well as at several other spirit healing centers in India.14 Most of the clients at Bālājī are Hindu, from Hindi-speaking areas of India.15 Yet in a slight acknowledgment to the once-dominant Indo-Islamic culture, the clinical model is replete with Urdu terms. These terms are drawn from the British colonial legal system, which adopted the Persian-Urdu language of the Islamic legal system of the Mughals.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>03 Bengali</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/2_Modernity_and_the_Languages_of_Possession/4_Notes_on_Regional_Languages_and_Models_of_Possession/03_Bengali/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/2_Modernity_and_the_Languages_of_Possession/4_Notes_on_Regional_Languages_and_Models_of_Possession/03_Bengali/</guid>
      <description>In Bengali, √bharā (to fill) is attested in the sense of possession, in addition to its expected etymological usage.49 The nominal form bhar means “weight,” hence the two meanings conflate: being filled with or bearing the weight of a spirit or deity. The extended sense of possession as intense emotional engagement is also found in Bengali: for example, karuṇā-bharala (filled with [i.e., immersed in] compassion).50
Deborah Bhattacharyya, based in Bengal, examines possession and other behavior that “specifically refers to the collapse of the boundaries between the inside and outside of the individual”51 and are treatable through folk psychiatry.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>04 Marathi</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/2_Modernity_and_the_Languages_of_Possession/4_Notes_on_Regional_Languages_and_Models_of_Possession/04_Marathi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/2_Modernity_and_the_Languages_of_Possession/4_Notes_on_Regional_Languages_and_Models_of_Possession/04_Marathi/</guid>
      <description>In Marathi āveś carries the same semantic range as it does in Hindi. J. T. Molesworth notes many compounds borrowed from or modeled on Sanskrit, probably limited to Marathi literature (they are less likely in speech, even among upper castes): kāmāveś (absorption or immersion in love), krodhāveś (anger), lobhāveś (greed), śauryāveś (heroism), piśācāveś (evil or evil spirits), harṣāveś (laughter), śokāveś (grief), īrṣyāveś (envy), kṛpāveś (a state of grace), and mohāveś (delusion).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>05 Possession and Its Discourse in the Himalayas</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/2_Modernity_and_the_Languages_of_Possession/4_Notes_on_Regional_Languages_and_Models_of_Possession/05_Possession_and_Its_Discourse_in_the_Himalayas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/2_Modernity_and_the_Languages_of_Possession/4_Notes_on_Regional_Languages_and_Models_of_Possession/05_Possession_and_Its_Discourse_in_the_Himalayas/</guid>
      <description>Oracular possession in the Himalayas is very common. Daniela Berti reports that in Himachal Pradesh nearly all the village temples in Kulu district have mediums who are possessed by the main temple deity.74 The situation appears to be little different elsewhere across the Himalayas, from Ladakh to eastern Nepal. This is equally the case in Tibet, as Per-Arne Berglie notes: “Even more than the local lama … the dpa’ bo [spirit medium, lit.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>06 Tamil and Simhala</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/2_Modernity_and_the_Languages_of_Possession/4_Notes_on_Regional_Languages_and_Models_of_Possession/06_Tamil_and_Simhala/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/2_Modernity_and_the_Languages_of_Possession/4_Notes_on_Regional_Languages_and_Models_of_Possession/06_Tamil_and_Simhala/</guid>
      <description>In Tamil and Simhala,99 āvēcam (&amp;lt; Skt. āveśam) is perhaps the most common word for spirit or deity possession. Like other South Asian languages, Simhala betrays a linguistic nexus between possession and emotion: the substantive ävitu (possessed [by an evil spirit], mad) is related to the verb ävissenavā (to be angry).100 Obeyesekere, however, recognizes a much greater frequency in colloquial Simhala of ārūḍe (&amp;lt; Skt. ārūḍha [mounted]), divine possession, “in which the magnetism of the god infuses and suffuses the body.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>07 Malayalam</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/2_Modernity_and_the_Languages_of_Possession/4_Notes_on_Regional_Languages_and_Models_of_Possession/07_Malayalam/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/2_Modernity_and_the_Languages_of_Possession/4_Notes_on_Regional_Languages_and_Models_of_Possession/07_Malayalam/</guid>
      <description>Scholarship on possession in Kerala is now emerging, thanks in large part to the work of Sarah Caldwell, Rich Freeman, and Gilles Tarabout. Caldwell explores oracular possession among worshippers of Kāḷi. She writes about the performance of mudiyettu (divine offering),154 in which the goddess Kāḷi battles the demon Dārika. Caldwell notes that Kāḷi “will enter the actor’s body and consciousness as a great inner heat”155 and reports an informant saying, “We fix the picture of Bhagavati in our mind, and her supernatural power (caitanyam) enters our body.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>08 Tulu and Irula</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/2_Modernity_and_the_Languages_of_Possession/4_Notes_on_Regional_Languages_and_Models_of_Possession/08_Tulu_and_Irula/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/2_Modernity_and_the_Languages_of_Possession/4_Notes_on_Regional_Languages_and_Models_of_Possession/08_Tulu_and_Irula/</guid>
      <description>The recent major studies by Honko and Brückner of possession cults and epic performance in Tulunad in South Kanara District of Karnataka represent culminations in a long scholarly interest extending back to the Abbé Dubois in the early nineteenth century.166 The spirits invoked in the performance of the Siri epic are benevolent, which Claus points out “may be hard to believe” given “the incredible discomfort and agony evident in the bodily contortions and facial grimaces of the possessed young women.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>09 Assam and Possession at Kamakhya</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/2_Modernity_and_the_Languages_of_Possession/4_Notes_on_Regional_Languages_and_Models_of_Possession/09_Assam_and_Possession_at_Kamakhya/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/2_Modernity_and_the_Languages_of_Possession/4_Notes_on_Regional_Languages_and_Models_of_Possession/09_Assam_and_Possession_at_Kamakhya/</guid>
      <description>In view of its proximity to Bengal, Nepal, Tibet, and the rest of northeastern India, the presence of a large (and largely unexplored) indigenous Tantric literature, and a predominance of worshippers of exotic goddesses, Assam might be expected to evince a substantial amount of possession. I have no doubt that this is the case. However, this has been almost entirely unresearched. What little is documented, however, is intriguing and requires a brief explanation that contextualizes this absence in terms of the political and religious exigencies of colonial (or colonized) Assam.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>10 Exorcists, Oracles, and Healers</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/2_Modernity_and_the_Languages_of_Possession/4_Notes_on_Regional_Languages_and_Models_of_Possession/10_Exorcists_Oracles_and_Healers/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/2_Modernity_and_the_Languages_of_Possession/4_Notes_on_Regional_Languages_and_Models_of_Possession/10_Exorcists_Oracles_and_Healers/</guid>
      <description>In spite of the efforts of Meyer, Erndl, Bhattacharyya, Stanley, McDaniel, Srinivas, Freeman, Claus, Brückner, Macdonald, Pakaslahti, Gellner, Vogt, Wadley, Caldwell, Inglis, Wirz, and a few others to highlight the importance of local terminology, many ethnographers fail to provide not only the vocabulary for possession but also the specialized words or terms for the person possessed. Let us now briefly look at some of the vocabulary in Hindi, Urdu, Gujarati, Bengali, Marathi, Nepali, Tulu, Tamil, Malayalam, Simhala, and the language of the Maldive islands.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>11 Reflections on “Folk” and “Classical” in South Asia</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/2_Modernity_and_the_Languages_of_Possession/4_Notes_on_Regional_Languages_and_Models_of_Possession/11_Reflections_on_Folk_and_Classical_in_South_Asia/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/2_Modernity_and_the_Languages_of_Possession/4_Notes_on_Regional_Languages_and_Models_of_Possession/11_Reflections_on_Folk_and_Classical_in_South_Asia/</guid>
      <description>From the foregoing discussion of lexemes and terms in many South Asian languages, one conclusion is unavoidable: that with a few notable exceptions the expansion of the lexicon for possession—and, we might cautiously presume, many of the ideologies behind this expansion—was to a great extent derived from Sanskrit and Sanskritic culture, after which it became diversified and adapted into regional languages. Despite this conclusion, the ethnographies highlight the non-brahmanical, non-Sanskritic dimensions of possession and the rejection of clerical authority in favor of a nonmediated transcendence or, at most, a transcendence that is sanctioned—and, therefore, in a sense mediated—by the dynamics of the local culture.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>12 NOTES</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/2_Modernity_and_the_Languages_of_Possession/4_Notes_on_Regional_Languages_and_Models_of_Possession/12_NOTES/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/meta/AveshaH/articles/self-possessed/2_Modernity_and_the_Languages_of_Possession/4_Notes_on_Regional_Languages_and_Models_of_Possession/12_NOTES/</guid>
      <description>This is borne out in a study of the bibliographies in an issue of Puruṣārtha devoted to possession; cf. Assayag and Tarabout 1999. The issue contains thirteen articles (excluding the prologue and epilogue), of which five are on Kerala, two each on Himachal Pradesh and Karnataka (one of these on Tulunad), and one each on Rajasthan, Tamilnadu, Nepal, and Kashmir. The brief article on Kashmir is by André Padoux and is the only one in the collection devoted to possession in the premodern period (cf.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
