<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;13 VILLAGE GODDESSES on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/13_VILLAGE_GODDESSES/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;13 VILLAGE GODDESSES on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/13_VILLAGE_GODDESSES/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 THE LOCAL ROOTEDNESS OF THE VILLAGE GODDESSES</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/13_VILLAGE_GODDESSES/01_THE_LOCAL_ROOTEDNESS_OF_THE_VILLAGE_GODDESSES/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/13_VILLAGE_GODDESSES/01_THE_LOCAL_ROOTEDNESS_OF_THE_VILLAGE_GODDESSES/</guid>
      <description>One of the most persistent themes found in the myth, cult, and worship of village goddesses is their being rooted in specific, local villages. The village is the special place of the deity. She is the mother or mistress of the village, as suggested by a name popular in the South, Amman, meaning “mother, mistress, or lady.”8 Although it is common to speak of the goddess of such-and-such a village, it is probably more accurate to think of the village as belonging to the goddess.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>02 MYTHOLOGICAL THEMES</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/13_VILLAGE_GODDESSES/02_MYTHOLOGICAL_THEMES/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/13_VILLAGE_GODDESSES/02_MYTHOLOGICAL_THEMES/</guid>
      <description>An important theme in myths concerning the origin of village goddesses is the injustice done to women by men. Two of the best-known myths concerning the origin of the popular goddess Māriyamman in South India include this motif. In one version a young Brahman girl is courted by and eventually married to an untouchable who has disguised himself as a Brahman. On discovering the trick, the woman becomes furious and kills herself.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>03 FESTIVALS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/13_VILLAGE_GODDESSES/03_FESTIVALS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/13_VILLAGE_GODDESSES/03_FESTIVALS/</guid>
      <description>Although the village goddesses are typically characterized as protecting, ordering, and instituting village civilization, they also have a reputation for behaving in disruptive, violent, and dangerous ways, particularly during festivals held in their honor. This is particularly clear during festivals in honor of village goddesses during epidemics. Many village goddesses are specifically associated with diseases, and during epidemics they may play several apparently contradictory roles. They may defend the village from the disease, which may be identified with invading demons.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>04 DEATH, DISEASE, AND AMBIVALENCE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/13_VILLAGE_GODDESSES/04_DEATH_DISEASE_AND_AMBIVALENCE/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/13_VILLAGE_GODDESSES/04_DEATH_DISEASE_AND_AMBIVALENCE/</guid>
      <description>The close association of village, local, and regional goddesses with disease, epidemic, disaster, and sudden death deserves further comment. Because the village goddesses institute, nourish, and protect villages, it would make sense to interpret their myth, cult, and worship as primarily revolving around their periodic struggles with invading demons who bring sickness, death, and disruption to the villages. Yet given the overwhelming association of these goddesses with the diseases themselves, given the common identification of epidemics with the goddesses’ “grace,” it would make sense to interpret their worship as primarily the attempt to propitiate them so that they will withhold their wrath from their people.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
