<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;11 TĀRĀ, CHINNAMASTĀ, AND THE MAHĀVIDYĀS on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/11_tArA_ChinnamastA_AND_THE_mahAvidyAs/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;11 TĀRĀ, CHINNAMASTĀ, AND THE MAHĀVIDYĀS on देवेषु विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/11_tArA_ChinnamastA_AND_THE_mahAvidyAs/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 THE MAHĀVIDYĀS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/11_tArA_ChinnamastA_AND_THE_mahAvidyAs/01_THE_mahAvidyAs/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/11_tArA_ChinnamastA_AND_THE_mahAvidyAs/01_THE_mahAvidyAs/</guid>
      <description>The Mahāvidyās (great revelations or manifestations) are a group of ten goddesses who are mentioned rather late in the Hindu literary tradition. Although some of the goddesses in this group are individually important and date back to a much earlier time (Kalī, for example), the group as a whole seems to be a medieval iconographic and mythological expression of an aspect of Mahādevī theology. An important point in Mahādevī theology is the Devī’s tendency to display or manifest herself in a great variety of forms.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>02 TĀRĀ</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/11_tArA_ChinnamastA_AND_THE_mahAvidyAs/02_tArA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/11_tArA_ChinnamastA_AND_THE_mahAvidyAs/02_tArA/</guid>
      <description>The goddess Tārā does not figure prominently in the Hindu tradition. Her place in Tibetan Buddhism, however, is central and quite ancient. Her appearance in the list of the Mahāvidyās can probably be explained, at least in part, by the religious communication that existed for centuries between Tibet and Bengal (where the texts that mention the Mahāvidyās were written). Many important Buddhist missionaries to Tibet came from Bengal, and Buddhists continued to be mentioned in Bengali texts until the sixteenth century.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>03 CHINNAMASTĀ</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/11_tArA_ChinnamastA_AND_THE_mahAvidyAs/03_ChinnamastA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/devaH/AryaH/hindukaH/meta/articles/kinsley/hindu-godesses/11_tArA_ChinnamastA_AND_THE_mahAvidyAs/03_ChinnamastA/</guid>
      <description>Chinnamastā, like Tārā, is also popular in Tantric and Tibetan Buddhism. In Buddhism she is known as Vajrayoginī. The Buddhist Tantric text, the Sadhanamālā, describes her as follows:
Vajrayoginī . . . carries in her left hand her own head severed by herself with her own Kartri held in her right hand. Her left hand is raised upwards while the right is placed below. She is nude, and her right leg is stretched while the left is bent down.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
